<Group id="partitions">
<title>Restrict Partition Mount Options</title>
<description>System partitions can be mounted with certain options
that limit what files on those partitions can do. These options
are set in the <tt>/etc/fstab</tt> configuration file, and can be
used to make certain types of malicious behavior more difficult.</description>

<Value id="var_removable_partition" type="string" operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>Removable Partition</title>
<description>This value is used by the checks mount_option_nodev_removable_partitions, mount_option_noexec_removable_partitions, 
and mount_option_nosuid_removable_partitions to ensure that the correct mount options are set on partitions mounted from
removable media such as CD-ROMs, USB keys, and floppy drives. This value should be modified to reflect any removable
partitions that are required on the local system.</description>
<value selector="dev_cdrom">/dev/cdrom</value>
</Value>

<Rule id="mount_option_nodev_removable_partitions">
<title>Add nodev Option to Removable Media Partitions</title>
<description>The <tt>nodev</tt> mount option prevents files from being
interpreted as character or block devices. 
Legitimate character and block devices should exist only in
the <tt>/dev</tt> directory on the root partition or within chroot
jails built for system services. 
<mount-desc-macro option="nodev" part="any removable media partitions" />
</description>
<rationale> The only legitimate location for device files is the <tt>/dev</tt> directory
located on the root partition.  An exception to this is chroot jails, and it is
not advised to set <tt>nodev</tt> on partitions which contain their root
filesystems.  </rationale>
<ident stig="GEN002430" />
<oval id="mount_option_nodev_removable_partitions" value="var_removable_partition" />
<ref nist="ECSC-1" disa="366" />
</Rule>

<!-- investigate: this is like obsoleted by gvfs/DeviceKit-based mounting now -->
<Rule id="mount_option_nosuid_removable_partitions">
<title>Add nosuid Option to Removable Media Partitions</title>
<description>The <tt>nosuid</tt> mount option prevents set-user-identifier (suid)
and set-group-identifier (sgid) permissions from taking effect. These permissions
allow users to execute binaries with the same permissions as the owner and group
of the file respectively. Users should not be allowed to introduce suid and guid
files into the system via partitions mounted from removeable media.
<mount-desc-macro option="nosuid" part="any removable media partitions" />
</description>
<rationale>The presence of suid and sgid executables should be tightly controlled. Allowing
users to introduce suid or sgid binaries from partitions mounted off of
removable media would allow them to introduce their own highly-privileged programs.</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN002420" />
<oval id="mount_option_nosuid_removable_partitions" value="var_removable_partition" />
<ref nist="ECLP-1" disa="225" />
</Rule>


</Group>
