<Group id="intro" prodtype="all">
<title>Introduction</title>
<description>
<!-- purpose and scope of guidance -->
The purpose of this guidance is to provide security configuration
recommendations and baselines for the <product-name-macro/> operating
system. Recommended settings for the basic operating system are provided,
as well as for many network services that the system can provide to other systems.
<!-- audience -->The guide is intended for system administrators. Readers are assumed to
possess basic system administration skills for Unix-like systems, as well
as some familiarity with the product's documentation and administration
conventions. Some instructions within this guide are complex.
All directions should be followed completely and with understanding of
their effects in order to avoid serious adverse effects on the system
and its security.
</description>

<Group id="general-principles" prodtype="all">
<title>General Principles</title>
<description>
The following general principles motivate much of the advice in this
guide and should also influence any configuration decisions that are
not explicitly covered.
</description>

<Group id="principle-encrypt-transmitted-data" prodtype="all">
<title>Encrypt Transmitted Data Whenever Possible</title>
<description>
Data transmitted over a network, whether wired or wireless, is susceptible
to passive monitoring. Whenever practical solutions for encrypting
such data exist, they should be applied. Even if data is expected to
be transmitted only over a local network, it should still be encrypted.
Encrypting authentication data, such as passwords, is particularly
important. Networks of <product-name-macro/> machines can and should be configured
so that no unencrypted authentication data is ever transmitted between
machines.
</description>
</Group>


<Group id="principle-minimize-software" prodtype="all">
<title>Minimize Software to Minimize Vulnerability</title>
<description>
The simplest way to avoid vulnerabilities in software is to avoid
installing that software. On <product-name-macro/>,
<os-type-macro type="rhel7,rhel6,rhel5,fedora,opensuse,suse11,suse12,osp7,eap5,fuse6,wrlinux">the RPM Package Manager (originally Red Hat
Package Manager, abbreviated RPM)</os-type-macro><os-type-macro type="debian">
the Package Manager (originally
<weblink-macro link="https://www.debian.org/doc/manuals/debian-faq/ch-pkgtools.en.html" text="apt" />)</os-type-macro>
allows for careful management of
the set of software packages installed on a system. Installed software
contributes to system vulnerability in several ways. Packages that
include setuid programs may provide local attackers a potential path to
privilege escalation. Packages that include network services may give
this opportunity to network-based attackers. Packages that include
programs which are predictably executed by local users (e.g. after
graphical login) may provide opportunities for trojan horses or other
attack code to be run undetected. The number of software packages
installed on a system can almost always be significantly pruned to include
only the software for which there is an environmental or operational need.
</description>
</Group>

<Group id="principle-separate-servers" prodtype="all">
<title>Run Different Network Services on Separate Systems</title>
<description>
Whenever possible, a server should be dedicated to serving exactly one
network service. This limits the number of other services that can
be compromised in the event that an attacker is able to successfully
exploit a software flaw in one network service.
</description>
</Group>

<Group id="principle-use-security-tools" prodtype="all">
<title>Configure Security Tools to Improve System Robustness</title>
<description>
Several tools exist which can be effectively used to improve a system's
resistance to and detection of unknown attacks. These tools can improve
robustness against attack at the cost of relatively little configuration
effort. In particular, this guide recommends and discusses the use of
host-based firewalling, SELinux for protection against
vulnerable services, and a logging and auditing infrastructure for
detection of problems.
</description>
</Group>

<Group id="principle-least-privilege" prodtype="all">
<title>Least Privilege</title>
<description>
Grant the least privilege necessary for user accounts and software to perform tasks.
For example, <tt>sudo</tt> can be implemented to limit authorization to super user
accounts on the system only to designated personnel. Another example is to limit
logins on server systems to only those administrators who need to log into them in
order to perform administration tasks. Using SELinux also follows the principle of
least privilege: SELinux policy can confine software to perform only actions on the
system that are specifically allowed. This can be far more restrictive than the
actions permissible by the traditional Unix permissions model.
</description>
</Group>

</Group>


<Group id="how-to-use" prodtype="all">
<title>How to Use This Guide</title>
<description>
Readers should heed the following points when using the guide.
</description>


<Group id="intro-read-sections-completely" prodtype="all">
<title>Read Sections Completely and in Order</title>
<description>
Each section may build on information and recommendations discussed in
prior sections. Each section should be read and understood completely;
instructions should never be blindly applied. Relevant discussion may
occur after instructions for an action. 
</description>
</Group>


<Group id="intro-test-non-production" prodtype="all">
<title>Test in Non-Production Environment</title>
<description>
This guidance should always be tested in a non-production environment
before deployment. This test environment should simulate the setup in
which the system will be deployed as closely as possible.
</description>
</Group>

<Group id="intro-root-shell-assumed" prodtype="all">
<title>Root Shell Environment Assumed</title>
<description>
Most of the actions listed in this document are written with the
assumption that they will be executed by the root user running the
<tt>/bin/bash</tt> shell. Commands preceded with a hash mark (#)
assume that the administrator will execute the commands as root, i.e.
apply the command via <tt>sudo</tt> whenever possible, or use
<tt>su</tt> to gain root privileges if <tt>sudo</tt> cannot be
used. Commands which can be executed as a non-root user are are preceded
by a dollar sign ($) prompt.
</description>
</Group>

<Group id="intro-formatting-conventions" prodtype="all">
<title>Formatting Conventions</title>
<description>
Commands intended for shell execution, as well as configuration file text,
are featured in a <tt>monospace font</tt>. <i>Italics</i> are used
to indicate instances where the system administrator must substitute
the appropriate information into a command or configuration file.
</description>
</Group>

<Group id="intro-reboot-required" prodtype="all">
<title>Reboot Required</title>
<description>
A system reboot is implicitly required after some actions in order to
complete the reconfiguration of the system. In many cases, the changes
will not take effect until a reboot is performed. In order to ensure
that changes are applied properly and to test functionality, always
reboot the system after applying a set of recommendations from this guide.
</description>
</Group>

</Group>

</Group>
