<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-User_Guide-Intro">
	<title>Introduction to SSG </title>
	<section id="sect-User_Guide-Intro-Proj_History">
		<title>Project Description</title>
		<para> The SCAP Security Guide (SSG) project delivers security guidance, baselines and associated
            validation mechanisms utilizing the Security Content Automation Protocol (SCAP). SSG
            currently provides content for Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6 (RHEL6) and JBoss Enterprise
            Application Server 5 (JBoss EAP5).</para>
        <para>In addition to hardening advice, SSG links back to compliance requirements in order to
            eease deployment activities, such as certification and accreditation. These include
            requirements in the U.S. Government (Federal, Defense, and Intelligence Community) as
            well as of the financial services and health care industries. For example, high-level
            and widely-accepted policies such as NIST 80-53 provide prose stating that System
            Administrators must audit "privileged user actions," but do not define what "privileged
            actions" are. The SSG bridges the gap between generalized policy requirements and
            specific implementation guidance, in SCAP formats to support automation whenever
            possible.</para>
        <para>The project homepage is <ulink url="https://www.open-scap.org/security-policies/scap-security-guide"
                >https://www.open-scap.org/security-policies/scap-security-guide</ulink>.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-User_Guide-Intro-Collaboration">
		<title>Government/Industry Collaboration</title>
       <informaltable frame='none'>
            <tgroup cols='2'>
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="c_logos" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="c_text" colwidth="1.3*"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <inlinegraphic fileref="images/logos-400x400-nsa-300x300.jpg"/>
                        </entry>
                        <entry> The <ulink url="http://www.nsa.gov/">National Security
                                Agency</ulink>'s <ulink url="https://www.iad.gov/iad/index.cfm"
                                >Information Assurance Directorate</ulink> (NSA IAD) is
                            presidentially mandated to protect Confidential, Secret and Top Secret
                            information that could reasonably be expected to cause damage to U.S.
                            National Security. As part of this mission, NSA develops and distributes
                            configuration guidance for operating systems. These guides are currently
                            being used throughout the U.S. government and by numerous entities as a
                            security baseline for their systems. The SCAP Security Guide project
                            serves as NSA's upstream source for <ulink
                                url="http://www.nsa.gov/ia/mitigation_guidance/security_configuration_guides/operating_systems.shtml#linux2"
                                >Red Hat Enterprise Linux operating system guidance</ulink>. </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row><entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/logos-400x400-disa-300x300.jpg"
                            /></entry><entry>The <ulink
                                url="http://www.disa.mil/About/Our-Organization-Structure/OD-Field-Office/Field-Security-Operations"
                                >U.S. Defense Information Systems Agency, Field Security
                                Operations</ulink> (DISA FSO) authors hardening guidance known as
                            Security Technical Implementation Guides (<ulink
                                url="http://iase.disa.mil/stigs/index.html">STIGs</ulink>). These
                            documents, used throughout the U.S. Military to harden systems,
                            establish formal security compliance baselines. The SCAP Security Guide
                            project serves as the usptream development source for <ulink
                                url="http://iase.disa.mil/stigs/os/unix-linux/Pages/red-hat.aspx">Red Hat STIG
                                content</ulink> and helps DISA FSO move towards their business
                            objective of utilizing SCAP-based formates to automate security
                            compliance across U.S. Military organizations.</entry></row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><inlinegraphic
                                fileref="images/logos-400x400-nist-300x300.jpg"/></entry>
                        <entry>NIST publishes 'National Checklists' for software, which <ulink
                                url="http://web.nvd.nist.gov/view/ncp/repository">as defined
                            directly by NIST</ulink>:
                            <para><quote>The National Checklist Program (NCP),
                                defined by the <ulink
                                    url="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#SP-800-70-Rev.%202"
                                    >NIST SP 800-70 Rev. 2</ulink>, is the U.S. Government
                                repositiory of publicly available securiyy checklists (or
                                benchmarks) that provide detailed low level guidance on setting the
                                security configuration of operating systems and applications. NCP is
                                migrating its repository of checklists to conform to the Security
                                Content Automation Protocol (SCAP).</quote></para>
                            <para>The SCAP Security
                                Guide project serves as the upstream repository for Red Hat related
                                checklists, such as the <ulink
                                    url="http://web.nvd.nist.gov/view/ncp/repository/checklistDetail?id=430"
                                    >JBoss Enterprise Application Platform 5 (JBoss EAP5)</ulink>
                                baseline.</para></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
	</section>

</chapter>

