<Group id="dns">
<title>DNS Server</title>
<description>Most organizations have an operational need to run at
least one nameserver. However, there are many common attacks
involving DNS server software, and this server software should
be disabled on any system
on which it is not needed.</description>

<Group id="disabling_dns_server">
<title>Disable DNS Server</title>
<description>
DNS software should be disabled on any systems which does not
need to be a nameserver. Note that the BIND DNS server software is
not installed on Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 by default. The remainder of this section
discusses secure configuration of systems which must be
nameservers.
</description>

<Rule id="service_named_disabled" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Disable DNS Server</title>
<description>
<systemd-service-macro enable="false" service="named" />
</description>
<ocil><systemd-check-macro enable="false" service="named" /></ocil>
<rationale>
All network services involve some risk of compromise due to
implementation flaws and should be disabled if possible.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80325-4" />
<oval id="service_named_disabled" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-7" disa="366"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_bind_removed" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Uninstall bind Package</title>
<description>To remove the <tt>bind</tt> package, which contains the
<tt>named</tt> service, run the following command:
<pre>$ sudo yum erase bind</pre>
</description>
<ocil><package-check-macro package="bind" /> </ocil>
<rationale>
If there is no need to make DNS server software available,
removing it provides a safeguard against its activation.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80326-2" />
<oval id="package_bind_removed" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-7" disa="366" cis="3.9" />
</Rule>

</Group> <!--<Group id="disabling_dns_server">-->

<Group id="dns_server_isolation">
<title>Isolate DNS from Other Services</title>
<description>This section discusses mechanisms for preventing the DNS server
from interfering with other services. This is done both to protect the
remainder of the network should a nameserver be compromised, and to make direct
attacks on nameservers more difficult.</description>

<Group id="dns_server_dedicated">
<title>Run DNS Software on Dedicated Servers</title> <description>Since DNS is
a high-risk service which must frequently be made available to the entire
Internet, it is strongly recommended that no other services be offered by
systems which act as organizational DNS servers.</description>
</Group>

<Group id="dns_server_chroot">
<title>Run DNS Software in a chroot Jail</title>
<description>Install the <tt>bind-chroot</tt> package:
<pre>$ sudo yum install bind-chroot</pre>
Place a valid named.conf file inside the chroot jail:
<pre>$ sudo cp /etc/named.conf /var/named/chroot/etc/named.conf
$ sudo chown root:root /var/named/chroot/etc/named.conf
$ sudo chmod 644 /var/named/chroot/etc/named.conf</pre>
Create and populate an appropriate zone directory within the jail, based on the
options directive. If your <tt>named.conf</tt> includes:
<pre>options {
directory "/path/to/DIRNAME ";
...
}</pre>
then copy that directory and its contents from the original zone directory:
<pre>$ sudo cp -r /path/to/DIRNAME /var/named/chroot/DIRNAME</pre>
Add or correct the following line within <tt>/etc/sysconfig/named</tt>:
<pre>ROOTDIR=/var/named/chroot</pre>
</description>
<rationale>Chroot jails are not foolproof. However, they serve to make it more
difficult for a compromised program to be used to attack the entire host. They
do this by restricting a program's ability to traverse the directory upward, so
that files outside the jail are not visible to the chrooted process. Since RHEL
supports a standard mechanism for placing BIND in a chroot jail, you should
take advantage of this feature.</rationale>
<warning category="general">If you are running BIND in a chroot jail, then you
should use the jailed <tt>named.conf</tt> as the primary nameserver
configuration file. That is, when this guide recommends editing
<tt>/etc/named.conf</tt>, you should instead edit
<tt>/var/named/chroot/etc/named.conf</tt>.
</warning>
</Group>


</Group>

<Group id="dns_server_protection">
<title>Protect DNS Data from Tampering or Attack</title>
<description>This section discusses DNS configuration options which make it
more difficult for attackers to gain access to private DNS data or to modify
DNS data.</description>

<Group id="dns_server_separate_internal_external">
<title>Run Separate DNS Servers for External and Internal Queries</title>
<description>Is it possible to run external and internal nameservers on
separate systems? If so, follow the configuration guidance in this section. On
the external nameserver, edit <tt>/etc/named.conf</tt> to add or correct the
following directives:
<pre>options {
  allow-query { any; };
  recursion no;
  ...
};
zone "example.com " IN {
  ...
};</pre>
On the internal nameserver, edit <tt>/etc/named.conf</tt>. Add or correct the
following directives, where SUBNET is the numerical IP representation of your
organization in the form xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx/xx:
<pre>acl internal {
  SUBNET ;
  localhost;
};
options {
  allow-query { internal; };
  ...
};
zone "internal.example.com " IN {
  ...
};</pre>
</description>
<rationale>Enterprise nameservers generally serve two functions. One is to
provide public information about the systems in a domain for the benefit of
outside users who wish to contact those systems, for instance in order to send
mail to users in the enterprise, or to visit the enterprise's external web
page. The other is to provide nameservice to client systems within the
enterprise. Client systems require both private information about enterprise
systems (which may be different from the public information served to the rest
of the world) and public information about systems outside the enterprise,
which is used to send mail or visit websites outside of the organization.
<br />
In order to provide the public nameservice function, it is necessary to share
data with untrusted systems which request it - otherwise, the enterprise
cannot be conveniently contacted by outside users. However, internal data
should be protected from disclosure, and serving irrelevant public name queries
for outside domains leaves the DNS server open to cache poisoning and other
attacks. Therefore, local network nameservice functions should not be provided
to untrusted systems.
<br />
Separate systems should be used to fill these two functions whenever possible.
</rationale>

</Group>

<Group id="dns_server_partition_with_views">
<title>Use Views to Partition External and Internal Information</title>
<description>If it is not possible to run external and internal nameservers on
separate physical systems, run BIND9 and simulate this feature using views.
Edit <tt>/etc/named.conf</tt>. Add or correct the following directives (where
SUBNET is the numerical IP representation of your organization in the form
xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx/xx):
<pre>acl internal {
  SUBNET ;
  localhost;
};
view "internal-view" {
  match-clients { internal; };
  zone "." IN {
    type hint;
    file "db.cache";
  };
  zone "internal.example.com " IN {
    ...
  };
};

view "external-view" {
  match-clients { any; };
  recursion no;
  zone "example.com " IN {
    ...
  };
};</pre>
</description>
<rationale>The view feature is provided by BIND9 as a way to allow a single
nameserver to make different sets of data available to different sets of
clients. If possible, it is always better to run external and internal
nameservers on separate systems, so that even complete compromise of the
external server cannot be used to obtain internal data or confuse internal DNS
clients. However, this is not always feasible, and use of a feature like views
is preferable to leaving internal DNS data entirely unprotected.</rationale>
<warning category="general">As shown in the example, database files which are
required for recursion, such as the root hints file, must be available to any
clients which are allowed to make recursive queries. Under typical
circumstances, this includes only the internal clients which are allowed to use
this server as a general-purpose nameserver.</warning>
</Group>

<Rule id="dns_server_disable_zone_transfers" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Disable Zone Transfers from the Nameserver</title>
<description>Is it necessary for a secondary nameserver to receive zone data
via zone transfer from the primary server?  If not, follow the instructions in
this section. If so, see the next section for instructions on protecting zone
transfers.
Add or correct the following directive within <tt>/etc/named.conf</tt>:
<pre>options {
  allow-transfer { none; };
  ...
}</pre>
</description>
<rationale>If both the primary and secondary nameserver are under your control,
or if you have only one nameserver, it may be possible to use an external
configuration management mechanism to distribute zone updates. In that case, it
is not necessary to allow zone transfers within BIND itself, so they should be
disabled to avoid the potential for abuse.</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80327-0" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="dns_server_authenticate_zone_transfers" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Authenticate Zone Transfers</title>
<description>If it is necessary for a secondary nameserver to receive zone data
via zone transfer from the primary server, follow the instructions here.  Use
dnssec-keygen to create a symmetric key file in the current directory:
<pre>$ cd /tmp
$ sudo dnssec-keygen -a HMAC-MD5 -b 128 -n HOST dns.example.com
Kdns.example.com .+aaa +iiiii</pre>
This output is the name of a file containing the new key. Read the file to find
the base64-encoded key string:
<pre>$ sudo cat Kdns.example.com .+NNN +MMMMM .key
dns.example.com IN KEY 512 3 157 base64-key-string</pre>
Add the directives to <tt>/etc/named.conf</tt> on the primary server:
<pre>key zone-transfer-key {
  algorithm hmac-md5;
  secret "base64-key-string ";
};
zone "example.com " IN {
  type master;
  allow-transfer { key zone-transfer-key; };
  ...
};</pre>
Add the directives below to <tt>/etc/named.conf</tt> on the secondary nameserver:
<pre>key zone-transfer-key {
  algorithm hmac-md5;
  secret "base64-key-string ";
};

server IP-OF-MASTER {
  keys { zone-transfer-key; };
};

zone "example.com " IN {
  type slave;
  masters { IP-OF-MASTER ; };
  ...
};</pre>
</description>
<rationale>The BIND transaction signature (TSIG) functionality allows primary
and secondary nameservers to use a shared secret to verify authorization to
perform zone transfers. This method is more secure than using IP-based limiting
to restrict nameserver access, since IP addresses can be easily spoofed.
However, if you cannot configure TSIG between your servers because, for
instance, the secondary nameserver is not under your control and its
administrators are unwilling to configure TSIG, you can configure an
allow-transfer directive with numerical IP addresses or ACLs as a last resort.
</rationale>
<warning category="general">The purpose of the dnssec-keygen command is to
create the shared secret string base64-key-string. Once this secret has been
obtained and inserted into named.conf on the primary and secondary servers, the
key files Kdns.example.com .+NNN +MMMMM .key and Kdns.example.com .+NNN +MMMMM
.private are no longer needed, and may safely be deleted.</warning>
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-7" />
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80328-8" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="dns_server_disable_dynamic_updates" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Disable Dynamic Updates</title>
<description>Is there a mission-critical reason to enable the risky dynamic
update functionality? If not, edit <tt>/etc/named.conf</tt>. For each zone
specification, correct the following directive if necessary:
<pre>zone "example.com " IN {
  allow-update { none; };
  ...
};</pre>
</description>
<rationale>Dynamic updates allow remote servers to add, delete, or modify any
entries in your zone file. Therefore, they should be considered highly risky,
and disabled unless there is a very good reason for their use. If dynamic
updates must be allowed, IP-based ACLs are insufficient protection, since they
are easily spoofed. Instead, use TSIG keys (see the previous section for an
example), and consider using the update-policy directive to restrict changes to
only the precise type of change needed.</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80329-6" />
</Rule>

</Group> <!--<Group id="dns_server_protection">-->

</Group> <!--<Group id="dns">-->
