<Group id="ftp">
<title>FTP Server</title>
<description>FTP is a common method for allowing remote access to
files. Like telnet, the FTP protocol is unencrypted, which means
that passwords and other data transmitted during the session can be
captured and that the session is vulnerable to hijacking.
Therefore, running the FTP server software is not recommended.
<br /><br />
However, there are some FTP server configurations which may
be appropriate for some environments, particularly those which
allow only read-only anonymous access as a means of downloading
data available to the public.</description>

<Group id="disabling_vsftpd">
<title>Disable vsftpd if Possible</title>
<description>To minimize attack surface, disable vsftpd if at all
possible.</description>

<Rule id="service_vsftpd_disabled" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Disable vsftpd Service</title>
<description>
<systemd-service-macro enable="false" service="vsftpd" />
</description>
<ocil>
<systemd-check-macro enable="false" service="vsftpd" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
Running FTP server software provides a network-based avenue
of attack, and should be disabled if not needed.
Furthermore, the FTP protocol is unencrypted and creates
a risk of compromising sensitive information.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80244-7" />
<oval id="service_vsftpd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="1436" cis="2.2.9" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_vsftpd_removed" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Uninstall vsftpd Package</title>
<description>
<yum-macro install="false" package="vsftpd" />
</description>
<ocil>
<package-check-macro package="vsftpd" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
Removing the vsftpd package decreases the risk of its
accidental activation.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80245-4" />
<oval id="package_vsftpd_removed" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" stigid="040690" />
<ref nist="CM-6(b),CM-7" disa="366" srg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" />
</Rule>

</Group> <!-- <Group id="disabling_vsftpd"> -->

<Group id="ftp_use_vsftpd">
<title>Use vsftpd to Provide FTP Service if Necessary</title>
<description>If your use-case requires FTP service, install and
set-up vsftpd to provide it.</description>

<Rule id="package_vsftpd_installed" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Install vsftpd Package</title>
<description>If this system must operate as an FTP server, install the <tt>vsftpd</tt> package via the standard channels.
<pre>$ sudo yum install vsftpd</pre>
</description>
<rationale>After Red Hat Enterprise Linux 2.1, Red Hat switched from distributing wu-ftpd with Red Hat Enterprise Linux to distributing vsftpd. For security
and for consistency with future Red Hat releases, the use of vsftpd is recommended.</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80246-2" />
<oval id="package_vsftpd_installed" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

</Group> <!-- <Group id="ftp_use_vsftpd"> -->

<Group id="ftp_configure_vsftpd">
<title>Use vsftpd to Provide FTP Service if Necessary</title>
<description>The primary vsftpd configuration file is
<tt>/etc/vsftpd.conf</tt>, if that file exists, or
<tt>/etc/vsftpd/vsftpd.conf</tt> if it does not. 
</description>
<Rule id="ftp_log_transactions" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Enable Logging of All FTP Transactions</title>
<description>Add or correct the following configuration options within the <tt>vsftpd</tt>
configuration file, located at <tt>/etc/vsftpd/vsftpd.conf</tt>:
<pre>xferlog_enable=YES
xferlog_std_format=NO
log_ftp_protocol=YES</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="xferlog_enable is missing, or is not set to yes">
Find if logging is applied to the FTP daemon.
<br/><br/>
Procedures:
<br/><br/>
If vsftpd is started by xinetd the following command will indicate the xinetd.d startup file:
<pre>$ grep vsftpd /etc/xinetd.d/*</pre>
<pre>$ grep server_args <i>vsftpd xinetd.d startup file</i></pre>
This will indicate the vsftpd config file used when starting through xinetd.
If the <i>server_args</i> line is missing or does not include the vsftpd configuration file, then the default config file (/etc/vsftpd/vsftpd.conf) is used.
<pre>$ sudo grep xferlog_enable <i>vsftpd config file</i></pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>To trace malicious activity facilitated by the FTP service, it must be configured to ensure that all commands sent to
the FTP server are logged using the verbose vsftpd log
format. The default vsftpd log file is <tt>/var/log/vsftpd.log</tt>.</rationale>
<warning category="general">If verbose logging to <tt>vsftpd.log</tt> is done, sparse logging of downloads to <tt>/var/log/xferlog</tt> will not also occur. However, the information about what files were downloaded is included in the information logged to <tt>vsftpd.log</tt></warning>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80247-0" />
<oval id="ftp_log_transactions" />
<!--<ref nist="CM-7" /> -->
</Rule>

<Rule id="ftp_present_banner" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Create Warning Banners for All FTP Users</title>
<description>Edit the vsftpd configuration file, which resides at <tt>/etc/vsftpd/vsftpd.conf</tt>
by default. Add or correct the following configuration options:
<pre>banner_file=/etc/issue</pre>
</description>
<rationale>This setting will cause the system greeting banner to be used for FTP connections as well.</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80248-8" />
<ref disa="48" />
<oval id="ftp_present_banner" />
<!--<ref nist="CM-7" /> -->
<ocil clause="it does not">
If FTP services are not installed, this is not applicable.
<br /><br />
To verify this configuration, run the following command:
<pre>grep "banner_file" /etc/vsftpd/vsftpd.conf</pre>

The output should show the value of <tt>banner_file</tt> is set to <tt>/etc/issue</tt>, an example of which is shown below:
<pre>$ sudo grep "banner_file" /etc/vsftpd/vsftpd.conf
banner_file=/etc/issue</pre>
</ocil>
</Rule>

<Group id="ftp_restrict_users">
<title>Restrict the Set of Users Allowed to Access FTP</title>
<description>This section describes how to disable non-anonymous (password-based) FTP logins, or, if it is not possible to
do this entirely due to legacy applications, how to restrict insecure FTP login to only those users who have an
identified need for this access.</description>

<Rule id="ftp_restrict_to_anon" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Restrict Access to Anonymous Users if Possible</title>
<description>Is there a mission-critical reason for users to transfer files to/from their own accounts using FTP, rather than
using a secure protocol like SCP/SFTP? If not, edit the vsftpd configuration file. Add or correct the following configuration option:
<pre>local_enable=NO</pre>
If non-anonymous FTP logins are necessary, follow the guidance in the remainder of this section to secure
these logins as much as possible.</description>
<rationale>The use of non-anonymous FTP logins is strongly discouraged. Since SSH clients and servers are widely available, and since SSH provides support for a transfer mode which resembles FTP in user interface, there is no good reason to allow password-based FTP access. </rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80249-6" />
<!--<oval id="ftp_restrict_to_anon" />-->
<ref nist="CM-7,AC-3" />
</Rule>

<Group id="ftp_limit_users">
<title>Limit Users Allowed FTP Access if Necessary</title>
<description>If there is a mission-critical reason for users to access their accounts via the insecure FTP protocol, limit the set of users who are allowed this access. Edit the vsftpd configuration file. Add or correct the following configuration options:
<pre>userlist_enable=YES
userlist_file=/etc/vsftp.ftpusers
userlist_deny=NO</pre>
Edit the file <tt>/etc/vsftp.ftpusers</tt>. For each user USERNAME who should be allowed to access the system via FTP, add a line containing that user's name:
<pre>USERNAME</pre>
If anonymous access is also required, add the anonymous usernames to <tt>/etc/vsftp.ftpusers</tt> as well.
<pre>anonymous
ftp</pre>
</description>
<rationale>Historically, the file <tt>/etc/ftpusers</tt> contained a list of users who were not allowed to access the system via FTP. It was used to prevent system users such as the root user from logging in via the insecure FTP protocol. However, when the configuration option <tt>userlist deny=NO</tt> is set, vsftpd interprets ftpusers as the set of users who are allowed to login via FTP. Since it should be possible for most users to access their accounts via secure protocols, it is recommended that this setting be used, so that non-anonymous FTP access can be limited to legacy users who have been explicitly identified.</rationale>
<!--<oval id="ftp_limit_users" />-->
<!--<ref nist="CM-7" /> -->
</Group>

</Group> <!-- <Group id="ftp_restrict_users"> -->

<Rule id="ftp_disable_uploads" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Disable FTP Uploads if Possible</title>
<description>Is there a mission-critical reason for users to upload files via FTP? If not,
edit the vsftpd configuration file to add or correct the following configuration options:
<pre>write_enable=NO</pre>
If FTP uploads are necessary, follow the guidance in the remainder of this section to secure these transactions
as much as possible.</description>
<rationale>Anonymous FTP can be a convenient way to make files available for universal download. However, it is less
common to have a need to allow unauthenticated users to place files on the FTP server. If this must be done, it
is necessary to ensure that files cannot be uploaded and downloaded from the same directory.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80250-4" />
<!--<oval id="ftp_disable_uploads" />-->
<!--<ref nist="CM-7" /> -->
</Rule>

<Rule id="ftp_home_partition" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Place the FTP Home Directory on its Own Partition</title>
<description>By default, the anonymous FTP root is the home directory of the FTP user account. The df command can
be used to verify that this directory is on its own partition.</description>
<rationale>If there is a mission-critical reason for anonymous users to upload files, precautions must be taken to prevent
these users from filling a disk used by other services.</rationale>
<!--<oval id="ftp_home_partition" />-->
<!--<ref nist="CM-7" /> -->
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80251-2" />
</Rule>

<Group id="ftp_configure_firewall">
<title>Configure Firewalls to Protect the FTP Server</title>
<description>By default, <tt>firewalld</tt>
blocks access to the ports used by the web server.
<firewalld-desc-macro allow="true" proto="tcp" service="ftp" />
</description>
<rationale>These settings configure firewalld to allow connections to an FTP server. The first line allows initial connections
to the FTP server port.
FTP is an older protocol which is not very compatible with firewalls. During the initial FTP dialogue, the client
and server negotiate an arbitrary port to be used for data transfer. The <tt>ip_conntrack_ftp</tt>  module is used by
firewalld to listen to that dialogue and allow connections to the data ports which FTP negotiates. This allows an
FTP server to operate on a system which is running a firewall.</rationale>
<!--<oval id="ftp_configure_firewall" />-->
<!--<ref nist="CM-7" /> -->
</Group>

</Group> <!-- <Group id="ftp_configure_vsftpd"> -->
</Group> <!-- <Group id="ftp"> -->
