<Group id="ldap">
<title>LDAP</title>
<description>LDAP is a popular directory service, that is, a
standardized way of looking up information from a central database.
Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 includes software that enables a system to act as both
an LDAP client and server.
</description>

<Group id="openldap_client">
<title>Configure OpenLDAP Clients</title>
<description>This section provides information on which security settings are
important to configure in OpenLDAP clients by manually editing the appropriate
configuration files.  Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 provides an automated configuration tool called
authconfig and a graphical wrapper for authconfig called
<tt>system-config-authentication</tt>. However, these tools do not provide as
much control over configuration as manual editing of configuration files. The
authconfig tools do not allow you to specify locations of SSL certificate
files, which is useful when trying to use SSL cleanly across several protocols.
Installation and configuration of OpenLDAP on Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 is available at
<weblink-macro link="https://docs.redhat.com/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/7/html/System_Administrators_Guide/ch-Directory_Servers.html"/>.
</description>
<warning category="general">Before configuring any system to be an
LDAP client, ensure that a working LDAP server is present on the
network.</warning>

<Rule id="ldap_client_start_tls" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Configure LDAP Client to Use TLS For All Transactions</title>
<description>This check verifies that RHEL7 implements cryptography
to protect the integrity of remote LDAP authentication sessions.
<br /><br />
To determine if LDAP is being used for authentication, use the following
command:
<pre>$ sudo grep -i useldapauth /etc/sysconfig/authconfig</pre>
<br /><br />
If <tt>USELDAPAUTH=yes</tt>, then LDAP is being used. To check if LDAP is
configured to use TLS, use the following command:
<pre>$ sudo grep -i ssl /etc/pam_ldap.conf</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the 'ssl' option is not 'start_tls'">
If the system is not using TLS, set the <tt>ssl</tt> option in <tt>/etc/pam_ldap.conf</tt>
to <tt>start_tls</tt>.
</ocil>
<rationale>Without cryptographic integrity protections, information can be
altered by unauthorized users without detection. The ssl directive specifies 
whether to use TLS or not. If not specified it will default to no. 
It should be set to start_tls rather than doing LDAP over SSL.</rationale>
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="AC-17(2),CM-7" disa="1453" ossrg="SRG-OS-000250-GPOS-00093" stigid="040180" />
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80291-8" />
<oval id="ldap_client_start_tls" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ldap_client_tls_cacertpath" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Configure Certificate Directives for LDAP Use of TLS</title>
<description>Ensure a copy of a trusted CA certificate has been placed in
the file <tt>/etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</tt>. Configure LDAP to enforce TLS 
use and to trust certificates signed by that CA. First, edit the file 
<tt>/etc/nslcd.conf</tt>, and add or correct either of the following lines:
<pre>tls_cacertdir /etc/pki/tls/CA</pre>
or
<pre>tls_cacertfile /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</pre>
Then review the LDAP server and ensure TLS has been configured.
</description>
<ocil clause="there is no output, or the lines are commented out">
To ensure TLS is configured with trust certificates, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep cert /etc/nslcd.conf</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>The tls_cacertdir or tls_cacertfile directives are required when
tls_checkpeer is configured (which is the default for openldap versions 2.1 and
up). These directives define the path to the trust certificates signed by the
site CA.</rationale>
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-7" disa="776,778,1453" />
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80292-6" />
<oval id="ldap_client_tls_cacertpath" />
</Rule>

</Group><!--End <Group id="openldap_client"> -->

<Group id="openldap_server">
<title>Configure OpenLDAP Server</title>
<description>This section details some security-relevant settings
for an OpenLDAP server.  Installation and configuration of OpenLDAP on Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 is available at:
<weblink-macro link="https://docs.redhat.com/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/7/html/System_Administrators_Guide/ch-Directory_Servers.html"/>.
</description>

<Rule id="package_openldap-servers_removed" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Uninstall openldap-servers Package</title>
<description>The <tt>openldap-servers</tt> package should be removed if not in use.
Is this system the OpenLDAP server? If not, remove the package.
<pre>$ sudo yum erase openldap-servers</pre>
The openldap-servers RPM is not installed by default on Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7
system. It is needed only by the OpenLDAP server, not by the
clients which use LDAP for authentication. If the system is not
intended for use as an LDAP Server it should be removed.
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not">
To verify the <tt>openldap-servers</tt> package is not installed, 
run the following command:
<pre>$ rpm -q openldap-servers</pre>
The output should show the following:
<pre>package openldap-servers is not installed</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>Unnecessary packages should not be installed to decrease the attack
surface of the system.  While this software is clearly essential on an LDAP
server, it is not necessary on typical desktop or workstation systems.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80293-4" />
<oval id="package_openldap-servers_removed" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-7" disa="366" cis="3.7" />
</Rule>

<Group id="ldap_server_config_certificate_files">
<title>Install and Protect LDAP Certificate Files</title>
<description>Create the PKI directory for LDAP certificates if it does not already exist:
<pre>$ sudo mkdir /etc/pki/tls/ldap
$ sudo chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/ldap
$ sudo chmod 755 /etc/pki/tls/ldap</pre>
Using removable media or some other secure transmission format, install the certificate files
onto the LDAP server:
<ul>
<li><tt>/etc/pki/tls/ldap/serverkey.pem</tt>: the private key <tt>ldapserverkey.pem</tt></li>
<li><tt>/etc/pki/tls/ldap/servercert.pem</tt>: the certificate file <tt>ldapservercert.pem</tt></li>
</ul>
Verify the ownership and permissions of these files:
<pre>$ sudo chown root:ldap /etc/pki/tls/ldap/serverkey.pem
$ sudo chown root:ldap /etc/pki/tls/ldap/servercert.pem
$ sudo chmod 640 /etc/pki/tls/ldap/serverkey.pem
$ sudo chmod 640 /etc/pki/tls/ldap/servercert.pem</pre>
Verify that the CA's public certificate file has been installed as
<tt>/etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</tt>, and has the correct permissions:
<pre>$ sudo mkdir /etc/pki/tls/CA
$ sudo chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem
$ sudo chmod 644 /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</pre>

As a result of these steps, the LDAP server will have access to its own private
certificate and the key with which that certificate is encrypted, and to the
public certificate file belonging to the CA. Note that it would be possible for
the key to be protected further, so that processes running as ldap could not
read it. If this were done, the LDAP server process would need to be restarted
manually whenever the server rebooted.
</description>
</Group>


</Group>
</Group>
