<Group id="ntp">
<title>Network Time Protocol</title>
<description>The Network Time Protocol is used to manage the system
clock over a network. Computer clocks are not very accurate, so
time will drift unpredictably on unmanaged systems. Central time
protocols can be used both to ensure that time is consistent among
a network of systems, and that their time is consistent with the
outside world.
<br /><br />
If every system on a network reliably reports the same time, then it is much
easier to correlate log messages in case of an attack. In addition, a number of
cryptographic protocols (such as Kerberos) use timestamps to prevent certain
types of attacks. If your network does not have synchronized time, these
protocols may be unreliable or even unusable.
<br /><br />
Depending on the specifics of the network, global time accuracy may be just as
important as local synchronization, or not very important at all. If your
network is connected to the Internet, using a public timeserver (or one
provided by your enterprise) provides globally accurate timestamps which may be
essential in investigating or responding to an attack which originated outside
of your network.
<br /><br />
A typical network setup involves a small number of internal systems operating
as NTP servers, and the remainder obtaining time information from those
internal servers.
<br /><br />
There is a choice between the daemons <tt>ntpd</tt> and <tt>chronyd</tt>, which
are available from the repositories in the <tt>ntp</tt> and <tt>chrony</tt>
packages respectively.
<br /><br />
The default <tt>chronyd</tt> daemon can work well when external time references
are only intermittently accesible, can perform well even when the network is
congested for longer periods of time, can usually synchronize the clock faster
and with better time accuracy, and quickly adapts to sudden changes in the rate
of the clock, for example, due to changes in the temperature of the crystal
oscillator. <tt>Chronyd</tt> should be considered for all systems which are
frequently suspended or otherwise intermittently disconnected and reconnected
to a network. Mobile and virtual systems for example.
<br /><br />
The <tt>ntpd</tt> NTP daemon fully supports NTP protocol version 4 (RFC 5905),
including broadcast, multicast, manycast clients and servers, and the orphan
mode. It also supports extra authentication schemes based on public-key
cryptography (RFC 5906). The NTP daemon (<tt>ntpd</tt>) should be considered
for systems which are normally kept permanently on. Systems which are required
to use broadcast or multicast IP, or to perform authentication of packets with
the <tt>Autokey</tt> protocol, should consider using <tt>ntpd</tt>.
<br /><br />
Refer to <weblink-macro link="https://access.redhat.com/documentation/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/7/html/System_Administrators_Guide/ch-Configuring_NTP_Using_the_chrony_Suite.html"/> for more detailed comparison of features of <tt>chronyd</tt>
and <tt>ntpd</tt> daemon features respectively, and for further guidance how to
choose between the two NTP daemons.
<br /><br />
The upstream manual pages at <weblink-macro link="http://chrony.tuxfamily.org/manual.html"/> for
<tt>chronyd</tt> and <weblink-macro link="http://www.ntp.org"/> for <tt>ntpd</tt> provide additional
information on the capabilities and configuration of each of the NTP daemons.
</description>
<platform idref="cpe:/a:machine" />

<Value id="var_multiple_time_servers" type="string" >
<title>Vendor Approved Time Servers</title>
<description>The list of vendor-approved time servers</description>
<value selector="rhel">0.rhel.pool.ntp.org,1.rhel.pool.ntp.org,2.rhel.pool.ntp.org,3.rhel.pool.ntp.org</value>
<value selector="fedora">0.fedora.pool.ntp.org,1.fedora.pool.ntp.org,2.fedora.pool.ntp.org,3.fedora.pool.ntp.org</value>
</Value>

<Value id="var_time_service_set_maxpoll" type="number" >
<title>Maximum NTP or Chrony Poll</title>
<description>The maximum NTP or Chrony poll interval number in seconds specified as a power of two.</description>
<value selector="">10</value>
<value selector="system_default">10</value>
<value selector="36_hours">17</value>
</Value>

<Rule id="service_chronyd_or_ntpd_enabled" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Enable the NTP Daemon</title>
<description>
<systemd-service-macro enable="true" service="chronyd" />
Note: The <tt>chronyd</tt> daemon is enabled by default.
<br /><br />
<systemd-service-macro enable="true" service="ntpd" />
Note: The <tt>ntpd</tt> daemon is not enabled by default. Though as mentioned
in the previous sections in certain environments the <tt>ntpd</tt> daemon might
be preferred to be used rather than the <tt>chronyd</tt> one. Refer to:
<weblink-macro link="https://access.redhat.com/documentation/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/7/html/System_Administrators_Guide/ch-Configuring_NTP_Using_the_chrony_Suite.html"/>
for guidance which NTP daemon to choose depending on the environment used.
</description>
<ocil>
  <systemd-check-macro enable="true" service="chronyd" />
  <systemd-check-macro enable="true" service="ntpd" />
</ocil>
<rationale>Enabling some of <tt>chronyd</tt> or <tt>ntpd</tt> services ensures
that the NTP daemon will be running and that the system will synchronize its
time to any servers specified. This is important whether the system is
configured to be a client (and synchronize only its own clock) or it is also
acting as an NTP server to other systems.  Synchronizing time is essential for
authentication services such as Kerberos, but it is also important for
maintaining accurate logs and auditing possible security breaches.
<br /><br />
The <tt>chronyd</tt> and <tt>ntpd</tt> NTP daemons offer all of the
functionality of <tt>ntpdate</tt>, which is now deprecated. Additional
information on this is available at
<weblink-macro link="http://support.ntp.org/bin/view/Dev/DeprecatingNtpdate"/></rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27444-9" />
<oval id="service_chronyd_or_ntpd_enabled" />
<ref nist="AU-8(1)" disa="160" pcidss="Req-10.4" cis="2.2.1.1" cui="3.3.7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="chronyd_or_ntpd_specify_remote_server" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Specify a Remote NTP Server</title>
<description>Depending on specific functional requirements of a concrete
production environment, the Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 Server system can be
configured to utilize the services of the <tt>chronyd</tt> NTP daemon (the
default), or services of the <tt>ntpd</tt> NTP daemon. Refer to
<weblink-macro link="https://access.redhat.com/documentation/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/7/html/System_Administrators_Guide/ch-Configuring_NTP_Using_the_chrony_Suite.html"/>
for more detailed comparison of the features of both of the choices, and for
further guidance how to choose between the two NTP daemons.
<br />
To specify a remote NTP server for time synchronization, perform the following:
<ul>
<li> if the system is configured to use the <tt>chronyd</tt> as the NTP daemon (the
default), edit the file <tt>/etc/chrony.conf</tt> as follows,</li>
<li> if the system is configured to use the <tt>ntpd</tt> as the NTP daemon,
edit the file <tt>/etc/ntp.conf</tt> as documented below.</li>
</ul>
Add or correct the following lines, substituting the IP or hostname of a remote
NTP server for <em>ntpserver</em>:
<pre>server <i>ntpserver</i></pre>
This instructs the NTP software to contact that remote server to obtain time
data.
</description>
<ocil clause="this is not the case">
To verify that a remote NTP service is configured for time synchronization,
open the following file:
<ul>
<li><pre>/etc/chrony.conf</pre> in the case the system in question is
configured to use the <tt>chronyd</tt> as the NTP daemon (default setting)</li>
<li><pre>/etc/ntp.conf</pre> in the case the system in question is configured
to use the <tt>ntpd</tt> as the NTP daemon</li>
</ul>
In the file, there should be a section similar to the following:
<pre>server <i>ntpserver</i></pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>Synchronizing with an NTP server makes it possible to collate system
logs from multiple sources or correlate computer events with real time events.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27278-1" />
<oval id="chronyd_or_ntpd_specify_remote_server" />
<ref nist="AU-8(1)" disa="160" pcidss="Req-10.4.1,Req-10.4.3" cis="3.6" cui="3.3.7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="chronyd_or_ntpd_specify_multiple_servers" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Specify Additional Remote NTP Servers</title>
<description>Depending on specific functional requirements of a concrete
production environment, the Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 Server system can be
configured to utilize the services of the <tt>chronyd</tt> NTP daemon (the
default), or services of the <tt>ntpd</tt> NTP daemon. Refer to
<weblink-macro link="https://access.redhat.com/documentation/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/7/html/System_Administrators_Guide/ch-Configuring_NTP_Using_the_chrony_Suite.html"/>
for more detailed comparison of the features of both of the choices, and for
further guidance how to choose between the two NTP daemons.
<br />
Additional NTP servers can be specified for time synchronization. To do so,
perform the following:
<ul>
<li> if the system is configured to use the <tt>chronyd</tt> as the NTP daemon
(the default), edit the file <tt>/etc/chrony.conf</tt> as follows,</li>
<li> if the system is configured to use the <tt>ntpd</tt> as the NTP daemon,
edit the file <tt>/etc/ntp.conf</tt> as documented below.</li>
</ul>
Add additional lines of the following form, substituting the IP address or
hostname of a remote NTP server for <em>ntpserver</em>:
<pre>server <i>ntpserver</i></pre>
</description>
<rationale>Specifying additional NTP servers increases the availability of
accurate time data, in the event that one of the specified servers becomes
unavailable. This is typical for a system acting as an NTP server for
other systems.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27012-4" />
<oval id="chronyd_or_ntpd_specify_multiple_servers"/>
<ref nist="AU-8(1)" pcidss="Req-10.4.3" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="chronyd_or_ntpd_set_maxpoll" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Configure Time Service Maxpoll Interval</title>
<description>The <tt>maxpoll</tt> should be configured to
<sub idref="var_time_service_set_maxpoll" /> in <tt>/etc/ntp.conf</tt> or
<tt>/etc/chrony.conf</tt> to continuously poll time servers. To configure
<tt>maxpoll</tt> in <tt>/etc/ntp.conf</tt> or <tt>/etc/chrony.conf</tt>
add the following:
<pre>maxpoll <sub idref="var_time_service_set_maxpoll" /></pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not exist or maxpoll has not been set to the expected value">
To verify that <tt>maxpoll</tt> has been set properly, perform the following:
<pre>$ sudo grep maxpoll /etc/ntp.conf /etc/chrony.conf</pre>
The output should return
<pre>maxpoll <sub idref="var_time_service_set_maxpoll" /></pre>.
</ocil>
<rationale>Inaccurate time stamps make it more difficult to correlate
events and can lead to an inaccurate analysis. Determining the correct
time a particular event occurred on a system is critical when conducting
forensic analysis and investigating system events. Sources outside the
configured acceptable allowance (drift) may be inaccurate.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80439-3" />
<oval id="chronyd_or_ntpd_set_maxpoll" value="var_time_service_set_maxpoll" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" stigid="040500" />
<ref nist="AU-8(1)(a)" disa="1891,2046" srg="SRG-OS-000355-GPOS-00143, SRG-OS-000356-GPOS-00144" />
</Rule>


<!-- future Rules (for later profiles/enhancements):
ensuring use of the restrict keyword
enabling cryptographic authentication (multiple options)
-->

</Group>
