<Group id="routing">
<title>Network Routing</title>
<description>A router is a very desirable target for a
potential adversary because they fulfill a variety of 
infrastructure networking roles such as access to network segments,
gateways to other networks, filtering, etc. Therefore, if one is
required, the system acting as a router should be dedicated
to that purpose alone and be stored in a physically secure
location. The system's default routing software is Quagga, and
provided in an RPM package of the same name.</description>

<Group id="disabling_quagga">
<title>Disable Quagga if Possible</title>
<description>If Quagga was installed and activated, but the system
does not need to act as a router, then it should be disabled
and removed.
</description>

<Rule id="service_zebra_disabled" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Disable Quagga Service</title>
<description>
<systemd-service-macro enable="false" service="zebra" />
</description>
<ocil>
<systemd-check-macro enable="false" service="zebra" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
Routing protocol daemons are typically used on routers to exchange network
topology information with other routers. If routing daemons are used when not
required, system network information may be unnecessarily transmitted across
the network.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27191-6" />
<oval id="service_zebra_disabled" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" stigid="040730" />
<ref nist="SC-32" disa="366" srg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_quagga_removed" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Uninstall quagga Package</title>
<description>
<yum-macro install="false" package="quagga" />
</description>
<ocil>
<package-check-macro package="quagga" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
Routing software is typically used on routers to exchange network topology information
with other routers. If routing software is used when not required, system network
information may be unnecessarily transmitted across the network.
<br/>
If there is no need to make the router software available,
removing it provides a safeguard against its activation.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27594-1" />
<oval id="package_quagga_removed" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" stigid="TBD" />
<ref nist="SC-32" disa="366" srg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" />
</Rule>

</Group>
</Group>

