<Group id="mail">
<title>Mail Server Software</title>
<description>
Mail servers are used to send and receive email over the network.
Mail is a very common service, and Mail Transfer Agents (MTAs) are obvious
targets of network attack.
Ensure that systems are not running MTAs unnecessarily,
and configure needed MTAs as defensively as possible.
<br /><br />
Very few systems at any site should be configured to directly receive email over the
network. Users should instead use mail client programs to retrieve email
from a central server that supports protocols such as IMAP or POP3.
However, it is normal for most systems to be independently capable of sending email,
for instance so that cron jobs can report output to an administrator.
Most MTAs, including Postfix, support a submission-only mode in which mail can be sent from
the local system to a central site MTA (or directly delivered to a local account),
but the system still cannot receive mail directly over a network.
<br /><br />
The <tt>alternatives</tt> program in Red Hat Enterprise Linux permits selection of other mail server software
(such as Sendmail), but Postfix is the default and is preferred.
Postfix was coded with security in mind and can also be more effectively contained by
SELinux as its modular design has resulted in separate processes performing specific actions.
More information is available on its website, <weblink-macro link="http://www.postfix.org"/>.
</description>

<Rule id="service_postfix_enabled">
<title>Enable Postfix Service</title>
<description>The Postfix mail transfer agent is used for local mail delivery
within the system. The default configuration only listens for connections to
the default SMTP port (port 25) on the loopback interface (127.0.0.1).  It is
recommended to leave this service enabled for local mail delivery.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="true" service="postfix" />
</description>
<ocil clause="the system is not a cross domain solution and the service is not enabled">
<service-check-macro enable="true" service="postfix" />
</ocil>
<rationale>Local mail delivery is essential to some system maintenance and
notification tasks.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26325-1" stig="RHEL-06-000287" />
<oval id="service_postfix_enabled" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_sendmail_removed" severity="medium">
<title>Uninstall Sendmail Package</title>
<description>Sendmail is not the default mail transfer agent and is
not installed by default.
<yum-macro install="false" package="sendmail" />
</description>
<ocil>
<package-check-macro package="sendmail" />
</ocil>
<rationale>The sendmail software was not developed with security in mind and
its design prevents it from being effectively contained by SELinux.  Postfix
should be used instead.  
</rationale>
<ident cce="27515-6" stig="RHEL-06-000288" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
<oval id="package_sendmail_removed" />
</Rule>

<Group id="postfix_client">
<title>Configure SMTP For Mail Clients</title>
<description>This section discusses settings for Postfix in a submission-only
e-mail configuration.</description>

<Rule id="postfix_network_listening_disabled" severity="medium">
<title>Disable Postfix Network Listening</title>
<description>
Edit the file <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt> to ensure that only the following
<tt>inet_interfaces</tt> line appears:
<pre>inet_interfaces = localhost</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not">
Run the following command to ensure postfix accepts mail messages from only the local system:
<pre>$ grep inet_interfaces /etc/postfix/main.cf</pre>
If properly configured, the output should show only <tt>localhost</tt>.
</ocil>
<rationale>
This ensures <tt>postfix</tt> accepts mail messages
(such as cron job reports) from the local system only,
and not from the network, which protects it from network attack.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26780-7" stig="RHEL-06-000249" />
<oval id="postfix_network_listening_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="382"/>
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="postfix_harden_os">
<title>Configure Operating System to Protect Mail Server
</title>
<description>The guidance in this section is appropriate for any host which is
operating as a site MTA, whether the mail server runs using Sendmail, Postfix,
or some other software.
</description>



<Group id="postfix_configure_ssl_certs">
<title>Configure SSL Certificates for Use with SMTP AUTH</title>
<description>
If SMTP AUTH is to be used, the use of SSL to protect credentials in transit is strongly recommended.
There are also configurations for which it may be desirable to encrypt all mail in transit from one MTA to another,
though such configurations are beyond the scope of this guide. In either event, the steps for creating and installing
an SSL certificate are independent of the MTA in use, and are described here.
</description>


<Group id="postfix_install_ssl_cert">
<title>Ensure Security of Postfix SSL Certificate</title>
<description>Create the PKI directory for mail certificates, if it does not already exist:
<pre>$ sudo mkdir /etc/pki/tls/mail
$ sudo chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/mail
$ sudo chmod 755 /etc/pki/tls/mail</pre>
Using removable media or some other secure transmission format, install the files generated in the previous
step onto the mail server:
<pre>/etc/pki/tls/mail/serverkey.pem: the private key mailserverkey.pem
/etc/pki/tls/mail/servercert.pem: the certificate file mailservercert.pem</pre>
Verify the ownership and permissions of these files:
<pre>$ sudo chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/mail/serverkey.pem
$ sudo chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/mail/servercert.pem
$ sudo chmod 600 /etc/pki/tls/mail/serverkey.pem
$ sudo chmod 644 /etc/pki/tls/mail/servercert.pem</pre>
Verify that the CA's public certificate file has been installed as <tt>/etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</tt>, and has the
correct permissions:
<pre>$ sudo chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem
$ sudo chmod 644 /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</pre>
</description>
</Group>

</Group>

<Group id="postfix_server_configuration">
<title>Configure Postfix if Necessary</title>
<description>Postfix stores its configuration files in the directory
/etc/postfix by default. The primary configuration file is
<tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt>.
</description>

<Rule id="postfix_server_banner" severity="medium">
<title>Configure SMTP Greeting Banner</title>
<description>Edit <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt>, and add or correct the
following line, substituting some other wording for the banner information if
you prefer:
<pre>smtpd_banner = $myhostname ESMTP</pre>
</description>
<rationale>The default greeting banner discloses that the listening mail
process is Postfix.  When remote mail senders connect to the MTA on port 25,
they are greeted by an initial banner as part of the SMTP dialogue. This banner
is necessary, but it frequently gives away too much information, including the
MTA software which is in use, and sometimes also its version number. Remote
mail senders do not need this information in order to send mail, so the banner
should be changed to reveal only the hostname (which is already known and may
be useful) and the word ESMTP, to indicate that the modern SMTP protocol
variant is supported.
</rationale>
<oval id="postfix_server_banner" />
<ref nist="AC-22, AU-13" />
<ident cce="27508-1" />
</Rule>

<Group id="postfix_server_denial_of_service">
<title>Configure Postfix Resource Usage to Limit Denial of Service Attacks</title>
<description>Edit <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt>. Edit the following lines to
configure the amount of system resources Postfix can consume:
<pre>default_process_limit = 100
smtpd_client_connection_count_limit = 10
smtpd_client_connection_rate_limit = 30
queue_minfree = 20971520
header_size_limit = 51200
message_size_limit = 10485760
smtpd_recipient_limit = 100</pre>
The values here are examples.
</description>
<rationale>These configuration options serve to make it more difficult for
attackers to consume resources on the MTA host.  The
<tt>default_process_limit</tt> parameter controls how many <tt>smtpd</tt>
processes can exist at a time, while
<tt>smtpd_client_connection_count_limit</tt> controls the number of those which
can be occupied by any one remote sender, and
<tt>smtpd_client_connection_rate_limit</tt> controls the number of connections
any one client can make per minute. By default, local hosts (those in
<tt>mynetworks</tt>) are exempted from per-client rate limiting.  The
<tt>queue_minfree</tt> parameter establishes a free space threshold, in order
to stop e-mail receipt before the queue filesystem is entirely full. The
<tt>header_size_limit</tt>, <tt>message_size_limit</tt>, and
<tt>smtpd_recipient_limit</tt> parameters place bounds on the legal sizes of
messages received via SMTP.
</rationale>
<warning category="general">Note: The values given here are examples, and may
need to be modified for any particular site. By default, the Postfix anvil
process gathers mail receipt statistics. To get information about about what
connection rates are typical at your site, look in <tt>/var/log/maillog</tt>
for lines with the daemon name postfix/anvil.
</warning>
</Group>


<Group id="postfix_server_mail_relay">
<title>Control Mail Relaying</title>
<description>Postfix's mail relay controls are implemented with the help of the
smtpd recipient restrictions option, which controls the restrictions placed on
the SMTP dialogue once the sender and recipient envelope addresses are known.
The guidance in the following sections should be applied to all systems. If
there are systems which must be allowed to relay mail, but which cannot be
trusted to relay unconditionally, configure SMTP AUTH with SSL support.
</description>

<Group id="postfix_server_mail_relay_set_trusted_networks">
<title>Configure Trusted Networks and Hosts</title>
<description>Edit <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt>, and configure the contents of
the <tt>mynetworks</tt> variable in one of the following ways:
<ul>
<li>If any system in the subnet containing the MTA may be trusted to relay
messages, add or correct the following line:
<pre>mynetworks_style = subnet</pre>
This is also the default setting, and is in effect if all
<tt>my_networks_style</tt> directives are commented.</li>
<li>If only the MTA host itself is trusted to relay messages, add or correct
the following line:
<pre>mynetworks_style = host</pre></li>
<li>If the set of systems which can relay is more complicated, manually
specify an entry for each netblock or IP address which is trusted to relay by
setting the <tt>mynetworks</tt> variable directly:
<pre>mynetworks = 10.0.0.0/16, 192.168.1.0/24, 127.0.0.1</pre></li>
</ul>
</description>
<rationale>The <tt>mynetworks</tt> variable must contain only the set of
systems for which this MTA should unconditionally relay mail. This is a trust
relationship - if spammers gain access to these systems, your site will
effectively become an open relay. It is recommended that only systems which
are managed by you or by another trusted organization be placed in mynetworks,
and users of all other systems be required to use SMTP AUTH to send mail.
</rationale>
</Group>

<Group id="postfix_server_mail_smtpd_relay_restrictions">
<title>Enact SMTP Relay Restrictions</title>
<description>
To configure Postfix to restrict addresses to which it
will send mail, see:
<weblink-macro link="http://www.postfix.org/SMTPD_ACCESS_README.html#danger"/>
<br/>
The full contents of <tt>smtpd_recipient_restrictions</tt> will
vary by site, since this is a common place to put spam restrictions and other
site-specific options. The <tt>permit_mynetworks</tt> option allows all mail to
be relayed from the systems in <tt>mynetworks</tt>. Then, the
<tt>reject_unauth_destination</tt> option denies all mail whose destination
address is not local, preventing any other systems from relaying. These two
options should always appear in this order, and should usually follow one
another immediately unless SMTP AUTH is used.
</description>
</Group>

<Group id="postfix_server_mail_smtpd_recipient_restrictions">
<title>Enact SMTP Recipient Restrictions</title>
<description>
To configure Postfix to restrict addresses to which it
will send mail, see:
<weblink-macro link="http://www.postfix.org/SMTPD_ACCESS_README.html#danger"/>
<br/>
The full contents of <tt>smtpd_recipient_restrictions</tt> will
vary by site, since this is a common place to put spam restrictions and other
site-specific options. The <tt>permit_mynetworks</tt> option allows all mail to
be relayed from the systems in <tt>mynetworks</tt>. Then, the
<tt>reject_unauth_destination</tt> option denies all mail whose destination
address is not local, preventing any other systems from relaying. These two
options should always appear in this order, and should usually follow one
another immediately unless SMTP AUTH is used.
</description>
</Group>

<Group id="postfix_server_mail_relay_smtp_auth_for_untrusted_networks">
<title>Require SMTP AUTH Before Relaying from Untrusted Clients</title>
<description>SMTP authentication allows remote clients to relay mail safely by
requiring them to authenticate before submitting mail. Postfix's SMTP AUTH uses
an authentication library called SASL, which is not part of Postfix itself.  To
enable the use of SASL authentication, see
<weblink-macro link="http://www.postfix.org/SASL_README.html"/>
</description>
</Group>

<Group id="postfix_server_mail_relay_require_tls_for_smtp_auth">
<title>Use TLS for SMTP AUTH</title>
<description>
Postfix provides options to use TLS for certificate-based
authentication and encrypted sessions. An encrypted session protects the
information that is transmitted with SMTP mail or with SASL authentication.
To configure Postfix to protect all SMTP AUTH transactions
using TLS, see <weblink-macro link="http://www.postfix.org/TLS_README.html"/>.
</description>
</Group>

</Group>
</Group>
</Group>
</Group>
