<Group id="obsolete">
<title>Obsolete Services</title>
<description>This section discusses a number of network-visible
services which have historically caused problems for system
security, and for which disabling or severely limiting the service
has been the best available guidance for some time. As a result of
this, many of these services are not installed as part of Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6
by default.
<br /><br />
Organizations which are running these services should
switch to more secure equivalents as soon as possible.
If it remains absolutely necessary to run one of
these services for legacy reasons, care should be taken to restrict
the service as much as possible, for instance by configuring host
firewall software such as <tt>iptables</tt> to restrict access to the
vulnerable service to only those remote hosts which have a known
need to use it.</description>

<Group id="inetd_and_xinetd">
<title>Xinetd</title>
<description>The <tt>xinetd</tt> service acts as a dedicated listener for some
network services (mostly, obsolete ones) and can be used to provide access
controls and perform some logging. It has been largely obsoleted by other
features, and it is not installed by default. The older Inetd service
is not even available as part of Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6.</description>

<Rule id="service_xinetd_disabled" severity="medium">
<title>Disable xinetd Service</title>
<description>
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="xinetd" />
</description>
<ocil>
If network services are using the xinetd service, this is not applicable.
<br /><br />
<service-check-macro enable="false" service="xinetd" /></ocil>
<rationale>
The xinetd service provides a dedicated listener service for some programs,
which is no longer necessary for commonly-used network services. Disabling
it ensures that these uncommon services are not running, and also prevents
attacks against xinetd itself.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27046-2" stig="RHEL-06-000203" />
<oval id="service_xinetd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="305"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_xinetd_removed">
<title>Uninstall xinetd Package</title>
<description>The <tt>xinetd</tt> package can be uninstalled with the following command:
<pre>$ sudo yum erase xinetd</pre>
</description>
<ocil>
If network services are using the xinetd service, this is not applicable.
<br /><br />
<package-check-macro package="xinetd" /> </ocil>
<rationale>
Removing the <tt>xinetd</tt> package decreases the risk of the
xinetd service's accidental (or intentional) activation.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27005-8" stig="RHEL-06-000204" />
<oval id="package_xinetd_removed" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="305"/>
</Rule>

</Group>
<Group id="telnet">
<title>Telnet</title>
<description>The telnet protocol does not provide confidentiality or integrity
for information transmitted on the network. This includes authentication
information such as passwords. Organizations which use telnet should be
actively working to migrate to a more secure protocol.</description>

<Rule id="service_telnetd_disabled" severity="high">
<title>Disable telnet Service</title>
<description>
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="telnet" />
</description>
<ocil><xinetd-service-check-macro enable="false" service="telnet" /></ocil>
<rationale>
The telnet protocol uses unencrypted network communication, which
means that data from the login session, including passwords and
all other information transmitted during the session, can be
stolen by eavesdroppers on the network. The telnet protocol is also
subject to man-in-the-middle attacks.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26836-7" stig="RHEL-06-000211" />
<oval id="service_telnetd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7,IA-5(1)(c)" disa="68,1436,197,877,888" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_telnet-server_removed" severity="high">
<title>Uninstall telnet-server Package</title>
<description>The <tt>telnet-server</tt> package can be uninstalled with
the following command:
<pre>$ sudo yum erase telnet-server</pre></description>
<ocil><package-check-macro package="telnet-server" /> </ocil>
<rationale>
Removing the <tt>telnet-server</tt> package decreases the risk of the
telnet service's accidental (or intentional) activation.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27073-6" stig="RHEL-06-000206" />
<oval id="package_telnet-server_removed" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="305,381"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_telnet_removed" severity="low">
<title>Remove telnet Clients</title>
<description>The telnet client allows users to start connections to other 
systems via the telnet protocol.</description>
<ocil><yum-macro install="false" package="telnet" /></ocil>
<rationale>The <tt>telnet</tt> protocol is insecure and unencrypted. The use
of an unencrypted transmission medium could allow an unauthorized user
to steal credentials. The <tt>ssh</tt> package provides an
encrypted session and stronger security and is included in Red Hat
Enterprise Linux.</rationale>
<ident cce="27428-2" />
<oval id="package_telnet_removed" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="r_services">
<title>Rlogin, Rsh, and Rexec</title>
<description>The Berkeley r-commands are legacy services which
allow cleartext remote access and have an insecure trust
model.</description>

<Rule id="package_rsh-server_removed" severity="high">
<title>Uninstall rsh-server Package</title>
<description>The <tt>rsh-server</tt> package can be uninstalled with
the following command:
<pre>$ sudo yum erase rsh-server</pre>
</description>
<ocil><package-check-macro package="rsh-server" /> </ocil>
<rationale>The <tt>rsh-server</tt> package provides several obsolete and insecure
network services. Removing it
decreases the risk of those services' accidental (or intentional)
activation.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27062-9" stig="RHEL-06-000213" />
<oval id="package_rsh-server_removed" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="305,381"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_rexec_disabled" severity="high">
<title>Disable rexec Service</title>
<description>The <tt>rexec</tt> service, which is available with
the <tt>rsh-server</tt> package and runs as a service through xinetd,
should be disabled.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="rexec" />
</description> 
<ocil><xinetd-service-check-macro enable="false" service="rexec" /></ocil>
<rationale>The rexec service uses unencrypted network communications, which
means that data from the login session, including passwords and
all other information transmitted during the session, can be
stolen by eavesdroppers on the network.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27208-8" stig="RHEL-06-000216" />
<oval id="service_rexec_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="68,1436"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_rsh_disabled" severity="high">
<title>Disable rsh Service</title>
<description>The <tt>rsh</tt> service, which is available with
the <tt>rsh-server</tt> package and runs as a service through xinetd,
should be disabled.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="rsh" />
</description> 
<ocil><xinetd-service-check-macro enable="false" service="rsh" /></ocil>
<rationale>The rsh service uses unencrypted network communications, which
means that data from the login session, including passwords and
all other information transmitted during the session, can be
stolen by eavesdroppers on the network.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26994-4" stig="RHEL-06-000214" />
<oval id="service_rsh_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7,IA-5(1)(c)" disa="68,1436" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_rsh_removed">
<title>Uninstal rsh Package</title>
<description>The <tt>rsh</tt> package contains the client commands
for the rsh services</description>
<ocil><yum-macro install="false" package="rsh"/></ocil>
<rationale>These legacy clients contain numerous security exposures and have
been replaced with the more secure SSH package. Even if the server is removed,
it is best to ensure the clients are also removed to prevent users from
inadvertently attempting to use these commands and therefore exposing
their credentials. Note that removing the <tt>rsh</tt> package removes
the clients for <tt>rsh</tt>,<tt>rcp</tt>, and <tt>rlogin</tt>.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27359-9" />
<oval id="package_rsh_removed" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_rlogin_disabled" severity="high">
<title>Disable rlogin Service</title>
<description>The <tt>rlogin</tt> service, which is available with
the <tt>rsh-server</tt> package and runs as a service through xinetd,
should be disabled.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="rlogin" />
</description> 
<ocil><xinetd-service-check-macro enable="false" service="rlogin" /></ocil>
<rationale>The rlogin service uses unencrypted network communications, which
means that data from the login session, including passwords and
all other information transmitted during the session, can be
stolen by eavesdroppers on the network.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26865-6" stig="RHEL-06-000218" />
<oval id="service_rlogin_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7,IA-5(1)(c)" disa="1436" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="no_rsh_trust_files" severity="high">
<title>Remove Rsh Trust Files</title>
<description>The files <tt>/etc/hosts.equiv</tt> and <tt>~/.rhosts</tt> (in
each user's home directory) list remote hosts and users that are trusted by the
local system when using the rshd daemon.
To remove these files, run the following command to delete them from any
location:
<pre>$ sudo rm /etc/hosts.equiv</pre>
<pre>$ rm ~/.rhosts</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="these files exist">
The existence of the file <tt>/etc/hosts.equiv</tt> or a file named
<tt>.rhosts</tt> inside a user home directory indicates the presence
of an Rsh trust relationship.
</ocil>
<rationale>Trust files are convenient, but when
used in conjunction with the R-services, they can allow
unauthenticated access to a system.</rationale>
<ident cce="27270-8" stig="RHEL-06-000019" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="1436" />
<oval id="no_rsh_trust_files" />
</Rule>

</Group>
<Group id="nis">
<title>NIS</title>
<description>The Network Information Service (NIS), also known as 'Yellow
Pages' (YP), and its successor NIS+ have been made obsolete by
Kerberos, LDAP, and other modern centralized authentication
services. NIS should not be used because it suffers from security
problems inherent in its design, such as inadequate protection of
important authentication information.</description>

<Rule id="package_ypserv_removed" severity="medium">
<title>Uninstall ypserv Package</title>
<description>The <tt>ypserv</tt> package can be uninstalled with
the following command:
<pre>$ sudo yum erase ypserv</pre>
</description>
<ocil><package-check-macro package="ypserv" /> </ocil>
<rationale>Removing the <tt>ypserv</tt> package decreases the risk of the
accidental (or intentional) activation of NIS or NIS+ services.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27079-3" stig="RHEL-06-000220" />
<oval id="package_ypserv_removed" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="305,381"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_ypbind_disabled" severity="medium">
<title>Disable ypbind Service</title>
<description>The <tt>ypbind</tt> service, which allows the system to act as a client in
a NIS or NIS+ domain, should be disabled.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="ypbind" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="ypbind" /></ocil>
<rationale>
Disabling the <tt>ypbind</tt> service ensures the system is not acting
as a client in a NIS or NIS+ domain.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26894-6" stig="RHEL-06-000221" />
<oval id="service_ypbind_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="305"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_ypbind_removed">
<title>Remove NIS Client</title>
<description>The Network Information Service (NIS), formerly known as Yellow Pages,
is a client-server directory service protocol used to distribute system configuration
files. The NIS client (<tt>ypbind</tt>) was used to bind a system to an NIS server
and receive the distributed configuration files.</description>
<ocil><yum-macro install="false" package="ypbind"/></ocil>
<rationale>The NIS service is inherently an insecure system that has been vulnerable
to DOS attacks, buffer overflows and has poor authentication for querying NIS maps.
NIS generally has been replaced by such protocols as Lightweight Directory Access 
Protocol (LDAP). It is recommended that the service be removed.</rationale>
<ident cce="27372-2" />
<oval id="package_ypbind_removed" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="tftp">
<title>TFTP Server</title>
<description>
TFTP is a lightweight version of the FTP protocol which has
traditionally been used to configure networking equipment. However,
TFTP provides little security, and modern versions of networking
operating systems frequently support configuration via SSH or other
more secure protocols. A TFTP server should be run only if no more
secure method of supporting existing equipment can be
found.</description>

<Rule id="service_tftp_disabled" severity="medium">
<title>Disable tftp Service</title>
<description>The <tt>tftp</tt> service should be disabled.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="tftp" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="tftp" /></ocil>
<rationale>
Disabling the <tt>tftp</tt> service ensures the system is not acting
as a TFTP server, which does not provide encryption or authentication.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27055-3" stig="RHEL-06-000223" />
<oval id="service_tftp_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="1436" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_tftp-server_removed" severity="medium">
<title>Uninstall tftp-server Package</title>
<description>
<yum-macro install="false" package="tftp-server" />
</description>
<ocil>
<package-check-macro package="tftp-server" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
Removing the <tt>tftp-server</tt> package decreases the risk of the
accidental (or intentional) activation of tftp services.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26946-4" stig="RHEL-06-000222" />
<oval id="package_tftp-server_removed" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="305"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_tftp_removed">
<title>Remove tftp</title>
<description>Trivial File Transfer Protocol (TFTP) is a simple file transfer protocol,
typically used to automatically transfer configuration or boot files between systems.
TFTP does not support authentication and can be easily hacked. The package
<tt>tftp</tt> is a client program that allows for connections to a <tt>tftp</tt> server.
</description>
<ocil><yum-macro install="false" package="tftp"/></ocil>
<rationale>It is recommended that TFTP be remvoed, unless there is a specific need
for TFTP (such as a boot server). In that case, use extreme caution when configuring
the services.</rationale>
<ident cce="27448-0" />
<oval id="package_tftp_removed" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="tftpd_uses_secure_mode" severity="high">
<title>Ensure <tt>tftp</tt> Daemon Uses Secure Mode</title>
<description>If running the <tt>tftp</tt> service is necessary, it should be configured
to change its root directory at startup. To do so, ensure
<tt>/etc/xinetd.d/tftp</tt> includes <tt>-s</tt> as a command line argument, as shown in
the following example (which is also the default):
<pre>server_args = -s /var/lib/tftpboot</pre>
</description>
<rationale>Using the <tt>-s</tt> option causes the TFTP service to only serve files from the
given directory. Serving files from an intentionally-specified directory
reduces the risk of sharing files which should remain private.
</rationale>
<ocil clause="this flag is missing">
If TFTP is not installed, this is not applicable.  To determine if TFTP is installed, 
run the following command:
<pre>$ rpm -qa | grep tftp</pre>
<br /><br />
Verify <tt>tftp</tt> is configured by with the <tt>-s</tt> option by running the
following command:
<pre>grep "server_args" /etc/xinetd.d/tftp</pre>
The output should indicate the <tt>server_args</tt> variable is configured with the <tt>-s</tt>
flag, matching the example below:
<pre> $ grep "server_args" /etc/xinetd.d/tftp
server_args = -s /var/lib/tftpboot</pre>
</ocil>
<ident cce="27272-4" stig="RHEL-06-000338" />
<oval id="tftpd_uses_secure_mode" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="366"/>
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="talk">
<title>Chat/Messaging Services</title>
<description>
The talk software makes it possible for users to send and receive messages
across systems through a terminal session.
</description>

<Rule id="package_talk-server_removed" severity="medium">
<title>Uninstall talk-server Package</title>
<description>
<yum-macro install="false" package="talk-server" />
</description>
<ocil>
<package-check-macro package="talk-server" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
The talk software presents a security risk as it uses unencrypted protocols
for communications. Removing the <tt>talk-server</tt> package decreases the
risk of the accidental (or intentional) activation of talk services.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27427-4" />
<oval id="package_talk-server_removed" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_talk_removed">
<title>Uninstall talk Package</title>
<description>The <tt>talk</tt> package contains the client program for the
Internet talk protocol, which allows the user to chat with other users on
different systems. Talk is a communication program which copies lines from one
terminal to the terminal of another user.
</description>
<ocil><yum-macro install="false" package="talk"/></ocil>
<rationale>
The talk software presents a security risk as it uses unencrypted protocols
for communications. Removing the <tt>talk</tt> package decreases the
risk of the accidental (or intentional) activation of talk client program.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27373-0" />
<oval id="package_talk_removed" />
</Rule>

</Group>
</Group>
