<Group id="xwindows">
<title>X Window System</title>
<description>The X Window System implementation included with the
system is called X.org.</description>

<Group id="disabling_xwindows">
<title>Disable X Windows</title>
<description>Unless there is a mission-critical reason for the
system to run a graphical user interface, ensure X is not set to start
automatically at boot and remove the X Windows software packages.
There is usually no reason to run X Windows
on a dedicated server system, as it increases the system's attack surface and consumes
system resources. Administrators of server systems should instead login via
SSH or on the text console.</description>

<Rule id="xwindows_runlevel_setting">
<title>Disable X Windows Startup By Setting Runlevel</title>
<description>Setting the system's runlevel to 3 will prevent automatic startup
of the X server. To do so, ensure the following line in <tt>/etc/inittab</tt>
features a <tt>3</tt> as shown:
<pre>id:3:initdefault:</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not">
To verify the default runlevel is 3, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep initdefault /etc/inittab</pre>
The output should show the following:
<pre>id:3:initdefault:</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>Unnecessary services should be disabled to decrease the attack surface of the system.</rationale>
<ident cce="27119-7" />
<oval id="xwindows_runlevel_setting" />
<ref nist="AC-3" disa="366" stigid="RHEL-06-000290" srg="SRG-OS-000248" />
</Rule>


<Rule id="package_xorg-x11-server-common_removed">
<title>Remove the X Windows Package Group</title>
<description>Removing all packages which constitute the X Window System
ensures users or malicious software cannot start X.
To do so, run the following command:
<pre>$ sudo yum groupremove "X Window System"</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="it is not">
To ensure the X Windows package group is removed, run the following command:
<pre>$ rpm -qi xorg-x11-server-common</pre>
The output should be:
<pre>package xorg-x11-server-common is not installed</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>Unnecessary packages should not be installed to decrease the attack surface of the system.</rationale>
<ident cce="27198-1" />
<oval id="package_xorg-x11-server-common_removed" />
<ref disa="366" stigid="RHEL-06-000291" srg="SRG-OS-999999" />
</Rule>

<!-- to add: guidance in /etc/gdm/custom.conf for xdmcp disable, tcplisten disable -->
</Group>
</Group>
