<Group id="srg_support" hidden="true">
<title>Documentation to Support DISA OS SRG Mapping</title>
<description>These groups exist to document how the Red Hat Enterprise Linux
product meets (or does not meet) requirements listed in the DISA OS SRG, for
those cases where Groups or Rules elsewhere in scap-security-guide do
not clearly relate.
</description>

<Rule id="met_inherently">
<title>Product Meets this Requirement</title>
<rationale>
Red Hat Enterprise Linux meets this requirement by design.
<!-- We could include discussion of Common Criteria Testing if so desired here. -->
</rationale>
<ocil> RHEL6 supports this requirement and cannot be configured to be out of 
compliance. This is a permanent not a finding. 
</ocil> 
<description> 
This requirement is permanent not a finding. No fix is required.
</description>
<ref disa="56,26,42,66,68,135,223,131,132,133,134,85,159,1694,770,804,162,163,164,345,346,872,1493,1494,1495,226,1096,1111,386,34,35,156,186,99,1083,1089,1082,804,1209,1214,1237,1248,1265,1269,1314,1362,1368,1310,1311,1328,1399,1400,1425,1427,1499,1693,1665,1670,1674,206,154" />
</Rule> <!-- end met_inherently -->

<Rule id="unmet_impractical_guidance">
<title>Guidance Does Not Meet this Requirement Due to Impracticality or Scope</title>
<rationale>
The guidance does not meet this requirement.
The requirement is impractical or out of scope.
</rationale> 
<ocil> 
RHEL6 cannot support this requirement without assistance from an external 
application, policy, or service. This requirement is NA. 
</ocil> 
<description> 
This requirement is NA. No fix is required.
</description>
<ref disa="165,21,354,1094,371,372,535,537,539,780,1682,1383,370,37,221,25,28,29,30,24,1112,1126,1149,1157,1210,1211,1341,1372,1373,1374,1376,1377,1340,1352,1401,1555,1556,1150" />
</Rule> <!-- end unmet_impractical_guidance -->

<Rule id="unmet_impractical_product">
<title>Product Does Not Meet this Requirement Due to Impracticality or Scope</title>
<rationale>
The product does not meet this requirement. The requirement is impractical or out of scope.
</rationale>
<ocil> 
RHEL6 cannot support this requirement without assistance from an external 
application or server. This requirement is NA. 
</ocil>
<description>
This requirement is NA. No fix is required.
</description>
<ref disa="15,28,29,30,32,24,1695,1169,1170,1662,1395,553" /> 
</Rule> <!-- end unmet_impractical_product -->

<Rule id="requirement_unclear">
<title>Implementation of the Requirement is Unclear</title>
<rationale>
It is unclear how to satisfy this requirement.
</rationale> 
<ocil> 
RHEL6 does not support this requirement. This is a permanent finding. 
</ocil> 
<description>
This requirement is a permanent finding and cannot be fixed. An appropriate 
mitigation for the system must be implemented but this finding cannot be 
considered fixed.
</description>
<ref disa="20,31,218,219,1158,1291,1294,1295,1428,1500" />
</Rule> <!-- end requirement_unclear -->

<Rule id="new_rule_needed">
<title>A New Policy/Manual Rule is Needed</title>
<rationale>
A new Rule needs to be created in the scap-security-guide content.
</rationale> 
<ocil> 
RHEL6 does support this requirement but the guidance is not yet written. 
</ocil> 
<description> 
When the guidance is written, the fix will be forthcoming.
</description>
<ref disa="52,53,1009,1019,1159,1125,1140,1143" />
</Rule> <!-- end new_rule_needed -->

</Group>
