<Group id="integrity">
<title>Software Integrity Checking</title>
<description>
Both the AIDE (Advanced Intrusion Detection Environment)
software and the RPM package management system provide
mechanisms for verifying the integrity of installed software.
AIDE is the successor to the well-known Tripwire integrity
checker. The RPM package management system can conduct integrity
checks by comparing information in its metadata database with
files installed on the system.
<br /><br />
Integrity checking cannot <i>prevent</i> intrusions into your
system, but can detect that they have occurred. Requirements
for software integrity checking may be highly dependent on
the environment in which the system will be used.
</description>

<Group id="aide">
<title>Verify Integrity with AIDE</title>
<description>AIDE conducts integrity checks by comparing information
about files with previously-gathered information. Ideally, the AIDE
database should be created immediately after your system is built,
and before the system is connected to any network. AIDE is highly
configurable, with further configuration information located in
<tt>/usr/share/doc/aide-<i>VERSION</i></tt></description>
<ref disa="374,1069,1297,1589"/>


<Rule id="install_aide">
<title>Install AIDE</title>
<description>
Install the AIDE package with the command:
<pre># yum install aide</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the package is not installed">
<package-check-macro package="aide"/>
</ocil>
<rationale>
The AIDE package must be installed if it is to be available for integrity checking.
</rationale>
<ident cce="4209-3" />
<oval id="package_aide_installed" />
<ref nist="CM-6, CM-7, SC-28, SI-7" disa="1069"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="disable_prelink">
<title>Disable Prelinking</title>
<description>
The prelinking feature
changes binaries in an attempt to decrease their startup time.
In order to disable it, change or add the following line inside the file <tt>/etc/sysconfig/prelink</tt>:
<pre>PRELINKING=no</pre>
Next,  the following command to return binaries to a normal, non-prelinked state:
<pre># /usr/sbin/prelink -ua</pre>
</description>
<rationale>
The prelinking feature can interfere with the operation
of AIDE, because it changes binaries.
</rationale>
<ref nist="CM-6, SC-28, SI-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="aide_build_database">
<title>Build and Test AIDE Database</title>
<description>Run the following command to generate a new database:
<pre># /usr/sbin/aide --init</pre>
By default, the database will be written to the file <tt>/var/lib/aide/aide.db.new.gz</tt>.
Storing the database, the configuration file <tt>/etc/aide.conf</tt>, and the binary
<tt>/usr/sbin/aide</tt> (or hashes of these files), in a secure location (such as on read-only media) provides additional assurance about their integrity.
The newly-generated database can be installed as follows:
<pre># cp /var/lib/aide/aide.db.new.gz /var/lib/aide/aide.db.gz</pre>
To initiate a manual check, run the following command:
<pre># /usr/sbin/aide --check</pre>
If this check produces any unexpected output, investigate.
</description>
<rationale>
For AIDE to be effective, an initial database of "known-good" information about files
must be captured and it should be able to be verified against the installed files.
</rationale>
<ref nist="SC-28, SI-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="aide_periodic_cron_checking">
<title>Configure Periodic Execution of AIDE</title>
<description>
AIDE should be executed on a periodic basis to check for changes.
To implement a daily execution of AIDE at 4:05am using cron, add the following line to /etc/crontab:
<pre>05 4 * * * root /usr/sbin/aide --check</pre>
AIDE can be executed periodically through other means; this is merely one example.
</description>
<ocil clause="there is no output">
To determine that periodic AIDE execution has been scheduled, run the following command:
<pre># grep aide /etc/crontab</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
By default, AIDE does not install itself for periodic execution. Periodically
running AIDE may reveal unexpected changes in installed files.
</rationale>
<ref nist="CM-6, SC-28, SI-7" disa="416,1069,1166,1263"/>
</Rule>
<!--
<Group id="aide_verify_integrity_manually">
<title>Manually Verify Integrity of AIDE</title>
<description>
Manually verify the integrity of the AIDE binaries, configuration file, and database. Possibilities for doing
so include:
<br /><br />
1. Use sha1sum or md5sum to generate checksums on the files and then visually compare them to those
generated from the safely stored versions. This does not, of course, preclude the possibility that such
output could also be faked.
<br /><br />
2. Mount the stored versions on read-only media and run <tt>/bin/diff</tt> to verify that there are no differences
between the files.
<br /><br />
3. Copying the files to another system and performing the hash or file comparisons there may impart
additional confidence that the manual verification process is not being interfered with.
</description>
<rationale>
Because integrity checking is a means of intrusion detection and not intrusion prevention, it cannot be guaranteed
that the AIDE binaries, configuration files, or database have not been tampered with. An attacker could disable
or alter these files after a successful intrusion. Because of this, manual and frequent checks on these files is
recommended. The safely stored copies (or hashes) of the database, binary, and configuration file were created
earlier for this purpose.
</rationale>
<ref nist="SC-28, SI-7" />
</Group>
-->
</Group>

<Group id="rpm_verification">
<title>Verify Integrity with RPM</title>
<description>The RPM package management system includes the ability
to verify the integrity of installed packages by comparing the
installed files with information about the files taken from the
package metadata stored in the RPM database. Although an attacker
could corrupt the RPM database (analogous to attacking the AIDE
database as described above), this check can still reveal
modification of important files. To list which files on the system differ from what is expected by the RPM database:
<pre># rpm -qVa</pre>
See the man page for <tt>rpm</tt> to see a complete explanation of each column.
</description>

<Rule id="rpm_verify_permissions">
<title>Verify File Permissions with RPM</title>
<description>The RPM package management system can check file access
permissions of installed software packages, including many that are
important to system security. The following command will list which
files on the system have permissions that are different from what
is expected by the RPM database:
<pre># rpm -Va | grep '^.M'</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="there is output">
The following command will list which files on the system have permissions that are different from what
is expected by the RPM database:
<pre># rpm -Va | grep '^.M'</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Permissions on system binaries and configuration files that are too generous
could allow an unauthorized user to gain privileges that they should not have.
The permissions set by the vendor should be maintained. Any deviations from
this baseline should be investigated.</rationale>
<ident cce="14931-0" />
<oval id="rpm_verify_permissions" />
<ref nist="SI-7"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="rpm_verify_hashes">
<title>Verify File Hashes with RPM</title>
<description>The RPM package management system can check the hashes of
installed software packages, including many that are important to system
security. Run the following command to list which files on the system
have hashes that differ from what is expected by the RPM database:
<pre># rpm -Va | grep '^..5'</pre>
A "c" in the second column indicates that a file is a configuration file,
which may appropriately be expected to change.
</description>
<rationale>
The hash on important files like system executables should match the information given
by the RPM database. Executables with erroneous hashes could be a sign of nefarious activity
on the system.</rationale>
<ident cce="TODO" />
<oval id="rpm_verify_hashes" />
<ref nist="SI-7" disa="1496" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="additional_security_software">
<title>Additional Security Software</title>
<description>
Additional security software that is not provided or supported
by Red Hat can be installed to provide complementary or duplicative
security capabilities to those provided by the base platform.
</description>

<Rule id="install_hids">
<title>Install Intrusion Detection Software</title>
<description>
The base Red Hat platform already includes a sophisticated auditing system that
can detect intruder activity, as well as SELinux, which provides host-based
intrusion prevention capabilities by confining privileged programs and user
sessions which may become compromised.
<br/>
<br/>
Install an additional intrusion detection tool to provide complementary or
duplicative monitoring, reporting, and reaction capabilities to those of the base
platform.  For DoD systems, the McAfee Host-based Security System is provided
to fulfill this role.  
<!-- provide link to cybercom site? -->
<!-- need additional commentary: verify that HBSS (sans HIPS module) compatible w/SELinux -->
</description>
<ocil clause="no host-based intrusion detection tools are installed">
Inspect the system to determine if intrusion detection software has been installed.
Verify that the intrusion detection software is active. 
<!-- add instructions for HBSS?  the text in the RHEL 5 STIG is wrong as usual -->
</ocil>
<rationale>
Adding host-based intrusion detection tools can provide the capability to
automatically take actions in response to malicious behavior, which can provide
additional agility in reacting to network threats. These tools also often
include a reporting capability to provide network awareness of system, which
may not otherwise exist in an organization's systems management regime.
</rationale>
<ref disa="1263"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="install_antivirus">
<title>Install Virus Scanning Software</title>
<description>
Install virus scanning software, which uses signatures to search for the
presence of viruses on the filesystem. 
The McAfee uvscan virus scanning tool is provided for DoD systems.
Ensure virus definition files are no older than 7 days, or their last release.
<!-- need info here on where DoD admins can go to get this -->
Configure the virus scanning software to perform scans dynamically on all
accessed files.  If this is not possible, configure the
system to scan all altered files on the system on a daily
basis. If the system processes inbound SMTP mail, configure the virus scanner
to scan all received mail.
<!-- what's the basis for the IAO language? would not failure of a check
     imply a discussion, for every check in this document, 
     with the IAO (or SSO or ISSO or ISSM or whatever is the right acronym in your
     particular neighborhood) should occur? -->
</description>
<ocil clause="virus scanning software does not run daily, or has signatures that are out of date">
Inspect the system for a cron job or system service which executes
a virus scanning tool regularly.
<br/>
<!-- this should be handled as DoD-specific text in a future revision -->
To verify that the McAfee command line scan tool (uvscan) is scheduled for
regular execution, run the following command to check for a cron job:
<pre># grep uvscan /etc/cron* /var/spool/cron/*</pre>
This will reveal if and when the uvscan program will be run.
<br/>
To check on the age of uvscan virus definition files, run the following command:
<pre># cd /usr/local/uvscan
# ls -la avvscan.dat avvnames.dat avvclean.dat</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Virus scanning software can be used to detect if a system has been compromised by
computer viruses, as well as to limit their spread to other systems. 
</rationale>
<ref disa="1239,1668"/>
</Rule>

</Group>

</Group>
