<Group id="updating">
<title>Updating Software</title>
<description>The <tt>yum</tt> command line tool is used to install and
update software packages. The system also provides two graphical
package managers, <tt>pirut</tt> and <tt>pup</tt>. The <tt>pirut</tt>
tool is a graphical front-end for <tt>yum</tt> that allows users to install
and update packages while <tt>pup</tt> is a simple update tool for packages
that are already installed. In the <b>Applications</b> menu, <tt>pirut</tt>
is labeled <b>Add/Remove Software</b> and pup is labeled
<b>Software Updater</b>.
<br /><br />
Red Hat Enteprise Linux systems contain an embedded Installed Software
Catalog, or "RPM Database," which records metadata of installed packages.
The <tt>yum</tt>, <tt>pirut</tt>, and <tt>pup</tt> tools interface
with the Installed Software Catalog to ensure all system metadata is
accurate with regard to installed software and security patches, and
for this reason, their use is strongly encouraged.
</description>
<ref disa="1233" />

<Rule id="ensure_redhat_gpgkey_installed">
<title>Ensure Red Hat GPG Key Installed</title>
<description>
To ensure that the system can cryptographically verify base software
packages come from Red Hat (and to connect to the Red Hat Network to
receive them if desired), the Red Hat GPG key must properly be installed.  
To ensure that the GPG key is installed, run:
<pre># rhn_register</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the Red Hat GPG Key isn't installed">To ensure that the GPG key is isntalled, run:
<pre>$ rpm -q --queryformat "%{SUMMARY}\n" gpg-pubkey</pre>
The command should return the string:
<pre>gpg(Red Hat, Inc. (release key &lt;security@redhat.com&gt;)</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
This key is necessary to cryptographically verify that packages
are from Red Hat.
</rationale>
<ident cce="14440-2"/>
<oval id="package_red_hat_gpgkeys_installed" />
<ref nist="SI-2, SI-7, SC-13" disa="351"/>
<tested by="MM" on="20120928"/>
</Rule>

<!-- REMINDER: Before telling people to update their systems
     via the security_patches_up_to_date rule, we must
     ensure they have configured an update source! -->
<Rule id="ensure_gpgcheck_globally_activated">
<title>Ensure gpgcheck Enabled In Main Yum Configuration</title>
<description>The <tt>gpgcheck</tt> option should be used to ensure that
checking of an RPM package's signature always occurs prior to its
installation. To configure yum to check package signatures before installing
them, ensure that the following line appears in <tt>/etc/yum.conf</tt> in
the <tt>[main]</tt> section:
<pre>gpgcheck=1</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="GPG checking isn't enabled">
To determine whether <tt>yum</tt> is configured to use <tt>gpgcheck</tt>,
inspect <tt>/etc/yum.conf</tt> and ensure that the following appears in the
<tt>[main]</tt> section:
<pre>gpgcheck=1</pre>
A value of <tt>1</tt> indicates that <tt>gpgcheck</tt> is enabled. Absence of a
<tt>gpgcheck</tt> line or a setting of <tt>0</tt> indicates that it is
disabled.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Ensuring the validity of packages' cryptographic signatures prior to
installation ensures the provenance of the software and
protects against malicious tampering.
</rationale>
<ident cce="14914-6" />
<oval id="yum_gpgcheck_global_activation" />
<ref nist="SI-2" disa="352,663" />
<tested by="MM" on="20120928"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="ensure_gpgcheck_never_disabled">
<title>Ensure gpgcheck Enabled For All Yum Package Repositories</title>
<description>To ensure that signature checking is not disabled for
any repos, remove any lines from files in <tt>/etc/yum.repos.d</tt> of the form:
<pre>gpgcheck=0</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="GPG checking is disabled">
To determine whether <tt>yum</tt> has been configured to disable
<tt>gpgcheck</tt> for any repos,  inspect all files in
<tt>/etc/yum.repos.d</tt> and ensure that the following does not appear in any
sections:
<pre>gpgcheck=0</pre>
A value of <tt>0</tt> indicates that <tt>gpgcheck</tt> has been disabled for that repo. 
</ocil>
<rationale>
Ensuring that all packages' cryptographic signatures are valid prior to
installation ensures the provenance of the software and
protects against malicious tampering.
</rationale>
<ident cce="14813-0" />
<oval id="yum_gpgcheck_never_disabled" />
<ref nist="SI-2" disa="352,663"/>
<tested by="MM" on="20120928"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="security_patches_up_to_date">
<title>Ensure Software Patches Installed</title>
<description>If the system is joined to the Red Hat Network, a Red Hat Satellite Server,
or a yum server, run the following command to install updates:
<pre># yum update</pre>
If the system is not configured to use one of these sources, updates (in the form of RPM packages)
can be manually downloaded from the Red Hat Network and installed using <tt>rpm</tt>.
</description>
<ocil clause="updates are not installed">
If the system is joined to the Red Hat Network, a Red Hat Satellite Server, or
a yum server which provides updates, invoking the following command will
indicate if updates are available:
<pre># yum check-update</pre>
If the system is not configured to update from one of these sources,
run the following command to list when each package was last updated:
<pre>$ rpm -qa -last</pre>
Compare this to Red Hat Security Advisories (RHSA) listed at 
https://access.redhat.com/security/updates/active/
to determine if the system is missing applicable updates.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Installing software updates is a fundamental mitigation against
the exploitation of publicly-known vulnerabilities.
</rationale>
<ref nist="SI-2" disa="1227"/>
<tested by="MM" on="20120928"/>
</Rule>
</Group>
