<Group id="restrictions">
<title>Restrict Programs from Dangerous Execution Patterns</title>
<description>The recommendations in this section provide broad
protection against information disclosure or other misbehavior.
These protections are applied at the system initialization or
kernel level, and defend against certain types of badly-configured
or compromised programs.</description>

<Group id="daemon_umask">
<title>Set Daemon umask</title>
<description>The settings file <tt>/etc/sysconfig/init</tt> contains
settings which apply to all processes started at boot time. The
system umask must be set to at least 022, or daemon processes may
create world-writable files. The more restrictive setting 027
protects files, including temporary files and log files, from
unauthorized reading by unprivileged users on the system.
<br /><br />
If a particular daemon needs a less restrictive umask,
consider editing the startup script or sysconfig file of that
daemon to make a specific exception.</description>
<Value id="var-2.2.4.1.a" type="string"
operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>daemon umask</title>
<description>Enter umask for daemons</description>
<value selector="">027</value>
<value selector="022">022</value>
<value selector="027">027</value>
</Value>

<Rule id="set_daemon_umask">
<title>Set Daemon umask</title>
<description>The daemon umask should be set as
appropriate</description>
<ident cce="4220-0" />
<oval id="20053" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6"/>
</Rule>
</Group>

<Group id="coredumps">
<title>Disable Core Dumps</title>
<description>A core dump file is the memory image of an executable
program when it was terminated by the operating system due to
errant behavior. In most cases, only software developers would
legitimately need to access these files. The core dump files may
also contain sensitive information, or unnecessarily occupy large
amounts of disk space.
<br /><br />
By default, the system sets a soft limit to stop the creation
of core dump files for all users. This is accomplished in
<tt>/etc/profile</tt> with the line: <tt>ulimit -S -c 0 &gt; /dev/null
2$gt;&amp;1</tt>. However, compliance with this limit is voluntary; it is
a default intended only to protect users from the annoyance of
generating unwanted core files. Users can increase the allowed core
file size up to the hard limit, which is unlimited by default.
<br /><br />
Once a hard limit is set in <tt>/etc/security/limits.conf</tt>, the
user cannot increase that limit within his own session. If access
to core dumps is required, consider restricting them to only
certain users or groups. See the <tt>limits.conf</tt> man page for more
information.
<br /><br />
The core dumps of setuid programs are further protected. The
<tt>sysctl</tt> variable <tt>fs.suid_dumpable</tt> controls whether
the kernel allows core dumps from these programs at all. The default
value of 0 is recommended.</description>

<Rule id="disable_users_coredumps">
<title>Disable Core Dumps for all users</title>
<description>Core dumps for all users should be
disabled</description>
<ident cce="4225-9" />
<oval id="20055" />
<ref nist="SC-5" />
</Rule>


<Rule id="disable_setuid_coredumps">
<title>Disable Core Dumps for SUID programs</title>
<description>Core dumps for setuid programs should be
disabled</description>
<ident cce="4247-3" />
<oval id="20056" />
<ref nist="SI-11" />
</Rule>
</Group>

<Group id="enable_execshield_settings">
<title>Enable ExecShield</title>
<description>ExecShield comprises a number of kernel features to
provide protection against buffer overflows. These features include
random placement of the stack and other memory regions, prevention
of execution in memory that should only hold data, and special
handling of text buffers. This protection is enabled by default,
but the sysctl variables kernel.exec-shield and kernel.randomize va
space should be checked to ensure that it has not been disabled.
<br /><br />
ExecShield uses the segmentation feature on all x86 systems
to prevent execution in memory higher than a certain address. It
writes an address as a limit in the code segment descriptor, to
control where code can be executed, on a per-process basis. When
the kernel places a process's memory regions such as the stack and
heap higher than this address, the hardware prevents execution
there. However, this cannot always be done for all memory regions
in which execution should not occur, so follow guidance in Section
2.2.4.4 to further protect the system.</description>

<Rule id="enable_execshield">
<title>Enable ExecShield</title>
<description>ExecShield should be enabled</description>
<ident cce="4168-1" />
<oval id="20057" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="enable_randomize_va_space">
<title>Enable ExecShield randomized placement of virtual
memory regions</title>
<description>ExecShield randomized placement of virtual memory
regions should be enabled</description>
<rationale>
This makes it more difficult for an attacker to predict the location of
attack code they've introduced into the address space.  It also makes it 
more difficult for an attacker to know the
location of existing code in order to re-purpose it via ROP.
</rationale>
<ident cce="4146-7" />
<oval id="20058" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6" />
</Rule>
</Group>



<Group id="enable_nx">
<title>Enable Execute Disable (XD) or No Execute (NX) Support on
x86 Systems</title>
<description>Recent processors in the x86 family support the
ability to prevent code execution on a per memory page basis.
Generically and on AMD processors, this ability is called No
Execute (NX), while on Intel processors it is called Execute
Disable (XD). This ability can help prevent exploitation of buffer
overflow vulnerabilities and should be activated whenever possible.
Extra steps must be taken to ensure that this protection is
enabled, particularly on 32-bit x86 systems. Other processors, such
as Itanium and POWER, have included such support since inception
and the standard kernel for those platforms supports the
feature.</description>

<Group id="install_PAE_kernel_on_x86-32">
<title>Install New Kernel on Supported x86 Systems</title>
<description>Systems that are using the 64-bit x86 kernel package
do not need to install the kernel-PAE package because the 64-bit
x86 kernel already includes this support. However, if the system is
running 32-bit kernel package supports PAE and NX features as
determined in the previous section, the kernel-PAE package should
be installed to enable XD or NX support:
<br />
<pre>
# yum install kernel-PAE

</pre>
The installation process should also have conﬁgured the
bootloader to load the new kernel at boot. Verify this at reboot
and modify <tt>/etc/grub.conf</tt> if necessary.</description>
<warning category="hardware">The kernel-PAE package should not be
installed on older systems that do not support the XD or NX bit, as
this may prevent them from booting.</warning>
<Rule id="install_PAE_kernel_on_x86-32">
<title>Install New Kernel on Supported x86 Systems</title>
<description>Kernel support for the XD/NX processor feature should
be enabled</description>
<ident cce="4172-3" />
<oval id="20059" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>
</Group>
