<Group id="ssh">
<title>SSH Server</title>
<description>The SSH protocol is recommended for remote access (remote login and secure remote file transfer).
SSH provides both confidentiality and integrity for exchanged data but needs to be configured properly in term of:<br />
Cryptography usage, according to the current CVEs associated to the various cryptographic modes<br />
Authentication and autorization, depending on your needs but requiring some specific initial generic security<br />
consideration in the OpenSSH configuration writing
More detailed information is available from the OpenSSH project's website <weblink-macro link="http://www.openssh.org"/>. The Debian package for
server side implementation is called <tt>openssh-server</tt>.
</description>

<Value id="sshd_idle_timeout_value" type="number"
operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>SSH session Idle time</title>
<description>Specify duration of allowed idle time.</description>
<value selector="">300</value>
<value selector="5_minutes">300</value>
<value selector="10_minutes">600</value>
<value selector="15_minutes">900</value>
<value selector="60_minutes">3600</value>
<value selector="120_minutes">7200</value>
</Value>

<Value id="sshd_required" type="number"
operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>SSH is required to be installed</title>
<description>Specify if the Policy requires SSH to be installed. Used by SSH Rules
to determine if SSH should be uninstalled or configured.<br />
A value of 0 means that the policy doesn't care if OpenSSH server is installed or not. If it is installed, scanner will check for it's configuration, if it's not installed, the check will pass.<br />
A value of 1 indicates that OpenSSH server package is not required by the policy;<br />
A value of 2 indicates that OpenSSH server package is required by the policy.<br /></description>
<value selector="">0</value>
<value selector="no">1</value>
<value selector="yes">2</value>
</Value>

<Rule id="service_sshd_disabled">
<title>Disable SSH Server if possible (unusual cases)</title>
<description>Most of the time, the SSH server is needed. However, it can be disabled, do so.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="ssh" />
This is unusual, as SSH is a common method for encrypted and authenticated
remote access.
</description>
<oval id="service_sshd_disabled" />
</Rule>

<Group id="ssh_server">
<title>Configure OpenSSH Server if deployed</title>
<description>If the system needs to act as an SSH server, then
certain changes should be made to the OpenSSH daemon configuration
file <tt>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</tt>. The following recommendations can be
applied to this file. See the <tt>sshd_config(5)</tt> man page for more
detailed information.</description>

<Rule id="sshd_allow_only_protocol2" severity="high">
<title>Allow Only SSH Protocol 2</title>
<description>Only SSH protocol version 2 connections should be
permitted. The default setting in
<tt>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</tt> is correct, and can be
verified by ensuring that the following
line appears:
<pre>Protocol 2</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="it is not">
To check which SSH protocol version is allowed, run the following command:
<pre>$ sudo grep Protocol /etc/ssh/sshd_config</pre>
If configured properly, output should be <pre>Protocol 2</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
SSH protocol version 1 suffers from design flaws that
result in security vulnerabilities and
should not be used.
</rationale>
<ident cce="" />
<oval id="sshd_allow_only_protocol2" value="sshd_required" />
<ref nist="AC-17(7),IA-5(1)(c)" anssi="NT007(R1)" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="sshd_set_idle_timeout">
<title>Set SSH Idle Timeout Interval</title>
<description>SSH allows administrators to set an idle timeout interval.
After this interval has passed, the idle user will be automatically logged out.
<br /><br />
To set an idle timeout interval, edit the following line in <tt>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</tt> as
follows:
<pre>ClientAliveInterval <b>interval</b></pre>
The timeout <b>interval</b> is given in seconds. To have a timeout
of 15 minutes, set <b>interval</b> to 900.
<br /><br />
If a shorter timeout has already been set for the login
shell, that value will preempt any SSH
setting made here. Keep in mind that some processes may stop SSH
from correctly detecting that the user is idle.
</description>
<ocil clause="it is not">
Run the following command to see what the timeout interval is:
<pre>$ sudo grep ClientAliveInterval /etc/ssh/sshd_config</pre>
If properly configured, the output should be:
<pre>ClientAliveInterval 900</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Causing idle users to be automatically logged out
guards against compromises one system leading trivially
to compromises on another.
</rationale>
<ident cce="" />
<oval id="sshd_set_idle_timeout" value="sshd_idle_timeout_value" value2="sshd_required" />
<ref nist="AC-2(5),SA-8" pcidss="Req-8.1.8" />
</Rule>


<Rule id="sshd_set_keepalive">
<title>Set SSH Client Alive Count</title>
<description>To ensure the SSH idle timeout occurs precisely when the <tt>ClientAliveCountMax</tt> is set,
edit <tt>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</tt> as
follows:
<pre>ClientAliveCountMax 0</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="it is not">
To ensure the SSH idle timeout will occur when the <tt>ClientAliveCountMax</tt> is set, run the following command:
<pre>$ sudo grep ClientAliveCountMax /etc/ssh/sshd_config</pre>
If properly configured, output should be:
<pre>ClientAliveCountMax 0</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
This ensures a user login will be terminated as soon as the <tt>ClientAliveCountMax</tt>
is reached.
</rationale>
<ident cce="" />
<oval id="sshd_set_keepalive" value="sshd_required" />
<ref nist="AC-2(5),SA-8"  />
</Rule>

<Rule id="sshd_disable_root_login" severity="medium">
<title>Disable SSH Root Login</title>
<description>The root user should never be allowed to login to a
system directly over a network.
To disable root login via SSH, add or correct the following line
in <tt>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</tt>:
<pre>PermitRootLogin no</pre>
</description>
<ocil>
<sshd-check-macro option="PermitRootLogin" value="no" default="no" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
Permitting direct root login reduces auditable information about who ran
privileged commands on the system
and also allows direct attack attempts on root's password.
</rationale>
<ident cce="" />
<oval id="sshd_disable_root_login" />
<ref nist="AC-3,AC-6(2),IA-2(1)" anssi="NT007(R21)"  />
</Rule>


<Rule id="sshd_disable_empty_passwords" severity="high">
<title>Disable SSH Access via Empty Passwords</title>
<description>To explicitly disallow remote login from accounts with
empty passwords, add or correct the following line in
<tt>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</tt>:
<pre>PermitEmptyPasswords no</pre>
Any accounts with empty passwords should be disabled immediately, and PAM configuration
should prevent users from being able to assign themselves empty passwords.
</description>
<ocil>
<sshd-check-macro option="PermitEmptyPasswords" value="no" default="yes" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
Configuring this setting for the SSH daemon provides additional assurance that
remote login via SSH will require a password,
even in the event of misconfiguration elsewhere.
</rationale>
<ident cce="" />
<oval id="sshd_disable_empty_passwords" value="sshd_required" />
<ref nist="AC-3" anssi="NT007(R17)" />
</Rule>

</Group>
</Group>



