<Group id="accounts-banners">
<title>Warning Banners for System Accesses</title>
<description>Each system should expose as little information about
itself as possible.
<br /><br />
System banners, which are typically displayed just before a
login prompt, give out information about the service or the host's
operating system. This might include the distribution name and the
system kernel version, and the particular version of a network
service. This information can assist intruders in gaining access to
the system as it can reveal whether the system is running
vulnerable software. Most network services can be configured to
limit what information is displayed.
<br /><br />
Many organizations implement security policies that require a
system banner provide notice of the system's ownership, provide
warning to unauthorized users, and remind authorized users of their
consent to monitoring.</description>

<Value id="login_banner_text" type="string" operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>Login Banner Verbiage</title>
<description>Enter an appropriate login banner for your organization. Please note that new lines must
be expressed by the '\n' character.</description>
<!-- <value selector="any_text">.+</value> -->
<value selector="usgcb_default">
-- WARNING --\nThis system is for the use of authorized users only. Individuals\nusing this computer system without authority or in excess of their\nauthority are subject to having all their activities on this system\nmonitored and recorded by system personnel. Anyone using this\nsystem expressly consents to such monitoring and is advised that\nif such monitoring reveals possible evidence of criminal activity\nsystem personal may provide the evidence of such monitoring to law\nenforcement officials.
</value>
<value selector="dod_default">You are accessing a U.S. Government (USG) Information System (IS) that is provided for USG-authorized use only. By using this IS (which includes any device attached to this IS), you consent to the following conditions:
-The USG routinely intercepts and monitors communications on this IS for purposes including, but not limited to, penetration testing, COMSEC monitoring, network operations and defense, personnel misconduct (PM), law enforcement (LE), and counterintelligence (CI) investigations.
-At any time, the USG may inspect and seize data stored on this IS.
-Communications using, or data stored on, this IS are not private, are subject to routine monitoring, interception, and search, and may be disclosed or used for any USG-authorized purpose.
-This IS includes security measures (e.g., authentication and access controls) to protect USG interests -- not for your personal benefit or privacy.
-Notwithstanding the above, using this IS does not constitute consent to PM, LE or CI investigative searching or monitoring of the content of privileged communications, or work product, related to personal representation or services by attorneys, psychotherapists, or clergy, and their assistants. Such communications and work product are private and confidential. See User Agreement for details.
</value>
<value selector="dod_short">I've read &amp; consent to terms in IS user agreem't.</value>
</Value>

<Rule id="set_system_login_banner">
<title>Modify the System Login Banner</title>
<description>
To configure the system login banner:
<br /><br />
Edit <tt>/etc/issue</tt>. Replace the default text with a message
compliant with the local site policy or a legal disclaimer.

The DoD required text is either:
<br /><br />
<tt>You are accessing a U.S. Government (USG) Information System (IS) that is
provided for USG-authorized use only. By using this IS (which includes any
device attached to this IS), you consent to the following conditions: -The USG
routinely intercepts and monitors communications on this IS for purposes
including, but not limited to, penetration testing, COMSEC monitoring, network
operations and defense, personnel misconduct (PM), law enforcement (LE), and
counterintelligence (CI) investigations. -At any time, the USG may inspect and
seize data stored on this IS. -Communications using, or data stored on, this IS
are not private, are subject to routine monitoring, interception, and search,
and may be disclosed or used for any USG-authorized purpose. -This IS includes
security measures (e.g., authentication and access controls) to protect USG
interests- -not for your personal benefit or privacy. -Notwithstanding the
above, using this IS does not constitute consent to PM, LE or CI investigative
searching or monitoring of the content of privileged communications, or work
product, related to personal representation or services by attorneys,
psychotherapists, or clergy, and their assistants. Such communications and work
product are private and confidential. See User Agreement for details.</tt>
<br /><br />
or:
<br /><br />
<tt>I've read &amp; consent to terms in IS user agreement.</tt>
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not display the required banner">
To check if the system login banner is compliant,
run the following command:
<pre>$ cat /etc/issue</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Although unlikely to dissuade a serious attacker, the warning message
reinforces policy awareness during the logon process.
</rationale>
<ident cce="4060-0" />
<oval id="banner_etc_issue" value="login_banner_text"/>
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6, AC-8" disa="48,1384,1385,1386,1387,1388" />
</Rule>

<Group id="gui_login_banner">
<title>Implement a GUI Warning Banner</title>
<description>In the default graphical environment, users logging
directly into the system are greeted with a login screen provided
by the GNOME Display Manager (GDM). The warning banner should be
displayed in this graphical environment for these users.
The following sections describe how to configure the GDM login
banner.
</description>

<Rule id="enable_gdm_login_banner">
<title>Enable GUI Warning Banner</title>
<description>
To enable displaying a login warning banner in the GNOME
Display Manager's login screen, run the following command:
<pre>sudo -u gdm gconftool-2 \
  --type bool \
  --set /apps/gdm/simple-greeter/banner_message_enable true</pre>
To display a banner, this setting must be enabled and then
banner text must also be set.
</description>
<ocil clause="it is not">
To ensure a login warning banner is enabled, open the following file:
<pre>/etc/gconf/schemas/gdm-simple-greeter.schemas</pre>
Search for the <tt>banner_message_enable</tt> schema.
If properly configured, the <tt>default</tt> value should be <tt>true</tt>.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Although unlikely to dissuade a serious attacker, the warning message
reinforces policy awareness during the logon process.
</rationale>
<ident cce="4188-9" />
<oval id="banner_gui_enabled" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6, AC-8" disa="48,50" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="set_gdm_login_banner_text">
<title>Set GUI Warning Banner Text</title>
<description>
To set the text shown by the GNOME Display Manager
in the login screen, run the following command:
<pre>sudo -u gdm gconftool-2 \
  --type string \
  --set /apps/gdm/simple-greeter/banner_message_text \
  "Text of the warning banner here"</pre>
When entering a warning banner that spans several lines, remember
to begin and end the string with <tt>"</tt>. This command writes
directly to the file <tt>/var/lib/gdm/.gconf/apps/gdm/simple-greeter/%gconf.xml</tt>,
and this file can later be edited directly if necessary.
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not">
To ensure login warning banner text is properly set, open the following file:
<pre>/etc/gconf/schemas/gdm-simple-greeter.schemas</pre>
Search for the <tt>banner_message_text</tt> schema.
If properly configured, the proper banner text will appear within this schema.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Although unlikely to dissuade a serious attacker, the warning message
reinforces policy awareness during the logon process.
</rationale>
<ident cce="4188-9" />
<oval id="banner_gui_text_set" value="login_banner_text" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6, AC-8" disa="48,1384,1385,1386,1387,1388" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="user_list">
<title>Disable the User List</title>
<description>In the default graphical environment, users logging
directly into the system are greeted with a login screen that displays
all known users. This functionality should be disabled.
<br /><br />
Run the following command to disable the user list:
<pre>sudo -u gdm gconftool-2 \
  --type bool \
  --set /apps/gdm/simple-greeter/disable_user_list true</pre>
Leaving the user list enabled is a security risk since it allows anyone
with physical access to the system to quickly enumerate known user accounts
without logging in.
</description>
<Rule id="disable_user_list">
<title>Disable the User List</title>
<description>GDM's list of previously logged in users should not be displayed.</description>
<ref nist="AC-23, CM-6" />
</Rule>
</Group>

</Group>

