<Group id="srg_support" hidden="true">
<title>Documentation to Support DISA OS SRG Mapping</title>
<description>These groups exist to document how the Red Hat Enterprise Linux
product meets (or does not meet) requirements listed in the DISA OS SRG, for
those cases where Groups or Rules elsewhere in scap-security-guide do
not clearly relate.
</description>

<Group id="met_inherently" hidden="true">
<title>Product Meets this Requirement</title>
<description>
Red Hat Enterprise Linux meets this requirement by design.
<!-- We could include discussion of Common Criteria Testing if so 
     desired here. -->
</description>
<ref disa="131" />

<Rule id="audit_account_termination">
<title>The operating system must notify, as required, appropriate individuals for account termination.</title>
<rationale>The Red Hat Enterprise Linux Auditing Subsystem provides this functionality natively, placing this information in the audit logs for system administrator review.</rationale>
<ref disa="1686" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="audit_account_creation">
<title>The operating system must notify, as required, appropriate individuals when accounts are created.</title>
<rationale>The Red Hat Enterprise Linux Auditing Subsystem provides this functionality natively, placing this information in the audit logs for system administrator review.</rationale>
<ref disa="1683" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="enforce_DAC_per_user">
<title>The operating system must enforce a Discretionary Access Control (DAC) policy that includes or excludes access to the granularity of a single user</title>
<rationale>Red Hat Enterprise Linux enables Discretionary Access Control (DAC) policy natively, this functionality does not have to be specifically enabled or configured.</rationale>
<ref disa="1694" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="enforce_DAC_access_rights">
<title>The operating system must enforce a Discretionary Access Control (DAC) policy that limits propagation of access rights.</title>
<rationale>Red Hat Enterprise Linux enables Discretionary Access Control (DAC) policy natively, this functionality does not have to be specifically enabled or configured.</rationale>
<ref disa="1693" />

</Group>

<Group id="unmet_impractical_guidance" hidden="true">
<title>Guidance Does Not Meet this Requirement Due to Impracticality or Scope</title>
<description>
The guidance does not meet this requirement.
The requirement is impractical or out of scope.
</description>
<ref disa="354,1094" />

<Rule id="enforce_remote_connections">
<title>The operating system must enforce requirements for remote connections to the information system</title>
<rationale>The technical specifications to meet this policy are organizationally defined, and therefor generic guidance is not availabile.</rationale>
<ref disa="66" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="central_config_management">
<title>The operating system must employ automated mechanisms to centrally manage configuration settings</title>
<rationale>An organizational configuration management policy is out of scope of this security guide.</rationale>
<ref disa="370" />
</Rule>



</Group>

<Group id="unmet_impractical_product" hidden="true">
<title>Product Does Not Meet this Requirement Due to Impracticality or Scope</title>
<description>
The product does not meet this requirement.
The requirement is impractical or out of scope.
</description>

</Group>
</Group>
