<Group id="group-3.3">
<title>BaseServices</title>
<description>This section addresses the base services that are
configured to start up on boot in a RHEL5 default installation.
Some of these services listen on the network and should be treated
with particular discretion. The other services are local system
utilities that may or may not be extraneous. Each of these services
should be disabled if not required.</description>
<Group id="group-3.3.4">
<title>ISDN Support (isdn)</title>
<description>The ISDN service facilitates Internet connectivity in
the presence of an ISDN modem. If an ISDN modem is not being used,
disable this service:
<br />
<br />
<code># chkconfig isdn off</code></description>
<Rule id="rule-3.3.4.a">
<title>CCE-4286-1:ISDN Support (isdn)</title>
<description>The isdn service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4286-1" />
<oval id="20186" />
</Rule>
</Group>
<Group id="group-3.3.5">
<title>Kdump Kernel Crash Analyzer (kdump)</title>
<description>Kdump is a new kernel crash dump analyzer. It uses
kexec to boot a secondary kernel ('capture' kernel) following a
system crash. The kernel dump from the system crash is loaded into
the capture kernel for analysis.
<br />
<br />Unless the system is used for kernel development or testing,
disable the service:
<br />
<br />
<code># chkconfig kdump off</code></description>
<Rule id="rule-3.3.5.a">
<title>CCE-3425-6:Kdump Kernel Crash Analyzer (kdump)</title>
<description>The kdump service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="3425-6" />
<oval id="20187" />
</Rule>
</Group>
<Group id="group-3.3.9">
<title>Network Service (network)</title>
<description>The network service allows associated network
interfaces to access the network. This section contains general
guidance for controlling the operation of the service. For kernel
parameters which affect networking, see Section</description>
<Group id="group-3.3.9.3">
<title>Disable Zeroconf Networking</title>
<description>Zeroconf networking allows the system to assign itself
an IP address and engage in IP communication without a
statically-assigned address or even a DHCP server. Automatic
address assignment via Zeroconf (or DHCP) is not recommended.
<br />
<br />To disable Zeroconf automatic route assignment in the
169.245.0.0 subnet, add or correct the following line in
/etc/sysconfig/network:
<br />
<br />NOZEROCONF=yes
<br />
<br />Zeroconf addresses are in the network 169.254.0.0. The
networking scripts add entries to the system's routing table for
these addresses. Zeroconf address assignment commonly occurs when
the system is configured to use DHCP but fails to receive an
address assignment from the DHCP server.</description>
<Rule id="rule-3.3.9.3.a">
<title>CCE-14054-1:Disable Zeroconf Networking</title>
<description>Disable Zeroconf automatic route assignment in the
169.245.0.0 subnet.</description>
<ident cce="14054-1" />
<oval id="20193" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>

<Group id="group-3.3.12">
<title>Boot Caching (readahead early/readahead later)</title>
<description>The following services provide one-time caching of
files belonging to some boot services, with the goal of allowing
the system to boot faster.
<br />
<br />It is recommended that this service be disabled on most
machines:
<br />
<br />
<code># chkconfig readahead_early off
<br /># chkconfig readahead_later off
<br /></code>
<br />The readahead services do not substantially increase a
system's risk exposure, but they also do not provide great benefit.
Unless the system is running a specialized application for which
the file caching substantially improves system boot time, this
guide recommends disabling the services.</description>
<Rule id="rule-3.3.12.a">
<title>CCE-4421-4:Boot Caching (readahead early/readahead
later)</title>
<description>The readahead_early service should be
disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4421-4" />
<oval id="20196" />
</Rule>
<Rule id="rule-3.3.12.b">
<title>CCE-4302-6:Boot Caching (readahead early/readahead
later)</title>
<description>The readahead_later service should be
disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4302-6" />
<oval id="20197" />
</Rule>
</Group>
<Group id="group-3.3.14">
<title>Bluetooth Support</title>
<description>Bluetooth provides a way to transfer information
between devices such as mobile phones, laptops, PCs, printers,
digital cameras, and video game consoles over a short-range
wireless link. Any wireless communication presents a serious
security risk to sensitive or classified systems. Section 2.5.2
contains information on the related topic of wireless networking.
<br />
<br />Removal of hardware is the only way to ensure that the
Bluetooth wireless capability remains disabled. If it is completely
impractical to remove the Bluetooth hardware module, and site
policy still allows the device to enter sensitive spaces, every
effort to disable the capability via software should be made. In
general, acquisition policy should include provisions to prevent
the purchase of equipment that will be used in sensitive spaces and
includes Bluetooth capabilities.</description>
<Group id="group-3.3.14.1">
<title>Bluetooth Host Controller Interface Daemon
(bluetooth)</title>
<description>The bluetooth service enables the system to use
Bluetooth devices. If the system requires no Bluetooth devices,
disable this service:
<br />
<code># chkconfig bluetooth off</code></description>
<Rule id="rule-3.3.14.1.a">
<title>CCE-4355-4:Bluetooth Host Controller Interface Daemon
(bluetooth)</title>
<description>The bluetooth service should be
disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4355-4" />
<oval id="20200" />
</Rule>
</Group>


<Group id="group-3.3.14.2">
<title>Bluetooth Input Devices (hidd)</title>
<description>The hidd service provides support for Bluetooth input
devices. If the system has no Bluetooth input devices (e.g.
keyboard or mouse), disable this service:
<br />
<br />
<code># chkconfig hidd off</code></description>
<Rule id="rule-3.3.14.2.a">
<title>CCE-4377-8:Bluetooth Input Devices (hidd)</title>
<description>The hidd service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4377-8" />
<oval id="20201" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>
</Group>

