<Group id="group-3.9">
<title>DHCP</title>
<description>The Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) allows
systems to request and obtain an IP address and many other
parameters from a server.
<br />
<br />In general, sites use DHCP either to allow a large pool of
mobile or unknown machines to share a limited number of IP
addresses, or to standardize installations by avoiding static,
individual IP address configuration on hosts. It is recommended
that sites avoid DHCP as much as possible. Since DHCP
authentication is not well-supported, DHCP clients are open to
attacks from rogue DHCP servers. Such servers can give clients
incorrect information (e.g. malicious DNS server addresses) which
could lead to their compromise.
<br />
<br />If a machine must act as a DHCP client or server, configure
it defensively using the guidance in this section. This guide
recommends configuring networking on clients by manually editing
the appropriate files under /etc/sysconfig. It is also possible to
use the graphical front-end programs system-config-network and
system-config-network-tui, but these programs rewrite configuration
files from scratch based on their defaults – destroying any manual
changes – and should therefore be used with caution.</description>
<Group id="group-3.9.3">
<title>Disable DHCP Server if possible</title>
<description>If the dhcp package has been installed on a machine
which does not need to operate as a DHCP server, disable the
daemon:
<br />
<br />
<code># chkconfig dhcpd off
<br /></code>
<br />If possible, remove the software as well:
<br />
<br />
<code># yum erase dhcp
<br /></code>
<br />The DHCP server dhcpd is not installed or activated by
default. If the software was installed and activated, but the
system does not need to act as a DHCP server, it should be disabled
and removed. Unmanaged DHCP servers will provide faulty information
to clients, interfering with the operation of a legitimate site
DHCP server if there is one, or causing misconfigured machines to
exhibit unpredictable behavior if there is not.</description>
<Rule id="rule-3.9.3.a">
<title>CCE-4336-4:Disable DHCP Server if possible</title>
<description>The dhcpd service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4336-4" />
<oval id="20268" />
</Rule>
<Rule id="rule-3.9.3.b">
<title>CCE-4464-4:Uninstall DHCP Server if possible</title>
<description>The dhcp package should be uninstalled.</description>
<ident cce="4464-4" />
<oval id="20269" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>
