<Group id="ldap">
<title>LDAP</title>
<description>LDAP is a popular directory service, that is, a
standardized way of looking up information from a central database.
It is relatively simple to configure a RHEL5 machine to obtain
authentication information from an LDAP server. If your network
uses LDAP for authentication, be sure to configure both clients and
servers securely.</description>
<Group id="openldap_client">
<title>Configure OpenLDAP Clients</title>
<description>This guide recommends configuring OpenLDAP clients by
manually editing the appropriate configuration files. RHEL5
provides an automated configuration tool called authconfig and a
graphical wrapper for authconfig called
system-config-authentication. However, these tools do not give
sufficient flexibility over configuration. The authconfig tools do
not allow you to specify locations of SSL certificate files, which
is useful when trying to use SSL cleanly across several protocols.
They are also overly aggressive in placing services such as
netgroups and automounter maps under LDAP control, where it is
safer to use LDAP only for services to which it is relevant in your
environment.</description>
<warning category="general">Before configuring any machine to be an
LDAP client, ensure that a working LDAP server is present on the
network. See Section 3.12.3 for instructions on configuring an LDAP
server.</warning>
<Group id="openldap_tls">
<title>Configure LDAP to Use TLS for All Transactions</title>
<description>
<ol>
<li>Ensure a copy of the site's CA certificate has been placed in
the file /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem.</li>
<li>Configure LDAP to enforce TLS use and to trust certificates
signed by the site's CA. First, edit the file /etc/ldap.conf, and
add or correct the following lines:
<br />
<br />ssl start_tls
<br />tls_checkpeer yes
<br />tls_cacertdir /etc/pki/tls/CA
<br />tls_cacertfile /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem
<br />
<br />Then edit /etc/openldap/ldap.conf, and add or correct the
following lines:
<br />
<br />TLS_CACERTDIR /etc/pki/tls/CA
<br />TLS_CACERT /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</li>
</ol>
<br />
<br />Section 2.5.6 describes the system-wide configuration of SSL
for your enterprise. It is possible to place your certificate
information under some directory other than /etc/pki/tls, but using
a consistent directory structure across all SSL services at your
site is recommended. The LDAP server must be configured with a
certificate signed by the CA certificate named here.</description>
<Rule id="ldap_require_tls">
<title>Configure LDAP to Use TLS for All
Transactions</title>
<description>Clients require LDAP servers to provide valid
certificates for SSL communications.</description>
<ident cce="14894-0" />
<oval id="202885" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>

<Group id="openldap_server">
<title>Configure OpenLDAP Server</title>
<description>This section contains guidance on how to configure an
OpenLDAP server to securely provide information for use in a
centralized authentication service. This is not a comprehensive
guide to maintaining an OpenLDAP server, but may be helpful in
transitioning to an OpenLDAP infrastructure
nonetheless.</description>
<Group id="enabling_openldap_service">
<title>Install OpenLDAP Server RPM</title>
<description>Is this machine the OpenLDAP server? If so:
<br />
<br />
<code># yum install openldap-servers
<br /># chkconfig ldap on
<br /></code>
<br />The openldap-servers RPM is not installed by default on RHEL5
machines. It is needed only by the OpenLDAP server, not by the
clients which use LDAP for authentication.</description>
<Rule id="disable_openldap_service">
<title>Disable OpenLDAP service</title>
<description>The ldap service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="3501-4" />
<oval id="20289" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>
</Group>

