<Group id="mail">
<title>Mail Server Software</title>
<description>
Mail servers are used to send and receive email over the network.
Mail is a very common service, and Mail Transfer Agents (MTAs) are obvious 
targets of network attack. 
Ensure that machines are not running MTAs unnecessarily, 
and configure needed MTAs as defensively as possible.

Very few systems at any site should be configured to directly receive email over the 
network.  Users should instead use mail clients programs to retrieve email  
from a central server that support protocols such as IMAP or POP3.  
However, it is normal for most systems to be independently capable of sending email, 
for instance so that cron jobs can report output to an administrator. 
Most MTAs, including Postfix, support a submission-only mode in which mail can be sent from 
the local system to a central site MTA (or directly delivered to a local account), 
but the system still cannot receive mail directly over a network.

The <tt>alternatives</tt> program in RHEL permits selection of other mail server software 
(such as Sendmail), but Postfix is the default and is preferred.
Postfix was coded with security in mind and can also be more effectively contained by 
SELinux as its modular design has resulted in separate processes performing specific actions. 
More information is available on its website, http://www.postfix.org.</description>

<!-- postfix is installed by default on RHEL 6,
     but sendmail was the default on RHEL 5. -->

<!-- <Rule id="postfix_package_installation">
<title>The postfix package should be installed</title>
<description>TODO::INSERT</description>
<ident cce="14068-1" />
<oval id="package_postfix_installed" />
</Rule> -->
<Rule id="postfix_network_listening">
<title>Disable Postfix Network Listening</title>
<description>
Edit the file <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt> to ensure that only the following
<tt>inet_interfaces</tt> line appears:
<pre>
inet_interfaces = localhost
</pre>
</description>
<rationale>
This ensures that <tt>postfix</tt> accepts mail messages 
(such as cron job reports) from the local system only, 
and not from the network, which protects it from network attack.
</rationale>
<ident cce="15018-5" />
<oval id="postfix_network_listening_disabled" />
</Rule>
</Group>
