<Group id="ntp">
<title>Network Time Protocol</title>
<description>The Network Time Protocol is used to manage the system
clock over a network. Computer clocks are not very accurate, so
time will drift unpredictably on unmanaged systems. Central time
protocols can be used both to ensure that time is consistent among
a network of machines, and that their time is consistent with the
outside world.
<br /><br />
Local time synchronization is recommended for all networks.
If every machine on your network reliably reports the same time as
every other machine, then it is much easier to correlate log
messages in case of an attack. In addition, a number of
cryptographic protocols (such as Kerberos) use timestamps to
prevent certain types of attacks. If your network does not have
synchronized time, these protocols may be unreliable or even
unusable.
<br /><br />
Depending on the specifics of the network, global time
accuracy may be just as important as local synchronization, or not
very important at all. If your network is connected to the
Internet, it is recommended that you make use of a public
timeserver, since globally accurate timestamps may be necessary if
you need to investigate or respond to an attack which originated
outside of your network.
<br /><br />
Whether or not you use an outside timeserver, configure the
network to have a small number of machines operating as NTP
servers, and the remainder obtaining time information from those
internal servers.</description>

<Group id="configuring_ntpd">
<title>Configure an NTP Server</title>
<description>The site’s NTP server contacts a central NTP server,
probably either one provided by your ISP or a public time server,
to obtain accurate time data. The server then allows other machines
on your network to request the time data.
<br /><br />
The NTP server configuration file is located at <tt>/etc/ntp.conf</tt>.</description>
<Group id="enabling_ntpd">
<title>Enable the NTP Daemon</title>
<description>If this machine is an NTP server, ensure that <tt>ntpd</tt> is enabled at boot time.</description>

<Rule id="enable_ntpd">
<title>Enable the NTP Daemon</title>
<description>The <tt>ntpd</tt> service should be enabled.
<pre># chkconfig ntpd on</pre>
</description>
<rationale>
Enabling the <tt>ntpd</tt> service ensures that the local system time will be the same on all computers. This is essential for authentication services such as Kerberos, but it is also important for maintaining accurate logs and auditing possible security breaches.
</rationale>
<ident cce="4376-0" />
<oval id="service_ntpd_enabled" />
<ref disa="160" />
</Rule>
</Group>

<Group id="configuring_ntpd_client">
<title>Specify a Remote NTP Server for Time Data</title>
<description>Find the IP address of an appropriate remote NTP server and configure <tt>ntpd</tt> to use it to obtain accurate time data. If your site does not require time data to be accurate, but merely to be synchronized among local machines, this step can be omitted, and the NTP server will default to providing time data from the local clock. However, it is a good idea to periodically synchronize the clock to some source of accurate time, even if it is not appropriate to do so automatically.</description>

<Rule id="ntpd_specify_remote_server">
<title>Specify a Remote NTP Server for Time Data</title>
<description>A remote NTP Server for time synchronization should be specified. Edit the file <tt>/etc/ntp.conf</tt>, and add or correct the following lines, substituting the IP address of a remote NTP server for <em>server-ip</em>:
<pre>restrict server-ip mask 255.255.255.255 nomodify notrap noquery
server server-ip</pre>
This NTP server must contact a remote server to obtain accurate data, so NTP's configuration must allow that remote data to be used to modify the system clock. The restrict line changes the default access permissions for that remote server. The server line specifies the remote server as the preferred NTP server for time data. If you intend to synchronize to more than one server, specify restrict and server lines for each server.
<br /><br />
Note: It would be possible to specify a hostname, rather than an IP address, for the server field. However, the restrict setting applies only to network blocks of IP addresses, so it is considered more maintainable to use the IP address in both fields.</description>
<rationale>
Synchonizing <tt>ntpd</tt> with an accurate clock makes it easier to collate system logs from multiple sources or correlate computer events with real time events.
</rationale>
<ident cce="4385-1" />
<oval id="ntp_remote_server" />
<ref disa="160" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>
</Group>

