<Group id="obsolete">
<title>Obsolete Services</title>
<description>This section discusses a number of network-visible
services which have historically caused problems for system
security, and for which disabling or severely limiting the service
has been the best available guidance for some time. As a result of
this consensus, these services are not installed as part of RHEL6
by default.
<br /><br />
Organizations which are running these services should
prioritize switching to more secure services which provide the
needed functionality. If it is absolutely necessary to run one of
these services for legacy reasons, care should be taken to restrict
the service as much as possible, for instance by configuring host
firewall software (see Section 2.5.5) to restrict access to the
vulnerable service to only those remote hosts which have a known
need to use it.</description>

<Group id="inetd_and_xinetd">
<title>Inetd and Xinetd</title>
<description>Is there an operational need to run the deprecated
inetd or xinetd software packages? If not, ensure that they are
removed from the system:
<br />
<pre>
# yum erase inetd xinetd

</pre>
Beginning with Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5, the <tt>xinetd</tt> service
is no longer installed by default. This change represents increased
awareness that the dedicated network listener model does not
improve security or reliability of services, and that restriction
of network listeners is better handled using a granular model such
as SELinux than using <tt>xinetd</tt>'s limited security
options.</description>

<Rule id="disable_inetd">
<title>Disable Inetd</title>
<description>The <tt>inetd</tt> service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4234-1" />
<oval id="service_inetd_disabled" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="disable_xinetd">
<title>Disable Xinetd</title>
<description>The <tt>xinetd</tt> service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4252-3" />
<oval id="service_xinetd_disabled" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="uninstall_inetd">
<title>Uninstall Inetd</title>
<description>The <tt>inetd</tt> package should be uninstalled.</description>
<ident cce="4023-8" />
<oval id="package_inetd_removed" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="uninstall_xinetd">
<title>Uninstall Xinetd</title>
<description>The <tt>xinetd</tt> package should be uninstalled.</description>
<ident cce="4164-0" />
<oval id="package_xinetd_removed" />
</Rule>

</Group>
<Group id="telnet">
<title>Telnet</title>
<description>Is there a mission-critical reason for users to access
the system via the insecure telnet protocol, rather than the more
secure SSH protocol? If not, ensure that the telnet server is
removed from the system:
<br />
<pre>
# yum erase telnet-server

</pre>
The telnet protocol uses unencrypted network communication,
which means that data from the login session, including passwords
and all other information transmitted during the session, can be
stolen by eavesdroppers on the network, and also that outsiders can
easily hijack the session to gain authenticated access to the
telnet server. Organizations which use telnet should be actively
working to migrate to a more secure protocol.
<br /><br />

See Section 3.5 for information about the SSH service.</description>

<Rule id="disable_telnet_service" severity="high">
<title>Disable telnet service</title>
<description>
To disable the telnet service, run the following command:
<pre>
# chkconfig telnet off
</pre>
</description>
<rationale>
The telnet protocol uses unencrypted network communication, which 
means that data from the login session, including passwords and 
all other information transmitted during the session, can be 
stolen by eavesdroppers on the network.  The telnet protocol is also 
subject to man in the middle attacks. 
</rationale>
<ident cce="3390-2" />
<oval id="service_telnetd_disabled" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="uninstall_telnet_server">
<title>Uninstall Telnet server</title>
<description>The <tt>telnet-server</tt> package should be
uninstalled.</description>
<ident cce="4330-7" />
<oval id="package_telnet-server_removed" />
</Rule>

</Group>


<Group id="r_services">
<title>Rlogin, Rsh, and Rexec</title>
<description>The Berkeley r-commands are legacy services which
allow cleartext remote access and have an insecure trust
model.</description>

<Rule id="no_rsh_trust_files" severity="high">
<title>Remove Rsh Trust Files</title>
<description>The files /etc/hosts.equiv and ~/.rhosts list remote hosts and users that are trusted
by the local system when using the rshd daemon.</description>
<rationale>These files are not needed and should be removed.</rationale>
<ident cce="TODO" />
<oval id="no_rsh_trusted_host_files" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="uninstall_rsh-server">
<title>Remove the Rsh Server Commands from the
System</title>
<description>The <tt>rsh-server</tt> package should be
uninstalled.</description>
<ident cce="4308-3" />
<oval id="package_rsh-server_removed" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="disable_rcp" severity="high">
<title>Disable rexec</title>
<description>The <tt>rexec</tt> service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="undefined" />
<oval id="service_rexec_disabled" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="disable_rsh" severity="high">
<title>Disable rsh</title>
<description>The <tt>rsh</tt> service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4141-8" />
<oval id="service_rsh_disabled" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="disable_rlogin">
<title>Disable rlogin</title>
<description>The <tt>rlogin</tt> service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="3537-8" />
<oval id="service_rlogin_disabled" />
</Rule>

</Group>
<Group id="nis">
<title>NIS</title>
<description>The NIS client service <tt>ypbind</tt> is not activated by
default. In the event that it was activated at some point, disable
it by executing the command:
<br />
<pre>
# chkconfig ypbind off

</pre>
The NIS server package is not installed by default. In the
event that it was installed at some point, remove it from the
system by executing the command:
<br />
<pre>
# yum erase ypserv

</pre>
The Network Information Service (NIS), also known as 'Yellow
Pages' (YP), and its successor NIS+ have been made obsolete by
Kerberos, LDAP, and other modern centralized authentication
services. NIS should not be used because it suffers from security
problems inherent in its design, such as inadequate protection of
important authentication information.</description>

<Rule id="uninstall_ypserv">
<title>Uninstall NIS</title>
<description>The <tt>ypserv</tt> package should be
uninstalled.</description>
<ident cce="4348-9" />
<oval id="package_ypserv_removed" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="disable_ypbind">
<title>Disable NIS</title>
<description>The <tt>ypbind</tt> service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="3705-1" />
<oval id="service_ypbind_disabled" />
</Rule>
</Group>

<Group id="tftp">
<title>TFTP Server</title>
<description>Is there an operational need to run the deprecated
TFTP server software? If not, ensure that it is removed from the
system:
<br />
<pre>
# yum erase tftp-server

</pre>
TFTP is a lightweight version of the FTP protocol which has
traditionally been used to configure networking equipment. However,
TFTP provides little security, and modern versions of networking
operating systems frequently support configuration via SSH or other
more secure protocols. A TFTP server should be run only if no more
secure method of supporting existing equipment can be
found.</description>

<Rule id="uninstall_tftp-server">
<title>Uninstall TFTP Server</title>
<description>The tftp-server package should be
uninstalled.</description>
<ident cce="3916-4" />
<oval id="package_tftp-server_removed" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="disable_tftp">
<title>Disable TFTP Server</title>
<description>The tftp service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4273-9" />
<oval id="service_tftp_disabled" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="tftpd_uses_secure_mode" severity="high">
<title>TFTP Daemon Uses Secure Mode</title>
<description>Should the TFTP service be required for legitimate purposes it should be configured to change
the root directory on startup using the "-s" command line argument.</description>
<rationale>Using the "-s" command line argument causes the TFTP service to only serve files from the
given directory.</rationale>
<ident cce="TODO" />
<oval id="tftpd_uses_secure_mode" />
</Rule>

</Group>
</Group>
