<Group id="printing">
<title>Print Support</title>
<description>The Common Unix Printing System (CUPS) service
provides both local and network printing support. A system running
the CUPS service can accept print jobs from other systems, process
them, and send them to the appropriate printer. It also provides an
interface for remote administration through a web browser. The CUPS
service is installed and activated by default. The project homepage
and more detailed documentation are available at
http://www.cups.org.
<br /><br />
The HP Linux Imaging and Printing service (HPLIP) is a
separate package that provides support for some of the additional
features that HP printers provide that CUPS may not necessarily
support. It relies upon the CUPS service.</description>
<reference href="http://www.cups.org">CUPS is the standards-based,
open source printing system</reference>
<Group id="hplip_service">
<title>The HP Linux Imaging and Printing (HPLIP) Toolkit</title>
<description>The HPLIP package is an HP printing support utility
that is installed and enabled in a default installation. The HPLIP
package is comprised of two separate components. The first is the
main HPLIP service and the second is a smaller subcomponent called
HPIJS. HPLIP is a feature-oriented network service that provides
higher level printing support (such as bi-directional I/O,
scanning, photo card, and toolbox functionality). HPIJS is a lower
level basic printing driver that provides basic support for
non-PostScript HP printers.</description>
<Group id="disabling_hplip_service">
<title>Disable HPLIP Service if Possible</title>
<description>Since the HPIJS driver will still function without the
added HPLIP service, HPLIP should be disabled unless the specific
higher level functions that HPLIP provides are needed by a
non-PostScript HP printer on the system.
<br />
<pre>
# chkconfig hplip off

</pre>
Note: If installing the HPLIP package from scratch, it should
be noted that HPIJS can be installed directly without HPLIP. Please
see the FAQ at the HPLIP web site at
http://hplip.sourceforge.net/faqs.html for more information on how
to do this.</description>
<Rule id="disable_hplip_service">
<title>Disable HPLIP Service if Possible</title>
<description>The <tt>hplip</tt> service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="4425-5" />
<oval id="20266" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>
</Group>

