<Group id="xwindows">
<title>X Window System</title>
<description>The X Window System implementation included with the
system is called X.org.</description>

<Group id="disabling_xwindows">
<title>Disable X Windows if Possible</title>
<description>Unless there is a mission-critical reason for the
machine to run a GUI login screen, prevent X from starting
automatically at boot. There is usually no reason to run X Windows
on a dedicated server machine, since administrators can login via
SSH or on the text console.</description>
<Group id="xwindows_startx">
<title>Lock Down X Windows startx Configuration if
Necessary</title>
<description>If X is not to be started at boot time but the
software must remain installed, users will be able to run X
manually using the startx command. In some cases, this runs X with
a configuration which is less safe than the default. Follow these
instructions to mitigate risk from this
configuration.</description>
<Group id="xwindows_no_listen">
<title>Disable X Window System Listening</title>
<description>To prevent X.org from listening for remote
connections, create the file /etc/X11/xinit/xserverrc and fill it
with the following line:
<br />
<br />exec X :0 -nolisten tcp $@
<br />
<br />One of X.org's features is the ability to provide remote
graphical display. This feature should be disabled unless it is
required. If the system uses runlevel 5, which is the default, the
GDM display manager starts X safely, with remote listening
disabled. However, if X is started from the command line with the
startx command, then the server will listen for new connections on
X's default port, 6000.
<br />
<br />See the xinit(1), startx(1), and Xserver(1) man pages for
more information.</description>
<Rule id="disable_xwindows_listening">
<title>Disable X Window System Listening</title>
<description>Disable the ability to provide remote graphical
display</description>
<ident cce="4074-1" />
<oval id="20248" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>
</Group>

<Group id="xwindows_configuration">
<title>Configure X Windows if Necessary</title>
<description>If there is a mission-critical reason for this machine
to run a GUI, improve the security of the default X configuration
by following the guidance in this section.</description>
<Group id="xwindows_banner">
<title>Create Warning Banners for GUI Login Users</title>
<description>Edit the file /etc/gdm/custom.conf. Locate the
[greeter] section, and correct that section to contain the lines:
<br />
<br />[greeter]
<br />InfoMsgFile=/etc/issue
<br />
<br />See Section 2.3.7 for an explanation of banner file use. This
setting will cause the system greeting banner to be displayed in a
box prior to GUI login. If the default banner font is
inappropriate, it can be changed by specifying the InfoMsgFont
directive as well, for instance:
<br />
<br />InfoMsgFont=Sans 12</description>
<Rule id="set_gui_login_banner">
<title>Create Warning Banners for GUI Login
Users</title>
<description>Enable warning banner for GUI login</description>
<ident cce="3717-6" />
<oval id="20249" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>
</Group>
