<Group id="ftp">
<title>FTP Server</title>
<description>FTP is a common method for allowing remote access to
files. Like telnet, the FTP protocol is unencrypted, which means
that passwords and other data transmitted during the session can be
captured and that the session is vulnerable to hijacking.
Therefore, running the FTP server software is not recommended.
<br /><br />
However, there are some FTP server configurations which may
be appropriate for some environments, particularly those which
allow only read-only anonymous access as a means of downloading
data available to the public.</description>

<Rule id="service_unencrypted_ftp_disabled">
<title>Disable Unencrypted FTP Services</title>
<description>
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="vsftpd" />
</description>
<ocil>
<service-check-macro enable="false" service="vsftpd" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
Running unencrypted FTP server software provides a network-based avenue
of attack, and should be disabled if not needed.
Furthermore, the FTP protocol is unencrypted and creates
a risk of compromising sensitive information.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN004800" />
<oval id="service_unencrypted_ftp_disabled" />
<ref nist="ECSC-1" disa="366" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ftp_log_transactions">
<title>Enable Logging of All FTP Transactions</title>
<description>Add or correct the following configuration options within the <tt>vsftpd</tt>
configuration file, located at <tt>/etc/vsftpd/vsftpd.conf</tt>:
<pre>xferlog_enable=YES
xferlog_std_format=NO
log_ftp_protocol=YES</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="xferlog_enable is missing, or is not set to yes">
Find if logging is applied to the FTP daemon.
<br/><br/>
Procedures:
<br/><br/>
If vsftpd is started by xinetd the following command will indicate the xinetd.d startup file:
<pre># grep vsftpd /etc/xinetd.d/*</pre>
<pre># grep server_args <i>vsftpd xinetd.d startup file</i></pre>
This will indicate the vsftpd config file used when starting through xinetd.
If the <i>server_args</i> line is missing or does not include the vsftpd configuration file, then the default config file (/etc/vsftpd/vsftpd.conf) is used.
<pre># grep xferlog_enable <i>vsftpd config file</i></pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>To trace malicious activity facilitated by the FTP service, it must be configured to ensure that all commands sent to
the FTP server are logged using the verbose vsftpd log
format. The default vsftpd log file is <tt>/var/log/vsftpd.log</tt>.</rationale>
<warning category="general">If verbose logging to <tt>vsftpd.log</tt> is done, sparse logging of downloads to <tt>/var/log/xferlog</tt> will not also occur. However, the information about what files were downloaded is included in the information logged to <tt>vsftpd.log</tt></warning>
<ident stig="GEN004980" />
<oval id="ftp_log_transactions" />
<ref nist="ECAR-1,ECAR-2,ECAR-3" disa="130" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ftp_default_umask">
<title>FTP Umask Must Be 077.</title>
<description>
All FTP users must have a default umask of 077.
</description>
<rationale>
The umask controls the default access mode assigned to newly 
created files. An umask of 077 limits new files to mode 700 
or less permissive. Although umask is stored as a 4-digit 
number, the first digit representing special access 
modes is typically ignored or required to be zero (0).
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN005040" />
<oval id="ftp_default_umask" />
<ref nist="ECCD-1,ECCD-2" disa="225" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ftp_ftpusers_file_empty">
<title>Ftpusers File Contains Users</title>
<description>
The ftpusers file must contain account names not allowed to use FTP.
</description>
<rationale>
The ftpusers file contains a list of accounts not allowed to use FTP to transfer files. 
If the file does not contain the names of all accounts not authorized to use FTP, then 
unauthorized use of FTP may take place.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN004900" />
<oval id="ftp_ftpusers_file_empty" />
<ref nist="ECCD-1,ECCD-2" disa="225" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ftp_ftpusers_file_exists">
<title>Ftpusers File Exists</title>
<description>
The ftpusers file must exist.
</description>
<rationale>
The ftpusers file contains a list of accounts not allowed to use FTP to transfer files. 
If this file does not exist, then unauthorized accounts can utilize FTP.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN004880" />
<oval id="ftp_ftpusers_file_exists" />
<ref nist="ECCD-1,ECCD-2" disa="225" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ftp_anonymous_shell">
<title>FTP User Has Shell</title>
<description>
Anonymous FTP accounts must not have a functional shell.
</description>
<rationale>
If an anonymous FTP account has been configured to use a functional shell, 
attackers could gain access to the shell if the account is compromised.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN005000" />
<oval id="ftp_anonymous_shell" />
<ref nist="ECCD-1,ECCD-2" disa="225" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="tftpd_user_shell">
<title>TFTP User Has Shell</title>
<description>
The TFTP daemon must be configured to vendor specifications, including 
a dedicated TFTP user account, a non-login shell such as /bin/false, 
and a home directory owned by the TFTP user.
</description>
<rationale>
If TFTP has a valid shell, it increases the likelihood someone could 
log on to the TFTP account and compromise the system.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN005120" />
<oval id="tftpd_user_shell" />
<ref nist="ECSC-1" disa="225" />
</Rule>

</Group> <!-- <Group id="ftp"> -->
