<Group id="nfs_and_rpc">
<title>NFS and RPC</title>
<description>The Network File System is a popular distributed filesystem for
the Unix environment, and is very widely deployed.  This section discusses the
circumstances under which it is possible to disable NFS and its dependencies,
and then details steps which should be taken to secure
NFS's configuration. This section is relevant to machines operating as NFS
clients, as well as to those operating as NFS servers.
</description>

<Group id="disabling_nfs">
<title>Disable All NFS Services if Possible</title>
<description>If there is not a reason for the system to operate as either an
NFS client or an NFS server, follow all instructions in this section to disable
subsystems required by NFS.
</description>
<warning category="general">The steps in this section will prevent a machine
from operating as either an NFS client or an NFS server. Only perform these
steps on machines which do not need NFS at all.</warning>

<Group id="removing_nfs_services">
<title>Remove Services Used Only by NFS</title>
<description>If NFS is not needed, remove the NFS client daemons portmap and rpcbind.
<br /><br />
All of these daemons run with elevated privileges, and many listen for network
connections. If they are not needed, they should be disabled to improve system
security posture.</description>

<Rule id="package_rpc_removed">
<title>Remove portmap and rpcbind Packages</title>
<description>The <tt>portmap</tt> and <tt>rpcbind</tt> packages can be uninstalled with
the following command:
<pre># yum erase portmap rpcbind</pre>
</description>
<ocil><package-check-macro package="portmap" /> </ocil>
<ident stig="GEN003815" />
<oval id="package_rpc_removed" />
<ref nist="ECSC-1" disa="305" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="disabling_nfs_services">
<title>Disable Services Used Only by NFS</title>
<description>If NFS is not needed, disable the NFS client daemons nfslock, rpcgssd, and rpcidmapd.
<br /><br />
All of these daemons run with elevated privileges, and many listen for network
connections. If they are not needed, they should be disabled to improve system
security posture.</description>

<Rule id="service_rpc_disabled">
<title>Disable portmap and rpcbind Services</title>
<description>The rpcbind service increase the attack surface of 
the system and should only be used when needed.  The rpcbind service 
are used by a variety of services using Remote Procedure Calls (RPCs).
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="rpcbind" />
</description>
<ident stig="GEN003810" />
<oval id="service_rpc_disabled" />
<ref nist="ECSC-1" disa="1436" />
</Rule>

</Group>
</Group>

<Group id="nfs_configuring_all_machines">
<title>Configure All Machines which Use NFS</title>
<description>The steps in this section are appropriate for all machines which
run NFS, whether they operate as clients or as servers.</description>

<Group id="nfs_configuring_clients">
<title>Configure NFS Clients</title>
<description>The steps in this section are appropriate for machines which operate as NFS clients.</description>

<Rule id="nfs_mount_option_nosuid_remote_filesystems" severity="medium">
<title>Mount Remote Filesystems with nosuid</title>
<description>
<mount-desc-macro option="nosuid" part="any NFS mounts" />
</description>
<ocil clause="the setting does not show">
To verify the <tt>nosuid</tt> option is configured for all NFS mounts, run the following command:
<pre>$ mount  | grep nfs</pre>
All NFS mounts should show the <tt>nosuid</tt> setting in parentheses.  This is not applicable if NFS is 
not implemented.
</ocil>
<rationale>NFS mounts should not present suid binaries to users. Only vendor-supplied suid executables
should be installed to their default location on the local filesystem.</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN005900" />
<oval id="nfs_mount_option_nosuid_remote_filesystems" />
<ref nist="ECPA-1" disa="225" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="nfs_configuring_servers">
<title>Configure NFS Servers</title>
<description>The steps in this section are appropriate for machines which operate as NFS servers.</description>

<Rule id="nfs_no_anonymous">
<title>Specify UID and GID for Anonymous NFS Connections</title>
<description>To specify the UID and GID for remote root users, edit the <tt>/etc/exports</tt> file and add the following for each export:
<pre>
anonuid=-1
anongid=-1
</pre>
</description>
<rationale>Specifying the anonymous UID and GID as -1 ensures that the remote root user is mapped to a local account which has no permissions on the system.</rationale>
<oval id="nfs_no_anonymous" />
<ident stig="GEN005820" />
<ref nist="ECSC-1,IAIA-1,IAIA-2" disa="62" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="nfs_enforce_host_access">
<title>All Exports Must Define Allowed Targets</title>
<description>When configuring NFS exports, ensure that each export line in <tt>/etc/exports</tt> contains
a list of hosts which are allowed to access that export. If no hosts are specified on an export line,
then that export is available to any remote host which requests it. All lines of the exports file should
specify the hosts (or subnets, if needed) which are allowed to access the exported directory, so that
unknown or remote hosts will be denied.
<br /><br />
Authorized hosts can be specified in several different formats:
<ul>
<li>Name or alias that is recognized by the resolver</li>
<li>Fully qualified domain name</li>
<li>IP address</li>
<li>IP subnets in the format <tt>address/netmask</tt> or <tt>address/CIDR</tt></li>
</ul>
</description>
<rationale>The NFS access option limits user access to the specified level. 
This assists in protecting exported file systems.  If access is not restricted, 
unauthorized hosts may be able to access the system's NFS exports.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN005840" />
<oval id="nfs_enforce_host_access" />
<ref nist="ECSC-1" disa="366" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="nfs_use_root_squashing_all_exports">
<title>Use Root-Squashing on All Exports</title>
<description>If a filesystem is exported using root squashing, requests from root on the client
are considered to be unprivileged (mapped to a user such as nobody). This provides some mild
protection against remote abuse of an NFS server. Root squashing is enabled by default, and
should not be disabled.
<br /><br />
Ensure that no line in <tt>/etc/exports</tt> contains the option <tt>no_root_squash</tt>.
</description>
<rationale>If the NFS server allows root access to local file systems from remote hosts, this
access could be used to compromise the system.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN005880" />
<oval id="nfs_use_root_squashing_all_exports" />
<ref nist="EBRP-1" disa="225" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="nfs_no_insecure_locks_exports" severity="high">
<title>Ensure Insecure File Locking is Not Allowed</title>
<description>By default the NFS server requires secure file-lock requests,
which require credentials from the client in order to lock a file. Most NFS
clients send credentials with file lock requests, however, there are a few
clients that do not send credentials when requesting a file-lock, allowing the
client to only be able to lock world-readable files. To get around this, the
<tt>insecure_locks</tt> option can be used so these clients can access the
desired export. This poses a security risk by potentially allowing the client
access to data for which it does not have authorization.
Remove any instances of the 
<tt>insecure_locks</tt> option from the file <tt>/etc/exports</tt>.
</description>
<ocil clause="there is output">
To verify insecure file locking has been disabled, run the following command:
<pre># grep insecure_locks /etc/exports</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>Allowing insecure file locking could allow for sensitive data to be
viewed or edited by an unauthorized user.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN000000-LNX00560" />
<oval id="nfs_no_insecure_locks_exports" />
<ref nist="IAIA-1,IAIA-2" disa="225,764" />
</Rule>

</Group> <!-- nfs_configuring_servers -->

</Group>
</Group>
