<Group id="network">
<title>Network Configuration and Firewalls</title>
<description>Most machines must be connected to a network of some
sort, and this brings with it the substantial risk of network
attack. This section discusses the security impact of decisions
about networking which must be made when configuring a system.
<br /><br />
This section also discusses firewalls, network access
controls, and other network security frameworks, which allow
system-level rules to be written that can limit an attackers' ability
to connect to your system. These rules can specify that network
traffic should be allowed or denied from certain IP addresses,
hosts, and networks. The rules can also specify which of the
system's network services are available to particular hosts or
networks.</description>

<Group id="network_disable_unused_interfaces">
<title>Disable Unused Interfaces</title>
<description>Network interfaces expand the attack surface of the 
system.  Unused interfaces are not monitored or controlled, and 
should be disabled.
<br /><br />
If the system does not require network communications but still
needs to use the loopback interface, remove all files of the form
<tt>ifcfg-<i>interface</i></tt> except for <tt>ifcfg-lo</tt> from
<tt>/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts</tt>:
<pre>$ sudo rm /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-<i>interface</i></pre>
If the system is a standalone machine with no need for network access or even
communication over the loopback device, then disable this service.
<systemd-service-macro enable="false" service="network" />
</description>
</Group> 

<Rule id="network_disable_ddns_interfaces" severity="medium">
<title>Disable Client Dynamic DNS Updates</title>
<description>
Dynamic DNS allows clients to dynamically update their own DNS records.
The updates are transmitted by unencrypted means which can reveal information
to a potential malicious user. If the system does not require Dynamic DNS,
remove all <tt>DHCP_HOSTNAME</tt> references from the
<tt>/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-<i>interface</i></tt> scripts. If
<tt>dhclient</tt> is used, remove all <tt>send host-name <i>hostname</i></tt>
references from the <tt>/etc/dhclient.conf</tt> configuration file and/or any
reference from the <tt>/etc/dhcp</tt> directory.
</description>
<ocil clause="client Dynamic DNS updates are not disabled">
To verify that clients cannot automatically update DNS records, perform the
following:
<pre>$ grep -i dhcp_hostname /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-*</pre>
<pre>$ grep -rni "send host-name" /etc/dhclient.conf /etc/dhcp</pre>
The output should return no results.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Dynamic DNS updates transmit unencrypted information about a system
including its name and address and should not be used unless needed.
</rationale>
<oval id="network_disable_ddns_interfaces" />
<ref nist="CM-6(b)" disa="366" ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227"  />
</Rule>

<Rule id="network_disable_zeroconf">
<title>Disable Zeroconf Networking</title>
<description>Zeroconf networking allows the system to assign itself an IP
address and engage in IP communication without a statically-assigned address or
even a DHCP server. Automatic address assignment via Zeroconf (or DHCP) is not
recommended. To disable Zeroconf automatic route assignment in the 169.254.0.0
subnet, add or correct the following line in <tt>/etc/sysconfig/network</tt>:
<pre>NOZEROCONF=yes</pre>
</description>
<rationale>Zeroconf addresses are in the network 169.254.0.0. The networking
scripts add entries to the system's routing table for these addresses. Zeroconf
address assignment commonly occurs when the system is configured to use DHCP
but fails to receive an address assignment from the DHCP server.
</rationale>
<oval id="network_disable_zeroconf" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="network_sniffer_disabled" severity="medium">
<title>Ensure System is Not Acting as a Network Sniffer</title>
<description>The system should not be acting as a network sniffer, which can
capture all traffic on the network to which it is connected. Run the following
to determine if any interface is running in promiscuous mode:
<pre>$ ip link | grep PROMISC</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="any network device is in promiscuous mode">
Promiscuous mode of an interface can be disabled with the following command:
<pre>$ sudo ip link set dev <tt>device_name</tt> promisc off</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Network interfaces in promiscuous mode allow for the capture of all network traffic
visible to the system. If unauthorized individuals can access these applications, it
may allow them to collect information such as logon IDs, passwords, and key exchanges
between systems.
<br /><br />
If the system is being used to perform a network troubleshooting function, the use of these
tools must be documented with the Information Systems Security Manager (ISSM) and restricted
to only authorized personnel.
</rationale>
<oval id="network_sniffer_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7,CM-7(2).1(i),,MA-3" disa="366" ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227"  />
</Rule>

</Group>
