<Group id="xwindows">
<title>X Window System</title>
<description>The X Window System implementation included with the
system is called X.org.</description>

<Group id="disabling_xwindows">
<title>Disable X Windows</title>
<description>Unless there is a mission-critical reason for the
system to run a graphical user interface, ensure X is not set to start
automatically at boot and remove the X Windows software packages.
There is usually no reason to run X Windows
on a dedicated server machine, as it increases the system's attack surface and consumes
system resources. Administrators of server systems should instead login via
SSH or on the text console.</description>

<Rule id="xwindows_runlevel_setting" severity="medium">
<title>Disable X Windows Startup By Setting Default Target</title>
<description>Systems that do not require a graphical user interface should only boot by
default into <tt>multi-user.target</tt> mode. This prevents accidental booting of the system
into a <tt>graphical.target</tt> mode. Setting the system's default target to
<tt>multi-user.target</tt> will prevent automatic startup of the X server. To do so, run:
<pre>$ systemctl set-default multi-user.target</pre>
You should see the following output:
<pre>rm '/etc/systemd/system/default.target'
ln -s '/usr/lib/systemd/system/multi-user.target' '/etc/systemd/system/default.target'</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the X windows display server is running and/or has not been disabled">
To verify the default target is multi-user, run the following command:
<pre>$ systemctl get-default</pre>
The output should show the following:
<pre>multi-user.target</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>Services that are not required for system and application processes
must not be active to decrease the attack surface of the system. X windows has a
long history of security vulnerabilities and should not be used unless approved
and documented.</rationale>
<oval id="xwindows_runlevel_setting" />
<ref nist="AC-17(8).1(ii)" disa="366" ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_xorg-x11-server-common_removed" severity="medium">
<title>Remove the X Windows Package Group</title>
<description>By removing the xorg-x11-server-common package, the system no longer has X Windows
installed. If X Windows is not installed then the system cannot boot into graphical user mode.
This prevents the system from being accidentally or maliciously booted into a <tt>graphical.target</tt>
mode. To do so, run the following command:
<pre>$ sudo yum groupremove "X Window System"</pre>
<pre>$ sudo yum remove xorg-x11-server-common</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the X Windows package group or xorg-x11-server-common has not be removed">
To ensure the X Windows package group is removed, run the following command:
<pre>$ rpm -qi xorg-x11-server-common</pre>
The output should be:
<pre>package xorg-x11-server-common is not installed</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>Unnecessary service packages must not be installed to decrease the attack surface of the system. X windows has a long history of security
vulnerabilities and should not be installed unless approved and documented.
</rationale>
<oval id="package_xorg-x11-server-common_removed" />
<ref nist="AC-17(8).1(ii)" disa="366" cis="3.2" ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" />
</Rule>

<!-- to add: guidance in /etc/gdm/custom.conf for xdmcp disable, tcplisten disable -->
</Group>
</Group>

