<Group id="network-wireless">
<title>Wireless Networking</title>
<description>Wireless networking, such as 802.11
(WiFi) and Bluetooth, can present a security risk to sensitive or
classified systems and networks. Wireless networking hardware is
much more likely to be included in laptop or portable systems than
desktops or servers. 
<br /><br />
Removal of hardware provides the greatest assurance that the wireless
capability remains disabled. Acquisition policies often include provisions to
prevent the purchase of equipment that will be used in sensitive spaces and
includes wireless capabilities. If it is impractical to remove the wireless
hardware, and policy permits the device to enter sensitive spaces as long
as wireless is disabled, efforts should instead focus on disabling wireless capability
via software.</description>

<Group id="wireless_software">
<title>Disable Wireless Through Software Configuration</title>
<description>If it is impossible to remove the wireless hardware
from the device in question, disable as much of it as possible
through software. The following methods can disable software
support for wireless networking, but note that these methods do not
prevent malicious software or careless users from re-activating the
devices.</description>

<Rule id="kernel_module_bluetooth_disabled" severity="medium">
<title>Disable Bluetooth Kernel Modules</title>
<description>The kernel's module loading system can be configured to prevent
loading of the Bluetooth module. Add the following to
the appropriate <tt>/etc/modprobe.d</tt> configuration file
to prevent the loading of the Bluetooth module:
<pre>install net-pf-31 /bin/true
install bluetooth /bin/true</pre>
</description>
<ocil>
<module-disable-check-macro module="bluetooth" />
<module-disable-check-macro module="net-pf-31" />
</ocil>
<rationale>If Bluetooth functionality must be disabled, preventing the kernel
from loading the kernel module provides an additional safeguard against its
activation.</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN007660" />
<oval id="kernel_module_bluetooth_disabled" />
<ref nist="ECSC-1" disa="1551" />
</Rule>

</Group><!--<Group id="wireless_software">-->
</Group><!--<Group id="network-wireless">-->
