<Group id="updating">
<title>Updating Software</title>
<description>The <tt>yum</tt> command line tool is used to install and
update software packages. The system also provides a graphical
software update tool in the <b>System</b> menu, in the <b>Administration</b> submenu,
called <b>Software Update</b>.
<br /><br />
Red Hat Enterprise Linux systems contain an installed software catalog called
the RPM database, which records metadata of installed packages. Consistently using
<tt>yum</tt> or the graphical <b>Software Update</b> for all software installation
allows for insight into the current inventory of installed software on the system.
</description>

<Rule id="ensure_redhat_gpgkey_installed" severity="high">
<title>Ensure Red Hat GPG Key Installed</title>
<description>
To ensure the system can cryptographically verify base software
packages come from Red Hat (and to connect to the Red Hat Network to
receive them), the Red Hat GPG key must properly be installed.  
To install the Red Hat GPG key, run:
<pre>$ sudo subscription-manager register</pre>
If the system is not connected to the Internet or an RHN Satellite,
then install the Red Hat GPG key from trusted media such as
the Red Hat installation CD-ROM or DVD. Assuming the disc is mounted
in <tt>/media/cdrom</tt>, use the following command as the root user to import
it into the keyring:
<pre>$ sudo rpm --import /media/cdrom/RPM-GPG-KEY</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the Red Hat GPG Key is not installed">
To ensure that the GPG key is installed, run:
<pre>$ rpm -q --queryformat "%{SUMMARY}\n" gpg-pubkey</pre>
The command should return the string below:
<pre>gpg(Red Hat, Inc. (release key 2)  &lt;security@redhat.com&gt;</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
The Red Hat GPG key is necessary to cryptographically verify packages
are from Red Hat.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26506-6" />
<oval id="ensure_redhat_gpgkey_installed" />
<ref nist="SI-7,MA-1(b)" disa="351" pcidss="Req-6.2" stigid="RHEL-06-000008"
srg="SRG-OS-000090" />
</Rule>

<!-- REMINDER: Before telling people to update their systems
     via the security_patches_up_to_date rule, we must
     ensure they have configured an update source! -->
<Rule id="ensure_gpgcheck_globally_activated" severity="medium">
<title>Ensure gpgcheck Enabled In Main Yum Configuration</title>
<description>The <tt>gpgcheck</tt> option controls whether
RPM packages' signatures are always checked prior to installation.
To configure yum to check package signatures before installing
them, ensure the following line appears in <tt>/etc/yum.conf</tt> in
the <tt>[main]</tt> section:
<pre>gpgcheck=1</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="GPG checking is not enabled">
To determine whether <tt>yum</tt> is configured to use <tt>gpgcheck</tt>,
inspect <tt>/etc/yum.conf</tt> and ensure the following appears in the
<tt>[main]</tt> section:
<pre>gpgcheck=1</pre>
A value of <tt>1</tt> indicates that <tt>gpgcheck</tt> is enabled. Absence of a
<tt>gpgcheck</tt> line or a setting of <tt>0</tt> indicates that it is
disabled.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Ensuring the validity of packages' cryptographic signatures prior to
installation ensures the authenticity of the software and
protects against malicious tampering.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26709-6" />
<oval id="ensure_gpgcheck_globally_activated" />
<ref nist="SI-7,MA-1(b)" disa="352,663" pcidss="Req-6.2" stigid="RHEL-06-000013"
srg="SRG-OS-000103" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ensure_gpgcheck_never_disabled" severity="low">
<title>Ensure gpgcheck Enabled For All Yum Package Repositories</title>
<description>To ensure signature checking is not disabled for
any repos, remove any lines from files in <tt>/etc/yum.repos.d</tt> of the form:
<pre>gpgcheck=0</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="GPG checking is disabled">
To determine whether <tt>yum</tt> has been configured to disable
<tt>gpgcheck</tt> for any repos,  inspect all files in
<tt>/etc/yum.repos.d</tt> and ensure the following does not appear in any
sections:
<pre>gpgcheck=0</pre>
A value of <tt>0</tt> indicates that <tt>gpgcheck</tt> has been disabled for that repo. 
</ocil>
<rationale>
Ensuring all packages' cryptographic signatures are valid prior to
installation ensures the authenticity of the software and
protects against malicious tampering.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26647-8" />
<oval id="ensure_gpgcheck_never_disabled" />
<ref nist="SI-7,MA-1(b)" disa="352,663" pcidss="Req-6.2" stigid="RHEL-06-000015"
srg="SRG-OS-000103" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="security_patches_up_to_date" severity="medium">
<title>Ensure Software Patches Installed</title>
<description>If the system is joined to the Red Hat Network, a Red Hat Satellite Server,
or a yum server, run the following command to install updates:
<pre>$ sudo yum update</pre>
If the system is not configured to use one of these sources, updates (in the form of RPM packages)
can be manually downloaded from the Red Hat Network and installed using <tt>rpm</tt>.
</description>
<!-- Directly define remotely located OVAL to be executed when scanning this rule -->
<check system="http://oval.mitre.org/XMLSchema/oval-definitions-5">
  <check-content-ref href="https://www.redhat.com/security/data/oval/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux_6.xml" />
</check>
<ocil clause="updates are not installed">
If the system is joined to the Red Hat Network, a Red Hat Satellite Server, or
a yum server which provides updates, invoking the following command will
indicate if updates are available:
<pre>$ sudo yum check-update</pre>
If the system is not configured to update from one of these sources,
run the following command to list when each package was last updated:
<pre>$ rpm -qa -last</pre>
Compare this to Red Hat Security Advisories (RHSA) listed at
<weblink-macro link="https://access.redhat.com/security/updates/active/"/>
to determine if the system is missing applicable updates.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Installing software updates is a fundamental mitigation against
the exploitation of publicly-known vulnerabilities.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27635-2" />
<!-- Particular OVAL check is defined directly via <check> element above -->
<!-- DO NOT REFERENCE an OVAL id here !!! -->
<ref nist="SI-2,MA-1(b)" disa="1227,1233" pcidss="Req-6.2" stigid="RHEL-06-000011"
srg="SRG-OS-000191" />
</Rule>
</Group>
