<Group id="network">
<title>Network Configuration and Firewalls</title>
<description>Most machines must be connected to a network of some
sort, and this brings with it the substantial risk of network
attack. This section discusses the security impact of decisions
about networking which must be made when configuring a system.
<br /><br />
This section also discusses firewalls, network access
controls, and other network security frameworks, which allow
system-level rules to be written that can limit attackers' ability
to connect to your system. These rules can specify that network
traffic should be allowed or denied from certain IP addresses,
hosts, and networks. The rules can also specify which of the
system's network services are available to particular hosts or
networks.</description>

<Rule id="network_disable_unused_interfaces">
<title>Disable Unused Interfaces</title>
<description>If the system does not require network communications but still needs to use the loopback interface, remove all files of the form <tt>ifcfg-interface</tt> except for <tt>ifcfg-lo</tt> from <tt>/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts</tt>:
<pre># rm /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-interface</pre>
If the system is a standalone machine with no need for network access or even communication over the loopback device, then disable this service with the following:
<pre># chkconfig network off</pre>
</description>
<rationale>The network interfaces expand the attack surface of a system.  If they are not needed they should be disabled.</rationale>
<!--<ident cce="TODO" />-->
<!--TODO:MANUAL<oval id="network_disable_unused_interfaces" />-->
</Rule>

<Rule id="network_disable_zeroconf">
<title>Disable Zeroconf Networking</title>
<description>Zeroconf networking allows the system to assign itself an IP address and engage in IP communication without a statically-assigned address or even a DHCP server. Automatic address assignment via Zeroconf (or DHCP) is not recommended.  To disable Zeroconf automatic route assignment in the 169.245.0.0 subnet, add or correct the following line in <tt>/etc/sysconfig/network</tt>:
<pre>NOZEROCONF=yes</pre>
</description>
<rationale>Zeroconf addresses are in the network 169.254.0.0. The networking scripts add entries to the system’s routing table for these addresses. Zeroconf address assignment commonly occurs when the system is configured to use DHCP but fails to receive an address assignment from the DHCP server.</rationale>
<ident cce="14054-1" />
<!--<oval id="network_disable_zeroconf" />-->
</Rule>

</Group>
