<Group id="network-wireless">
<title>Wireless Networking</title>
<description>Wireless networking (sometimes referred to as 802.11
or Wi-Fi) presents a serious security risk to sensitive or
classified systems and networks. Wireless networking hardware is
much more likely to be included in laptop or portable systems than
desktops or servers. See Section 3.3.14 for information on
Bluetooth wireless support. Bluetooth serves a different purpose
and possesses a much shorter range, but it still presents serious
security risks.
<br /><br />
Removal of hardware is the only way to absolutely ensure that
the wireless capability remains disabled. If it is completely
impractical to remove the wireless hardware, and site policy still
allows the device to enter sensitive spaces, every effort to
disable the capability via software should be made. In general,
acquisition policy should include provisions to prevent the
purchase of equipment that will be used in sensitive spaces and
includes wireless capabilities.</description>

<Group id="wireless_software">
<title>Disable Wireless Through Software Configuration</title>
<description>If it is impossible to remove the wireless hardware
from the device in question, disable as much of it as possible
through software. The following methods can disable software
support for wireless networking, but note that these methods do not
prevent malicious software or careless users from re-activating the
devices.</description>

<Rule id="wireless_disable_in_bios">
<title>Disable Wireless in BIOS</title>
<description>Some systems that include built-in wireless support offer the ability to disable the device through the BIOS. This is system-specific; consult your hardware manual or explore the BIOS setup during boot.</description>
<ident cce="3628-5" />
<!--TODO:OCIL <oval id="wireless_disable_in_bios" />-->
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="deactivate_wireless_interfaces">
<title>Deactivate Wireless Interfaces</title>
<description>Deactivating the wireless interfaces should prevent
normal usage of the wireless capability.
<br /><br />
First, identify the interfaces available with the command:
<pre># ifconfig -a</pre>
>Additionally,the following command may also be used to
determine whether wireless support ('extensions') is included for a
particular interface, though this may not always be a clear
indicator:
<pre># iwconfig</pre>
After identifying any wireless interfaces (which may have
names like <tt>wlan0</tt>, <tt>ath0</tt>, <tt>wifi0</tt>, <tt>em1</tt> or
<tt>eth0</tt>), deactivate the interface with the command:
<pre># ifdown interface</pre>
These changes will only last until the next reboot. To
disable the interface for future boots, remove the appropriate
interface file from <tt>/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts</tt>:
<pre># rm /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-interface</pre>
</description>
<ident cce="4276-2" />
<oval id="wireless_disable_interfaces" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="wireless_disable_drivers">
<title>Disable Wireless Drivers</title>
<description>Removing the kernel drivers that provide support for wireless Ethernet devices will prevent users from easily activating the devices. To remove the wireless drivers from the system:
<pre># rm -r /lib/modules/<i>kernelversion(s)</i>/kernel/drivers/net/wireless</pre>
</description>
<warning category="general">This command must also be repeated every time the kernel is upgraded.</warning>
<ident cce="4170-7" />
<oval id="wireless_disable_drivers" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

</Group><!--<Group id="wireless_software">-->
</Group><!--<Group id="network-wireless">-->
