<Group id="network">
<title>Network Configuration and Firewalls</title>
<description>Most machines must be connected to a network of some
sort, and this brings with it the substantial risk of network
attack. This section discusses the security impact of decisions
about networking which must be made when configuring a system.
<br /><br />
This section also discusses firewalls, network access
controls, and other network security frameworks, which allow
system-level rules to be written that can limit an attackers' ability
to connect to your system. These rules can specify that network
traffic should be allowed or denied from certain IP addresses,
hosts, and networks. The rules can also specify which of the
system's network services are available to particular hosts or
networks.</description>

<Group id="network_disable_unused_interfaces">
<title>Disable Unused Interfaces</title>
<description>Network interfaces expand the attack surface of the 
system.  Unused interfaces are not monitored or controlled, and 
should be disabled.
<br /><br />
If the system does not require network communications but still
needs to use the loopback interface, remove all files of the form
<tt>ifcfg-<i>interface</i></tt> except for <tt>ifcfg-lo</tt> from
<tt>/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts</tt>:
<pre># rm /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-<i>interface</i></pre>
If the system is a standalone machine with no need for network access or even
communication over the loopback device, then disable this service.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="network" />
</description>
</Group> 

<Group id="network_restrict_access">
<title>Restrict Access to Network Configuration Changes</title>
<description>The network configuration should only be allowed to be modified by 
authorized users.</description>

<Rule id="sysconfig_networking_userctl_ifcfg" severity="medium">
<title>Network interfaces must not be configured to allow user control.</title>
<description>
</description>
<rationale>Configuration of network interfaces should be limited to privileged users.  
Manipulation of network interfaces may result in a Denial of Service or bypass of network 
security mechanisms.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN003581" />
<oval id="sysconfig_networking_userctl_ifcfg" />
<ref nist="ECLP-1" disa="225" />
</Rule>
</Group> 

</Group>
