<Group id="accounts-banners">
<title>Warning Banners for System Accesses</title>
<description>Each system should expose as little information about
itself as possible.
<br /><br />
System banners, which are typically displayed just before a
login prompt, give out information about the service or the host's
operating system. This might include the distribution name and the
system kernel version, and the particular version of a network
service. This information can assist intruders in gaining access to
the system as it can reveal whether the system is running
vulnerable software. Most network services can be configured to
limit what information is displayed.
<br /><br />
Many organizations implement security policies that require a
system banner provide notice of the system's ownership, provide
warning to unauthorized users, and remind authorized users of their
consent to monitoring.</description>
<Value id="login_banner_text" type="string"
operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>login banner verbiage</title>
<description>Enter an appropriate login banner for your
organization</description>
<value selector="any_text">.+</value>
</Value>


<Group id="system_login_banner">
<title>Modify the System Login Banner</title>
<description>The contents of the file <tt>/etc/issue</tt> are
displayed on the screen just above the login prompt for users
logging directly into a terminal. Remote login programs such as
SSH or FTP can be configured to display <tt>/etc/issue</tt> as well.
Instructions for configuring each server daemon to show this file
can be found in the relevant sections of Chapter 3.
<br /><br />
By default, the system will display the version of the OS,
the kernel version, and the host name.
<br /><br />
Edit <tt>/etc/issue</tt>. Replace the default text with a message
compliant with the local site policy or a legal
disclaimer.</description>
<Rule id="set_system_login_banner">
<title>Modify the System Login Banner</title>
<description>The system login banner text should be:
<sub idref="login_banner_text" /></description>
<ident cce="4060-0" />
<oval id="banner_etc_issue" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6, AC-8" />
</Rule>
</Group>


<Group id="gui_login_banner">
<title>Implement a GUI Warning Banner</title>
<description>In the default graphical environment, users logging
directly into the system are greeted with a login screen provided
by the GNOME display manager. The warning banner should be
displayed in this graphical environment for these users.
<br /><br />
Run the following command to set a warning banner:
<br />
<pre>
sudo -u gdm gconftool-2 \
     --type bool \
     --set /apps/gdm/simple-greeter/banner_message_enable true
sudo -u gdm gconftool-2 \
     --type string \
     --set /apps/gdm/simple-greeter/banner_message_text \
     "Insert the text of your warning banner here"

</pre>
When entering a warning banner that spans several lines, remember
to begin and end the string with <tt>"</tt>. These two commands write
to the file <tt>/var/lib/gdm/.gconf/apps/gdm/simple-greeter/%gconf.xml</tt>,
and create the necessary parent directories. Once created,
this file can be edited directly if necessary.
</description>
<Rule id="set_gui_login_banner">
<title>Implement a GUI Warning Banner</title>
<description>The direct Gnome login warning banner text should be
set appropriately</description>
<ident cce="4188-9" />
<oval id="banner_gui_gdm" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6, AC-8" />
</Rule>
</Group>

<Group id="user_list">
<title>Disable the User List</title>
<description>In the default graphical environment, users logging
directly into the system are greeted with a login screen that displays
all known users. This functionality should be disabled.
<br /><br />
Run the following command to disable the user list:
<br />
<pre>
sudo -u gdm gconftool-2 \
     --type bool \
     --set /apps/gdm/simple-greeter/disable_user_list true

</pre>
Leaving the user list enabled is a security risk since it allows anyone
with physical access to the system to quickly enumerate known user accounts
without logging in.
</description>
<Rule id="disable_user_list">
<title>Disable the User List</title>
<description>GDM's list of previously logged in users should not be displayed.</description>
</Rule>
</Group>

</Group>

