<Group id="accounts-banners">
<title>Warning Banners for System Accesses</title>
<description>Each system should expose as little information about
itself as possible.
<br />
<br />System banners, which are typically displayed just before a
login prompt, give out information about the service or the host's
operating system. This might include the distribution name and the
system kernel version, and the particular version of a network
service. This information can assist intruders in gaining access to
the system as it can reveal whether the system is running
vulnerable software. Most network services can be configured to
limit what information is displayed.
<br />
<br />Many organizations implement security policies that require a
system banner provide notice of the system's ownership, provide
warning to unauthorized users, and remind authorized users of their
consent to monitoring.</description>
<Value id="var-2.3.7" type="string"
operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>login banner verbiage</title>
<description>Enter an appropriate login banner for your
organization</description>
<value selector="any_text">.+</value>
</Value>


<Group id="system_login_banner">
<title>Modify the System Login Banner</title>
<description>The contents of the file /etc/issue are displayed on
the screen just above the login prompt for users logging directly
into a terminal. Remote login programs such as SSH or FTP can be
configured to display /etc/issue as well. Instructions for
configuring each server daemon to show this file can be found in
the relevant sections of Chapter 3.
<br />
<br />By default, the system will display the version of the OS,
the kernel version, and the host name.
<br />
<br />Edit /etc/issue. Replace the default text with a message
compliant with the local site policy or a legal
disclaimer.</description>
<Rule id="set_system_login_banner">
<title>Modify the System Login Banner</title>
<description>The system login banner text should be:
<sub idref="var-2.3.7" /></description>
<ident cce="4060-0" />
<oval id="20102" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6, AC-8" />
</Rule>
</Group>


<Group id="gui_login_banner">
<title>Implement a GUI Warning Banner</title>
<description>In the default graphical environment, users logging
directly into the system are greeted with a login screen provided
by the GNOME display manager. The warning banner should be
displayed in this graphical environment for these users.
<br />
<br />The files for the default RHEL theme can be found in
/usr/share/gdm/themes/RHEL. Add the following sample block of XML
to /usr/share/gdm/themes/RHEL/RHEL.xml after the first two "pixmap"
entries:
<br />
<pre>
 &lt;item type="rect"&gt; &lt;pos anchor="n" x="50%" y="10"
width="box" weight="box"/&gt; &lt;box&gt; &lt;item type="label"&gt; &lt;normal
font="Sans 14" color="#ffffff"/&gt; &lt;text&gt;
Insert the text of your warning banner here.&lt;/text&gt; &lt;/item&gt;
&lt;/box&gt; &lt;/item&gt;
</pre>
<br />The full syntax that GDM theme files expect is documented
elsewhere, but the above XML will create a text box centered at the
top of the screen. The font, text color, and exact positioning can
all be easily modified by editing the appropriate values. The
latest current GDM theme manual can be found at
http://www.gnome.org/
projects/gdm/docs/thememanual.html.</description>

<Rule id="set_gui_login_banner">
<title>Implement a GUI Warning Banner</title>
<description>The direct gnome login warning banner text should be
set appropriately</description>
<ident cce="4188-9" />
<oval id="20103" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6, AC-8" />
</Rule>
</Group>

</Group>

