<Group id="accounts-banners">
<title>Warning Banners for System Accesses</title>
<description>Each system should expose as little information about
itself as possible.
<br /><br />
System banners, which are typically displayed just before a
login prompt, give out information about the service or the host's
operating system. This might include the distribution name and the
system kernel version, and the particular version of a network
service. This information can assist intruders in gaining access to
the system as it can reveal whether the system is running
vulnerable software. Most network services can be configured to
limit what information is displayed.
<br /><br />
Many organizations implement security policies that require a
system banner provide notice of the system's ownership, provide
warning to unauthorized users, and remind authorized users of their
consent to monitoring.</description>

<Value id="login_banner_text" type="string" operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>Login Banner Verbiage</title>
<description>Enter an appropriate login banner for your organization. Please note that new lines must
be expressed by the '\n' character.</description>
<value selector="any_text">.+</value>
<value selector="usgcb_default">
-- WARNING --\nThis system is for the use of authorized users only. Individuals\nusing this computer system without authority or in excess of their\nauthority are subject to having all their activities on this system\nmonitored and recorded by system personnel. Anyone using this\nsystem expressly consents to such monitoring and is advised that\nif such monitoring reveals possible evidence of criminal activity\nsystem personal may provide the evidence of such monitoring to law\nenforcement officials.
</value>
</Value>

<Rule id="set_system_login_banner">
<title>Modify the System Login Banner</title>
<description>
The contents of the file <tt>/etc/issue</tt> are
displayed on the screen just above the login prompt for users
logging directly into a terminal. Remote login programs such as
SSH or FTP can be configured to display <tt>/etc/issue</tt> as well.
Instructions for configuring these daemons are available later.
<br /><br />
By default, the system will display the version of the OS,
the kernel version, and the host name.
<br /><br />
Edit <tt>/etc/issue</tt>. Replace the default text with a message
compliant with the local site policy or a legal disclaimer.
<!--<sub idref="login_banner_text" />-->
</description>
<rationale>
Although unlikely to dissuade a serious attacker, the warning message
reinforces policy awareness during the logon process.
</rationale>
<ident cce="4060-0" />
<oval id="banner_etc_issue" value="login_banner_text"/>
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6, AC-8" />
</Rule>

<Group id="gui_login_banner">
<title>Implement a GUI Warning Banner</title>
<description>In the default graphical environment, users logging
directly into the system are greeted with a login screen provided
by the GNOME Display Manager (GDM). The warning banner should be
displayed in this graphical environment for these users.
The following sections describe how to configure the GDM login
banner.
</description>

<Rule id="enable_gdm_login_banner">
<title>Enable GUI Warning Banner</title>
<description>
To enable displaying a login warning banner in the GNOME
Display Manager's login screen, run the following command:
<pre>sudo -u gdm gconftool-2 \
  --type bool \
  --set /apps/gdm/simple-greeter/banner_message_enable true</pre>
To display a banner, this setting must be enabled and then
banner text must also be set.
</description>
<rationale>
Although unlikely to dissuade a serious attacker, the warning message
reinforces policy awareness during the logon process.
</rationale>
<ident cce="4188-9" />
<oval id="banner_gui_enabled" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6, AC-8" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="set_gdm_login_banner_text">
<title>Set GUI Warning Banner Text</title>
<description>
To set the text shown by the GNOME Display Manager
in the login screen, run the following command:
<pre>sudo -u gdm gconftool-2 \
  --type string \
  --set /apps/gdm/simple-greeter/banner_message_text \
  "Text of the warning banner here"</pre>
When entering a warning banner that spans several lines, remember
to begin and end the string with <tt>"</tt>. This command writes
directly to the file <tt>/var/lib/gdm/.gconf/apps/gdm/simple-greeter/%gconf.xml</tt>,
and this file can later be edited directly if necessary.
</description>
<rationale>
Although unlikely to dissuade a serious attacker, the warning message
reinforces policy awareness during the logon process.
</rationale>
<ident cce="4188-9" />
<oval id="banner_gui_text_set" value="login_banner_text" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6, AC-8" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="user_list">
<title>Disable the User List</title>
<description>In the default graphical environment, users logging
directly into the system are greeted with a login screen that displays
all known users. This functionality should be disabled.
<br /><br />
Run the following command to disable the user list:
<pre>sudo -u gdm gconftool-2 \
  --type bool \
  --set /apps/gdm/simple-greeter/disable_user_list true</pre>
Leaving the user list enabled is a security risk since it allows anyone
with physical access to the system to quickly enumerate known user accounts
without logging in.
</description>
<Rule id="disable_user_list">
<title>Disable the User List</title>
<description>GDM's list of previously logged in users should not be displayed.</description>
</Rule>
</Group>

</Group>

