<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Benchmark xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" id="product-name" xsi:schemaLocation="http://checklists.nist.gov/xccdf/1.1 xccdf-1.1.4.xsd" style="SCAP_1.1" resolved="false" xml:lang="en-US" >

<status date="2011-12-20">draft</status>
<title>Guide to the Secure Configuration of <product-name-macro/></title>
<description>This guide presents a catalog of security-relevant
configuration settings for <product-name-macro/>. It is a rendering of
content structured in the eXtensible Configuration Checklist Description Format (XCCDF)
in order to support security automation.  The SCAP content is
is available in the <tt>scap-security-guide</tt> package which is developed at
<weblink-macro link="https://www.open-scap.org/security-policies/scap-security-guide" />.
<br/>
<br/>
Providing system administrators with such guidance informs them how to securely
configure systems under their control in a variety of network roles. Policy
makers and baseline creators can use this catalog of settings, with its
associated references to higher-level security control catalogs, in order to
assist them in security baseline creation. This guide is a <i>catalog, not a
checklist,</i> and satisfaction of every item is not likely to be possible or
sensible in many operational scenarios. However, the XCCDF format enables
granular selection and adjustment of settings, and their association with OVAL
and OCIL content provides an automated checking capability. Transformations of
this document, and its associated automated checking content, are capable of
providing baselines that meet a diverse set of policy objectives. Some example
XCCDF <i>Profiles</i>, which are selections of items that form checklists and
can be used as baselines, are available with this guide. They can be
processed, in an automated fashion, with tools that support the Security
Content Automation Protocol (SCAP). The DISA STIG for <product-name-macro/>,
which provides required settings for US Department of Defense systems, is
one example of a baseline created from this guidance.
</description>
<notice id="terms_of_use">Do not attempt to implement any of the settings in
this guide without first testing them in a non-operational environment. The
creators of this guidance assume no responsibility whatsoever for its use by
other parties, and makes no guarantees, expressed or implied, about its
quality, reliability, or any other characteristic.</notice>

<front-matter>The SCAP Security Guide Project<br/>
<weblink-macro link="https://www.open-scap.org/security-policies/scap-security-guide" /></front-matter>
<rear-matter>Red Hat and Red Hat Enterprise Linux are either registered
trademarks or trademarks of Red Hat, Inc. in the United States and other
countries. All other names are registered trademarks or trademarks of their
respective companies.</rear-matter>
<platform-cpes-macro/>
<version>0.9</version>
<metadata/>
</Benchmark>
