<Group id="logging">
<title>Configure Syslog</title>
<description>The syslog service has been the default Unix logging mechanism for
many years. It has a number of downsides, including inconsistent log format,
lack of authentication for received messages, and lack of authentication,
encryption, or reliable transport for messages sent over a network. However,
due to its long history, syslog is an accepted standard which is supported by
almost all Unix applications. In RHEL 6, rsyslog has replaced syslog as the
syslog daemon of choice. This section discusses how to configure rsyslog for
best effect, and how to use tools provided with the system to maintain and
monitor your logs.</description>

<Rule id="package_rsyslog_installed">
<title>Install rsyslog</title>
<description>This check queries the local RPM database to
make sure that the rsyslog RPM is installed.</description>
<ident cce="17742-8" />
<oval id="package_rsyslog_installed" />
<ref nist="AU-2, AU-9, CM-6" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="enable_rsyslog">
<title>Configure Rsyslog</title>
<description>The <tt>rsyslog</tt> service should be enabled or disabled
as appropriate.</description>
<ident cce="17698-2" />
<oval id="service_rsyslog_enabled" />
<ref nist="AU-2" />
</Rule>

<Group id="log_file_permissions">
<title>Confirm Existence and Permissions of System Log Files</title>
<description>For each log file LOGFILE referenced in
<tt>/etc/rsyslog.conf</tt>, run the commands:
<br />
<pre>
# touch LOGFILE
# chown root:root LOGFILE
# chmod 0600 LOGFILE

</pre>
Rsyslog will refuse to log to a file which does not exist.
All messages intended for that file will be silently discarded, so
it is important to verify that all log files exist. Some logs may
contain sensitive information, so it is better to restrict
permissions so that only administrative users can read or write
logfiles.</description>

<Value id="file_owner_logfiles_value" type="string"
operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>User who owns log files</title>
<description>Specify user owner of all logfiles specified in
<tt>/etc/rsyslog.conf</tt>.</description>
<value selector="root">root</value>
</Value>

<Value id="file_groupowner_logfiles_value" type="string"
operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>group who owns log files</title>
<description>Specify group owner of all logfiles specified in
<tt>/etc/rsyslog.conf.</tt></description>
<value selector="root">root</value>
</Value>

<Rule id="userowner_rsyslog_files">
<title>RSyslog Log Files Owned By Appropriate User</title>
<description>All <tt>rsyslog</tt> log files should be owned by the
appropriate user.</description>
<ident cce="17857-4" />
<oval id="rsyslog_files_ownership" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="groupowner_rsyslog_files">
<title>RSyslog Log Files Owned By Appropriate Group</title>
<description>All <tt>rsyslog</tt> log files should be owned by the
appropriate group.</description>
<ident cce="18240-2" />
<oval id="rsyslog_files_groupownership" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6" />
</Rule>


<Rule id="rsyslog_file_permissions">
<title>RSyslog Log Files Have Correct Permissions</title>
<description>File permissions for all <tt>rsyslog</tt> log files should be
set correctly.</description>
<ident cce="18095-0" />
<oval id="rsyslog_files_permissions" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6" />
</Rule>
</Group>

<Group id="rsyslog_sending_messages">
<title>Rsyslog Logs Sent To Remote Host</title>
<description>Edit <tt>/etc/rsyslog.conf</tt>. Add or correct the line:
<br />
<pre>
*.* @loghost.example.com

</pre>
where <tt>loghost.example.com</tt> is the name of your central log server.
<br /><br />
If system logs are to be useful in detecting malicious
activities, it is necessary to send logs to a remote server. An
intruder who has compromised the root account on a machine may
delete the log entries which indicate that the system was attacked
before they are seen by an administrator.
<br /><br />
However, it is recommended that logs be stored on the local
host in addition to being sent to the loghost, especially if
<tt>rsyslog</tt> has been configured to use the UDP protocol to send
messages over a network. UDP does not guarantee reliable delivery,
and moderately busy sites will lose log messages occasionally,
especially in periods of high traffic which may be the result of an
attack. In addition, remote <tt>rsyslog</tt> messages are not
authenticated in any way by default, so it is easy for an attacker to
introduce spurious messages to the central log server. Also, some
problems cause loss of network connectivity, which will prevent the
sending of messages to the central server. For all of these reasons, it is
better to store log messages both centrally and on each host, so
that they can be correlated if necessary.</description>

<Rule id="rsyslog_send_messages_to_logserver">
<title>Rsyslog Logs Sent To Remote Host</title>
<description>Rsyslog logs should be sent to a remote loghost or not
as appropriate</description>
<ident cce="17248-6" />
<oval id="rsyslog_remote_loghost" />
<ref nist="AU-2, AU-9" />
</Rule>
</Group>

<Group id="rsyslog_accepting_remote_messages">
<title>Enable <tt>rsyslogd</tt> to Accept Remote Messages on Loghosts
Only</title>
<description>Is this machine the central log server for your
organization? If so, edit the file <tt>/etc/rsyslog.conf</tt>. Add or
correct the following lines:
<br />
<pre>
$ModLoad imtcp.so
$InputTCPServerRun 514

</pre>
If the machine is not a log server, ensure that those two lines are
commented out.
<br /><br />
By default, RHEL6's <tt>rsyslog</tt> does not listen over the network
for log messages. The options <tt>$ModLoad imtcp.so</tt> and
<tt>$InputTCPServerRun 514</tt> enable <tt>rsyslogd</tt> to listen over
TCP port 514, and should be used only if necessary.
</description>
<!--<description>Is this machine the central log server for your
organization? If so, edit the file <tt>/etc/sysconfig/rsyslog</tt>. Add
or correct the following line:
<br />
<pre>
SYSLOGD_OPTIONS="-m 0 -r -s example.com "

</pre>
where <tt>example.com</tt> is the name of your domain.
<br /><br />
If the machine is not a log server, edit <tt>/etc/sysconfig/syslog</tt>,
and instead add or correct the line:
<br />
<pre>
SYSLOGD_OPTIONS="-m 0"

</pre>
By default, RHEL6's <tt>rsyslog</tt> does not listen over the network
for log messages. The <tt>-r</tt> flag enables <tt>rsyslogd</tt> to listen over a
network, and should be used only if necessary. The <tt>-s example.com</tt>
flag strips the domain name <tt>example.com</tt> from each sending machine's
hostname before logging messages from that host, to reduce the
amount of redundant information placed in log files. See the
<tt>rsyslogd(8)</tt> man page for further information.</description>
-->

<Rule id="rsyslog_accept_remote_messages">
<title>RSyslog Should Accept Remote Messages As Appropriate</title>
<description><tt>rsyslog</tt> should accept remote messages or not as
appropriate</description>
<ident cce="17639-6" />
<oval id="rsyslog_nolisten" />
<ref nist="AU-2, AU-9" />
</Rule>
</Group>

<Group id="log_rotation">
<title>Ensure All Logs are Rotated by <tt>logrotate</tt></title>
<description>Edit the file <tt>/etc/logrotate.d/syslog</tt>. Find the first
line, which should look like this (wrapped for clarity):
<br />
<pre>
/var/log/messages /var/log/secure /var/log/maillog /var/log/spooler \
  /var/log/boot.log /var/log/cron {

</pre>
Edit this line so that it contains a one-space-separated
listing of each log file referenced in <tt>/etc/rsyslog.conf</tt>.
<br /><br />
All logs in use on a system must be rotated regularly, or the
log files will consume disk space over time, eventually interfering
with system operation. The file <tt>/etc/logrotate.d/syslog</tt> is the
configuration file used by the <tt>logrotate</tt> program to maintain all
log files written by <tt>syslog</tt>. By default, it rotates logs weekly and
stores four archival copies of each log. These settings can be
modified by editing <tt>/etc/logrotate.conf</tt>, but the defaults are
sufficient for purposes of this guide.
<br /><br />
Note that <tt>logrotate</tt> is run nightly by the cron job
<tt>/etc/cron.daily/logrotate</tt>. If particularly active logs need to be
rotated more often than once a day, some other mechanism must be
used.</description>

<Rule id="ensure_logrotate_activated">
<title>Ensure Logs Are Rotated</title>
<description>The <tt>logrotate</tt> (<tt>rsyslog</tt> rotater) service should be
enabled.</description>
<ident cce="4182-2" />
<oval id="logrotate_rotate_all_files" />
<ref nist="AU-2, AU-9, CM-6" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>
