<Group id="selinux">
<title>SELinux</title>
<description>SELinux is a feature of the Linux kernel which can be
used to guard against misconfigured or compromised programs.
SELinux enforces the idea that programs should be limited in what
files they can access and what actions they can take.
<br /><br />
The default SELinux policy, as configured on RHEL6, has been
sufficiently developed and debugged that it should be usable on
almost any Red Hat machine with minimal configuration and a small
amount of system administrator training. This policy prevents
system services — including most of the common network-visible
services such as mail servers, ftp servers, and DNS servers — from
accessing files which those services have no valid reason to
access. This action alone prevents a huge amount of possible damage
from network attacks against services, from trojaned software, and
so forth.
<br /><br />
This guide recommends that SELinux be enabled using the
default (targeted) policy on every Red Hat system, unless that
system has requirements which make a stronger policy
appropriate.
</description>

<Group id="enabling_selinux">
<title>Enable SELinux</title>
<description>Edit the file <tt>/etc/selinux/config</tt>. Add or correct the
following lines:
<br />
<pre>
SELINUX=enforcing
SELINUXTYPE=targeted

</pre>
Edit the file <tt>/etc/grub.conf</tt>. Ensure that the following
arguments DO NOT appear on any kernel command line in the file:
<br />
<pre>
selinux=0
enforcing=0

</pre>
The directive <tt>SELINUX=enforcing</tt> enables SELinux at boot time.
If SELinux is causing a lot of problems or preventing the system
from booting, it is possible to boot into the warning-only mode
<tt>SELINUX=permissive</tt> for debugging purposes. Make certain to change
the mode back to enforcing after debugging, set the filesystems to
be relabelled for consistency using the command <tt>touch
/.autorelabel</tt>, and reboot.
<br /><br />
However, the RHEL6 default SELinux configuration should be
sufficiently reasonable that most systems will boot without serious
problems. Some applications that require deep or unusual system
privileges, such as virtual machine software, may not be compatible
with SELinux in its default configuration. However, this should be
uncommon, and SELinux's application support continues to improve.
In other cases, SELinux may reveal unusual or insecure program
behavior by design.
<br /><br />
The directive <tt>SELINUXTYPE=targeted</tt> configures SELinux to use
the default targeted policy. 
<br /><br />
The SELinux boot mode specified in <tt>/etc/selinux/config</tt> can be
overridden by command-line arguments passed to the kernel. It is
necessary to check <tt>grub.conf</tt> to ensure that this has not been done
and to protect the boot process.
</description>

<Value id="var-2.4.2.c" type="string"
operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>SELinux state</title>
<description>enforcing - SELinux security policy is enforced.
<br />permissive - SELinux prints warnings instead of enforcing.
<br />disabled - SELinux is fully disabled.</description>
<value selector="">enforcing</value>
<value selector="enforcing">enforcing</value>
<value selector="permissive">permissive</value>
<value selector="disabled">disabled</value>
</Value>
<Value id="var-2.4.2.d" type="string"
operator="equals" interactive="0">
<title>SELinux policy</title>
<description>Type of policy in use. Possible values are:
<br />targeted - Only targeted network daemons are protected.
<br />strict - Full SELinux protection.
<br />mls - Multiple levels of security</description>
<value selector="">targeted</value>
<value selector="targeted">targeted</value>
<value selector="strict">strict</value>
<value selector="mls">mls</value>
</Value>

<Rule id="enable_selinux_bootloader">
<title>Ensure SELinux Not Disabled in <tt>/etc/grub.conf</tt></title>
<description>SELinux should NOT be disabled in <tt>/etc/grub.conf</tt>.
Check that <tt>selinux=0</tt> is not found</description>
<ident cce="3977-6" />
<oval id="20104" />
<ref nist="AC-3, CM-6" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="set_selinux_state">
<title>Set the SELinux state</title>
<description>The SELinux state should be set
appropriately</description>
<ident cce="3999-0" />
<oval id="20106" />
<ref nist="CM-6, CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="set_selinux_policy">
<title>Set the SELinux policy</title>
<description>The SELinux policy should be set
appropriately.</description>
<ident cce="3624-4" />
<oval id="20107" />
<ref nist="CM-6, CM-7" />
</Rule>
</Group>

<Group id="selinux_daemons">
<title>Disable Unnecessary SELinux Daemons</title>
<description>Several daemons are installed by default as part of
the RHEL6 SELinux support mechanism. These daemons may improve the
system's ability to enforce SELinux policy in a useful fashion, but
may also represent unnecessary code running on the machine,
increasing system risk. If these daemons are not needed on your
system, they should be disabled.</description>
<Group id="group-2.4.3.2">
<title>Disable MCS Translation Service (mcstrans) if
Possible</title>
<description>Unless there is some overriding need for the
convenience of category label translation, disable the MCS
translation service:
<br />
<pre>
# chkconfig mcstrans off

</pre>
The mcstransd daemon provides the category label translation
information defined in <tt>/etc/selinux/targeted/setrans.conf</tt> to
client processes which request this information.
<br /><br />
Category labelling is unlikely to be used except in sites
with special requirements. Therefore, it should be disabled in
order to reduce the amount of potentially vulnerable code running
on the system. See Section 2.4.6 for more information about systems
which use category labelling.</description>
<Rule id="disable_mcstransd">
<title>Disable MCS Translation Service (mcstrans) if
Possible</title>
<description>The mcstrans service should be disabled.</description>
<ident cce="3668-1" />
<oval id="20110" />
<ref nist="CM-6, CM-7" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>


<Group id="selinux_confinement_of_daemons">
<title>Check for Unconfined Daemons</title>
<description>Device files are used for communication with important
system resources. SELinux contexts should exist for these. If a
device file is not labeled, then misconfiguration is likely.
<br /><br />
To check for unlabeled device files, run the following command:
<br />
<pre>
# ls -Z | grep unlabeled_t

</pre>
It should produce no output in a well-configured system.</description>
<Rule id="selinux_unlabeled_device_files">
<title>Check for Unlabeled Device Files</title>
<description>Check for device file that is not labeled.</description>
<ident cce="14991-4" />
<oval id="201115" />
<ref nist="CM-6, CM-7" />
</Rule>
</Group>
</Group>

