<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<section id="sect_RedHat-Getting_Help_and_Giving_Feedback">
	<title>Getting Help and Giving Feedback</title>
	 <section id="sect_RedHat-Do_You_Need_Help">
		<title>Do You Need Help?</title>
		 <indexterm>
			<primary>help</primary>
			 <secondary>getting help</secondary>

		</indexterm>
		 <para>
			If you experience difficulty with a procedure described in this documentation, you can find help in the following ways:
		</para>
		 <variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Red Hat Knowledgebase</term>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						Visit the Red Hat Knowledgebase at <ulink url="http://kbase.redhat.com" /> to search or browse through technical support articles about Red Hat products.
					</para>

				</listitem>

			</varlistentry>
			 <varlistentry>
				<term>Red Hat Global Support Services</term>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						Your Red Hat subscription entitles you to support from Red Hat Global Support Services (GSS). Visit <ulink url="http://support.redhat.com" /> for more information about obtaining help from GSS.
					</para>

				</listitem>

			</varlistentry>
			 <varlistentry>
				<term>Other Red Hat documentation</term>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						Access other Red Hat documentation at <ulink url="http://www.redhat.com/docs" />
					</para>

				</listitem>

			</varlistentry>
			 <varlistentry>
				<term>Red Hat electronic mailing lists</term>
				 <listitem>
					<para>
						Red Hat hosts a large number of electronic mailing lists for discussion of Red Hat software and technology. You can find a list of publicly available lists at <ulink url="https://www.redhat.com/mailman/listinfo" />. Click on the name of any list to subscribe to that list or to access the list archives.
					</para>

				</listitem>

			</varlistentry>

		</variablelist>

	</section>
	
	 <section id="sect-RedHat-We_Need_Feedback">
		<title>We Need Feedback!</title>
		 <indexterm>
			<primary>feedback</primary>
			 <secondary>contact information for this manual</secondary>

		</indexterm>
		 <para>
			If you find a typographical error in this manual, or if you have thought of a way to make this manual better, we would love to hear from you! Please submit a report in Bugzilla: <ulink url="http://bugzilla.redhat.com/">http://bugzilla.redhat.com/</ulink> against the product <application>&PRODUCT;.</application>
		</para>
		 <para>
			When submitting a bug report, be sure to mention the manual&#39;s identifier: <citetitle>&BOOKID;</citetitle>
		</para>
		 <para>
			If you have a suggestion for improving the documentation, try to be as specific as possible when describing it. If you have found an error, please include the section number and some of the surrounding text so we can find it easily.
		</para>

	</section>
	

</section>


