<Group id="auditing">
	<title>Auditing</title>
	<description>Auditing rules</description>


	<Rule id="jboss_roll_over_transfer_logs" severity="medium">
		<title>JBoss servers must be configured to roll over and transfer logs on a minimum weekly basis.</title>
		<description>Information stored in one location is vulnerable to accidental or incidental deletion or
			alteration. Protecting log data is important during a forensic investigation to ensure 
			investigators can track and understand what may have occurred. Off-loading should be set up 
			as a scheduled task but can be configured to be run manually, if other processes during 
			the off-loading are manual. Off-loading is a common process in information systems with 
			limited log storage capacity.</description>
		<rationale>Logs preservation and size limits can be implicitly incurred via periodic log rolling</rationale>
		<ident cce=""/>
		<ref ossrg="SRG-APP-000515-AS-000203" stigid="000735" />
	</Rule>

	<Rule id="jboss_http_mgmt_session_encryption" severity="medium">
		<title>HTTP management session traffic must be encrypted</title>
		<description>Types of management interfaces utilized by the JBoss EAP 
			application server include web-based HTTP interfaces as well as 
			command line-based management interfaces. In the event remote HTTP 
			management is required, the access must be via HTTPS. This 
			requirement is in conjunction with the requirement to isolate all 
			management access to a restricted network.</description>
		<rationale>Administrative activity should be secured and is not so by default</rationale>
		<ident cce=""/>
		<ref ossrg="SRG-APP-000014-AS-000009" stigid="000010" />
	</Rule>

	<Rule id="jboss_web_interface_https_enabled" severity="medium">
		<title>HTTPS must be enabled for JBoss web interfaces</title>
		<descritpion>Encryption is critical for protection of remote access 
			sessions. If encryption is not being used for integrity, malicious 
			users may gain the ability to modify the application server 
			configuration. The use of cryptography for ensuring integrity of 
			remote access sessions mitigates that risk. Application servers 
			utilize a web management interface and scripted commands when 
			allowing remote access. Web access requires the use of TLS, and 
			scripted access requires using ssh or some other form of approved 
			cryptography. Application servers must have a capability to enable a 
			secure remote admin capability. FIPS 140-2 approved TLS versions 
			include TLS V1.0 or greater. FIPS 140-2 approved TLS versions must 
			be enabled, and non-FIPS-approved SSL versions must be disabled. 
			NIST SP 800-52 specifies the preferred configurations for government 
			systems</description>
		<rationale>Remote web activity should be secured</rationale>
		<ident cce=""/>
		<ref ossrg="SRG-APP-000015-AS-000010" stigid="000015" />
	</Rule>

	<Rule id="jboss_java_applications_permissions" severity="high"/>
		<title>Java permissions must be set for hosted applications</title>
		<description>The Java Security Manager is a java class that manages the 
			external boundary of the Java Virtual Machine (JVM) sandbox, 
			controlling how code executing within the JVM can interact with 
			resources outside the JVM. The JVM requires a security policy in 
			order to restrict application access. A properly configured security 
			policy will define what rights the application has to the underlying 
			system. For example, rights to make changes to files on the host 
			system or to initiate network sockets in order to connect to another 
			system</description>
		<rationale>Restricting application access will prevent unauthorized use of JVM</rationale>
		<ident cce=""/>
		<ref ossrg="SRG-APP-000033-AS-000024" stigid="000025" />
	</Rule>

	<Rule id="jboss_mgmt_realm_user_roles" severity="medium">
		<title>Users in JBoss Management Security Realms must be in the appropriate role</title>
		<description>Security realms are a series of mappings between users and 
			passwords and users and roles. There are 2 JBoss security realms 
			provided by default; they are "management realm" and "application 
			realm". Management realm stores authentication information for the 
			management API, which provides functionality for the web-based 
			management console and the management command line interface (CLI). 
			mgmt-groups.properties stores user to group mapping for the 
			ManagementRealm but only when role-based access controls (RBAC) is 
			enabled. If management users are not in the appropriate role, 
			unauthorized access to JBoss resources can occur</description>
		<rationale>Appropriate assignment of roles allows users to be authorized for more finely differenced actions</rationale>
		<ident cce=""/>
		<ref ossrg="SRG-APP-000033-AS-000024" stigid="000040" />
	</Rule>

	<Rule id="jboss_default_app_realm_silent_authentication" severity="high">
		<title>Silent Authentication must be removed from the Default Application Security Realm</title>
		<description>Silent Authentication is a configuration setting that allows 
			local OS users access to the JBoss server and a wide range of 
			operations without specifically authenticating on an individual user 
			basis. By default $localuser is a Superuser. This introduces an 
			integrity and availability vulnerability and violates best practice 
			requirements regarding accountability</description>
		<rationale>Allowing silent authentication creates a relaxed means of accessing the system</rationale>
		<ident cce=""/>
		<ref ossrg="SRG-APP-000033-AS-000024" stigid="000045" />
	</Rule>

	<Rule id="jboss_default_mgmt_realm_silent_authentication" severity="high">
		<title>Silent Authentication must be removed from the Default Management Security Realm</title>
		<description>Silent Authentication is a configuration setting that allows 
			local OS users access to the JBoss server and a wide range of 
			operations without specifically authenticating on an individual user 
			basis. By default $localuser is a Superuser. This introduces an 
			integrity and availability vulnerability and violates best practice 
			requirements regarding accountability</description>
		<rationale>Allowing silent authentication creates a relaxed means of accessing the system</rationale>
		<ident cce=""/>
		<ref ossrg="SRG-APP-000033-AS-000024" stigid="000050" />
	</Rule>



</Group>


