<Group id="integrity">
<title>System and Software Integrity</title>
<description>
System and software integrity can be gained by installing antivirus, increasing
system encryption strength with FIPS, verifying installed software, enabling SELinux,
installing an Intrusion Prevention System, etc. However, installing or enabling integrity
checking tools cannot <i>prevent</i> intrusions, but they can detect that an intrusion
may have occurred. Requirements for integrity checking may be highly dependent on
the environment in which the system will be used. Snapshot-based approaches such
as AIDE may induce considerable overhead in the presence of frequent software updates.
</description>

<Rule id="disable_prelink" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Disable Prelinking</title>
<description>
The prelinking feature changes binaries in an attempt to decrease their startup
time. In order to disable it, change or add the following line inside the file
<tt>/etc/sysconfig/prelink</tt>:
<pre>PRELINKING=no</pre>
Next, run the following command to return binaries to a normal, non-prelinked state:
<pre>$ sudo /usr/sbin/prelink -ua</pre>
</description>
<rationale>
Because the prelinking feature changes binaries, it can interfere with the
operation of certain software and/or modes such as AIDE, FIPS, etc.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27078-5" />
<oval id="disable_prelink" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-6(d),CM-6(3),SC-28, SI-7" pcidss="Req-11.5" cjis="5.10.1.3" cui="3.13.11"/>
</Rule>

<Group id="software-integrity">
<title>Software Integrity Checking</title>
<description>
Both the AIDE (Advanced Intrusion Detection Environment)
software and the RPM package management system provide
mechanisms for verifying the integrity of installed software.
AIDE uses snapshots of file metadata (such as hashes) and compares these
to current system files in order to detect changes.
<br/><br/>
The RPM package management system can conduct integrity
checks by comparing information in its metadata database with
files installed on the system.
</description>

<Group id="aide">
<title>Verify Integrity with AIDE</title>
<description>AIDE conducts integrity checks by comparing information about
files with previously-gathered information. Ideally, the AIDE database is
created immediately after initial system configuration, and then again after any
software update.  AIDE is highly configurable, with further configuration
information located in <tt>/usr/share/doc/aide-<i>VERSION</i></tt>.
</description>

<Rule id="package_aide_installed" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Install AIDE</title>
<description>
Install the AIDE package with the command:
<pre>$ sudo yum install aide</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the package is not installed">
<package-check-macro package="aide"/>
</ocil>
<rationale>
The AIDE package must be installed if it is to be available for integrity checking.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27096-7" />
<oval id="package_aide_installed" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-3(d),CM-3(e),CM-6(d),CM-6(3),SC-28, SI-7" disa="" pcidss="Req-11.5" cis="1.3.1" cjis="5.10.1.3" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="aide_build_database" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Build and Test AIDE Database</title>
<description>Run the following command to generate a new database:
<pre>$ sudo /usr/sbin/aide --init</pre>
By default, the database will be written to the file <tt>/var/lib/aide/aide.db.new.gz</tt>.
Storing the database, the configuration file <tt>/etc/aide.conf</tt>, and the binary
<tt>/usr/sbin/aide</tt> (or hashes of these files), in a secure location (such as on read-only media) provides additional assurance about their integrity.
The newly-generated database can be installed as follows:
<pre>$ sudo cp /var/lib/aide/aide.db.new.gz /var/lib/aide/aide.db.gz</pre>
To initiate a manual check, run the following command:
<pre>$ sudo /usr/sbin/aide --check</pre>
If this check produces any unexpected output, investigate.
</description>
<ocil clause="there is no database file">
To find the location of the AIDE databse file, run the following command:
<pre>$ sudo ls -l <i>DBDIR</i>/<i>database_file_name</i></pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
For AIDE to be effective, an initial database of "known-good" information about files
must be captured and it should be able to be verified against the installed files.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27220-3" />
<oval id="aide_build_database" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-3(d),CM-3(e),CM-6(d),CM-6(3),SC-28,SI-7" pcidss="Req-11.5" cjis="5.10.1.3" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="aide_periodic_cron_checking" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Configure Periodic Execution of AIDE</title>
<description>
At a minimum, AIDE should be configured to run a weekly scan. At most, AIDE should be run daily.
To implement a daily execution of AIDE at 4:05am using cron, add the following line to <tt>/etc/crontab</tt>:
<pre>05 4 * * * root /usr/sbin/aide --check</pre>
To implement a weekly execution of AIDE at 4:05am using cron, add the following line to <tt>/etc/crontab</tt>:
<pre>05 4 * * 0 root /usr/sbin/aide --check</pre>
AIDE can be executed periodically through other means; this is merely one example.
</description>
<ocil clause="there is no output">
To determine that periodic AIDE execution has been scheduled, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep aide /etc/crontab</pre>
The output should return some similiar to the following:
<pre>05 4 * * * root /usr/sbin/aide --check</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
By default, AIDE does not install itself for periodic execution. Periodically
running AIDE is necessary to reveal unexpected changes in installed files.
<br/><br/>
Unauthorized changes to the baseline configuration could make the system vulnerable
to various attacks or allow unauthorized access to the operating system. Changes to
operating system configurations can have unintended side effects, some of which may
be relevant to security.
<br/><br/>
Detecting such changes and providing an automated response can help avoid unintended,
negative consequences that could ultimately affect the security state of the operating
system. The operating system's Information Management Officer (IMO)/Information System
Security Officer (ISSO) and System Administrators (SAs) must be notified via email and/or
monitoring system trap when there is an unauthorized modification of a configuration item.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="26952-2" />
<oval id="aide_periodic_cron_checking"/>
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-3(d),CM-3(e),CM-3(5),CM-6(d),CM-6(3),SC-28,SI-7" disa="1744" pcidss="Req-11.5" cis="1.3.1"
ossrg="SRG-OS-000363-GPOS-00150" stigid="020030" cjis="5.10.1.3" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="aide_scan_notification" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Configure Notification of Post-AIDE Scan Details</title>
<description>
AIDE should notify appropriate personnel of the details of a scan after the scan has been run.
If AIDE has already been configured for periodic execution in <tt>/etc/crontab</tt>, append the
following line to the existing AIDE line:
<pre> | /bin/mail -s "$(hostname) - AIDE Integrity Check" root@localhost</pre>
Otherwise, add the following line to <tt>/etc/crontab</tt>:
<pre>05 4 * * * root /usr/sbin/aide --check | /bin/mail -s "$(hostname) - AIDE Integrity Check" root@localhost</pre>
AIDE can be executed periodically through other means; this is merely one example.
</description>
<ocil clause="AIDE has not been configured or has not been configured to notify personnel of scan details">
To determine that periodic AIDE execution has been scheduled, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep aide /etc/crontab</pre>
The output should return something similar to the following:
<pre>05 4 * * * root /usr/sbin/aide --check | /bin/mail -s "$(hostname) - AIDE Integrity Check" root@localhost</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Unauthorized changes to the baseline configuration could make the system vulnerable
to various attacks or allow unauthorized access to the operating system. Changes to
operating system configurations can have unintended side effects, some of which may
be relevant to security.
<br/><br/>
Detecting such changes and providing an automated response can help avoid unintended,
negative consequences that could ultimately affect the security state of the operating
system. The operating system's Information Management Officer (IMO)/Information System
Security Officer (ISSO) and System Administrators (SAs) must be notified via email and/or
monitoring system trap when there is an unauthorized modification of a configuration item.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80374-2" />
<oval id="aide_scan_notification"/>
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-3(5)" disa="1744"
ossrg="SRG-OS-000363-GPOS-00150" stigid="020040" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="aide_verify_acls" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Configure AIDE to Verify Access Control Lists (ACLs)</title>
<description>
By default, the <tt>acl</tt> option is added to the <tt>FIPSR</tt> ruleset in AIDE.
If using a custom ruleset or the <tt>acl</tt> option is missing, add <tt>acl</tt>
to the appropriate ruleset.
For example, add <tt>acl</tt> to the following line in <tt>/etc/aide.conf</tt>:
<pre>FIPSR = p+i+n+u+g+s+m+c+acl+selinux+xattrs+sha256</pre>
AIDE rules can be configured in multiple ways; this is merely one example that is already
configured by default.
</description>
<ocil clause="the acl option is missing or not added to the correct ruleset">
To determine that AIDE is verifying ACLs, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep acl /etc/aide.conf</pre>
Verify that the <tt>acl</tt> option is added to the correct ruleset.
</ocil>
<rationale>
ACLs can provide permissions beyond those permitted through the file mode and must be
verified by the file integrity tools.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80375-9" />
<oval id="aide_verify_acls"/>
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SI-7.1" disa="366"
ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" stigid="021600" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="aide_verify_ext_attributes" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Configure AIDE to Verify Extended Attributes</title>
<description>
By default, the <tt>xattrs</tt> option is added to the <tt>FIPSR</tt> ruleset in AIDE.
If using a custom ruleset or the <tt>xattrs</tt> option is missing, add <tt>xattrs</tt>
to the appropriate ruleset.
For example, add <tt>xattrs</tt> to the following line in <tt>/etc/aide.conf</tt>:
<pre>FIPSR = p+i+n+u+g+s+m+c+acl+selinux+xattrs+sha256</pre>
AIDE rules can be configured in multiple ways; this is merely one example that is already
configured by default.
</description>
<ocil clause="the xattrs option is missing or not added to the correct ruleset">
To determine that AIDE is verifying extended file attributes, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep xattrs /etc/aide.conf</pre>
Verify that the <tt>xattrs</tt> option is added to the correct ruleset.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Extended attributes in file systems are used to contain arbitrary data and file metadata
with security implications.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80376-7" />
<oval id="aide_verify_ext_attributes"/>
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SI-7.1" disa="366"
ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" stigid="021610" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="aide_use_fips_hashes" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Configure AIDE to Use FIPS 140-2 for Validating Hashes</title>
<description>
By default, the <tt>sha512</tt> option is added to the <tt>NORMAL</tt> ruleset in AIDE.
If using a custom ruleset or the <tt>sha512</tt> option is missing, add <tt>sha512</tt>
to the appropriate ruleset.
For example, add <tt>sha512</tt> to the following line in <tt>/etc/aide.conf</tt>:
<pre>NORMAL = FIPSR+sha512</pre>
AIDE rules can be configured in multiple ways; this is merely one example that is already
configured by default.
</description>
<ocil clause="the sha512 option is missing or not added to the correct ruleset">
To determine that AIDE is configured for FIPS 140-2 file hashing, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep sha512 /etc/aide.conf</pre>
Verify that the <tt>sha512</tt> option is added to the correct ruleset.
</ocil>
<rationale>
File integrity tools use cryptographic hashes for verifying file contents and directories
have not been altered. These hashes must be FIPS 140-2 approved cryptographic hashes.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80377-5" />
<oval id="aide_use_fips_hashes"/>
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SI-7(1)" disa="366" ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227"
stigid="021620" cui="3.13.11" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="rpm_verification">
<title>Verify Integrity with RPM</title>
<description>The RPM package management system includes the ability
to verify the integrity of installed packages by comparing the
installed files with information about the files taken from the
package metadata stored in the RPM database. Although an attacker
could corrupt the RPM database (analogous to attacking the AIDE
database as described above), this check can still reveal
modification of important files. To list which files on the system differ from what is expected by the RPM database:
<pre>$ rpm -qVa</pre>
See the man page for <tt>rpm</tt> to see a complete explanation of each column.
</description>

<Rule id="rpm_verify_permissions" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Verify and Correct File Permissions with RPM</title>
<description>
Discretionary access control is weakened if a user or group has access
permissions to system files and directories greater than the default.

The RPM package management system can check file access permissions
of installed software packages, including many that are important
to system security.

Verify that the file permissions, ownership, and gruop membership of system files
and commands match vendor values. Check the file permissions, ownership, and group
membership with the following command:
<pre>$ sudo rpm -Va | grep '^.M'</pre>

Output indicates files that do not match vendor defaults. After locating a file with incorrect permissions, run the following command to determine which package owns it:
<pre>$ rpm -qf <i>FILENAME</i></pre>
<br />
Next, run the following command to reset its permissions to
the correct values:
<pre>$ sudo rpm --setperms <i>PACKAGENAME</i></pre>
<br />
</description>
<ocil clause="there is output">
The following command will list which files on the system have permissions different from what
is expected by the RPM database:
<pre>$ rpm -Va | grep '^.M'</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Permissions on system binaries and configuration files that are too generous
could allow an unauthorized user to gain privileges that they should not have.
The permissions set by the vendor should be maintained. Any deviations from
this baseline should be investigated.
</rationale>
<warning category="general">Note: Due to a bug in the <tt>gdm</tt> package, the
RPM verify command may continue to fail even after file permissions have been
correctly set on <tt>/var/log/gdm</tt>. This is being tracked in Red Hat
Bugzilla #1275532.
</warning>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27209-6" />
<oval id="rpm_verify_permissions" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="AC-6,AU-9(1),AU-9(3),CM-6(d),CM-6(3)" disa="1494,1496" pcidss="Req-11.5" cis="1.2.6,6.1.3,6.1.4,6.1.5,6.1.6,6.1.7,6.1.8,6.1.9,6.2.3" stigid="010010" ossrg="SRG-OS-000257-GPOS-00098,SRG-OS-000278-GPOS-00108" cjis="5.10.4.1" cui="3.3.8,3.4.1" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="rpm_verify_hashes" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Verify File Hashes with RPM</title>
<description>Without cryptographic integrity protections, system
executables and files can be altered by unauthorized users without
detection.

The RPM package management system can check the hashes of
installed software packages, including many that are important to system
security.

To verify that the cryptographic hash of system files and commands match vendor
values, run the following command to list which files on the system
have hashes that differ from what is expected by the RPM database:
<pre>$ rpm -Va | grep '^..5'</pre>

A "c" in the second column indicates that a file is a configuration file, which
may appropriately be expected to change.  If the file was not expected to
change, investigate the cause of the change using audit logs or other means.
The package can then be reinstalled to restore the file.

Run the following command to determine which package owns the file:
<pre>$ rpm -qf <i>FILENAME</i></pre>

The package can be reinstalled from a yum repository using the command:
<pre>$ sudo yum reinstall <i>PACKAGENAME</i></pre>

Alternatively, the package can be reinstalled from trusted media using the command:
<pre>$ sudo rpm -Uvh <i>PACKAGENAME</i></pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="there is output"> The following command will list which files on the system
have file hashes different from what is expected by the RPM database.
<pre>$ rpm -Va | awk '$1 ~ /..5/ &amp;&amp; $2 != "c"'</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
The hashes of important files like system executables should match the
information given by the RPM database. Executables with erroneous hashes could
be a sign of nefarious activity on the system.</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27157-7" />
<oval id="rpm_verify_hashes" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-6(d),CM-6(3),SI-7(1)" disa="663" pcidss="Req-11.5" 
cis="1.2.6" stigid="010020" ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" cjis="5.10.4.1" 
cui="3.3.8,3.4.1" />
</Rule>

</Group>

</Group>

<Group id="endpoint_security_software">
<title>Endpoint Protection Software</title>
<description>
Endpoint protection security software that is not provided or supported
by Red Hat can be installed to provide complementary or duplicative
security capabilities to those provided by the base platform.  Add-on
software may not be appropriate for some specialized systems.
</description>

<Rule id="install_hids" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Install Intrusion Detection Software</title>
<description>
The base Red Hat platform already includes a sophisticated auditing system that
can detect intruder activity, as well as SELinux, which provides host-based
intrusion prevention capabilities by confining privileged programs and user
sessions which may become compromised.
</description>
<warning category="general">Note in DoD environments, supplemental intrusion
detection tools, such as the McAfee Host-based Security System, are available
to integrate with existing infrastructure. When these supplemental tools
interfere with proper functioning of SELinux, SELinux takes precedence.</warning>
<ocil clause="no host-based intrusion detection tools are installed">
Inspect the system to determine if intrusion detection software has been installed.
Verify this intrusion detection software is active.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Host-based intrusion detection tools provide a system-level defense when an
intruder gains access to a system or network.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="26818-5" />
<oval id="install_hids" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SC-7" disa="1263" pcidss="Req-11.4" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="install_antivirus" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Install Virus Scanning Software</title>
<description>
Install virus scanning software, which uses signatures to search for the
presence of viruses on the filesystem.
Ensure virus definition files are no older than 7 days, or their last release.
<!-- need info here on where DoD admins can go to get this -->
Configure the virus scanning software to perform scans dynamically on all
accessed files.  If this is not possible, configure the
system to scan all altered files on the system on a daily
basis. If the system processes inbound SMTP mail, configure the virus scanner
to scan all received mail.
<!-- what's the basis for the IAO language? would not failure of a check
     imply a discussion, for every check in this document,
     with the IAO (or SSO or ISSO or ISSM or whatever is the right acronym in your
     particular neighborhood) should occur? -->
</description>
<ocil clause="virus scanning software does not run continuously, or at least daily, or has signatures that are out of date">
Inspect the system for a cron job or system service which executes
a virus scanning tool regularly.
<br/>
<!-- this should be handled as DoD-specific text in a future revision -->
To verify the McAfee VSEL system service is operational,
run the following command:
<pre>$ sudo /sbin/service nails status</pre>
<br/>
To check on the age of uvscan virus definition files, run the following command:
<pre>$ sudo cd /opt/NAI/LinuxShield/engine/dat
$ sudo ls -la avvscan.dat avvnames.dat avvclean.dat</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Virus scanning software can be used to detect if a system has been compromised by
computer viruses, as well as to limit their spread to other systems.
</rationale>
<oval id="install_antivirus" />
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="27140-3" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SC-28, SI-3" disa="1239,1668"/>
</Rule>

<Group id="mcafee_security_software">
<title>McAfee Endpoint Security Software</title>
<description>
In DoD environments, McAfee Host-based Security System (HBSS) and
VirusScan Enterprise for Linux (VSEL) is required to be installed on all systems.
</description>

<Rule id="install_mcafee_cma_rt" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Install the McAfee Runtime Libraries and Linux Agent</title>
<description>
Install the McAfee Runtime Libraries (MFErt) and Linux Agent (MFEcma).
</description>
<ocil clause="the HBSS HIPS module is not installed">
To verify that McAfee Runtime Libraries (MFErt) and Linux Agent (MFEcma)
are installed, run the following command(s):
<pre>$ rpm -q MFEcma</pre>
<pre>$ rpm -q MFErt</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
The McAfee Runtime Libraries (MFErt) and Linux Agent (MFEcma) are dependencies
for VirusScan Enterprise for Linux (VSEL) and Host-based Security System (HBSS)
to run.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80367-6" />
<oval id="install_mcafee_cma_rt" />
</Rule>

<Group id="mcafee_hbss_software">
<title>McAfee Host-Based Intrusion Detection Software (HBSS)</title>
<description>
McAfee Host-based Security System (HBSS) is a suite of software applications
used to monitor, detect, and defend computer networks and systems.
</description>

<Rule id="install_mcafee_hbss_hips" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Install the Host Intrusion Prevention System (HIPS) Module</title>
<description>
Install the McAfee Host Intrusion Prevention System (HIPS) Module if it is absolutely
necessary. If SELinux is enabled, do not install or enable this module.
</description>
<ocil clause="the HBSS HIPS module is not installed">
To verify that McAfee HIPS is installed, run the following command(s):
<pre>$ rpm -q MFEhiplsm</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Without a host-based intrusion detection tool, there is no system-level defense
when an intruder gains access to a system or network. Additionally, a host-based
intrusion prevention tool can provide methods to immediately lock out detected
intrusion attempts.
</rationale>
<warning category="general">Installing and enabling this module conflicts with SELinux.
SELinux takes precedence over this module.</warning>
<oval id="install_mcafee_hbss_hips" />
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80368-4" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SC-7,SI-4(1).1" disa="366,1263" pcidss="Req-11.4"
ossrg="STG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="install_mcafee_hbss_accm" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Install the Asset Configuration Compliance Module (ACCM)</title>
<description>
Install the Asset Configuration Compliance Module (ACCM).
</description>
<ocil clause="the HBSS ACCM module is not installed">
To verify that HBSS ACCM is installed, run the following command(s):
<pre>$ sudo ls /opt/McAfee/accm/bin/accm</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Without a host-based intrusion detection tool, there is no system-level defense
when an intruder gains access to a system or network. Additionally, a host-based
intrusion prevention tool can provide methods to immediately lock out detected
intrusion attempts.
</rationale>
<oval id="install_mcafee_hbss_accm" />
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80126-6" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SC-7,SI-4(1).1" disa="366,1263" pcidss="Req-11.4"
ossrg="STG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="install_mcafee_hbss_pa" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Install the Policy Auditor (PA) Module</title>
<description>
Install the Policy Auditor (PA) Module.
</description>
<ocil clause="the HBSS PA module is not installed">
To verify that HBSS PA is installed, run the following command(s):
<pre>$ sudo ls /opt/McAfee/auditengine/bin/auditmanager</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Without a host-based intrusion detection tool, there is no system-level defense
when an intruder gains access to a system or network. Additionally, a host-based
intrusion prevention tool can provide methods to immediately lock out detected
intrusion attempts.
</rationale>
<oval id="install_mcafee_hbss_pa" />
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80369-2" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SC-7,SI-4(1).1" disa="366,1263" pcidss="Req-11.4"
ossrg="STG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Rule id="install_mcafee_antivirus" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Install McAfee Virus Scanning Software</title>
<description>
Install McAfee VirusScan Enterprise for Linux antivirus software
which is provided for DoD systems and uses signatures to search for the
presence of viruses on the filesystem.
</description>
<ocil clause="virus scanning software is not installed or running">
To verify that McAfee VirusScan Enterprise for Linux is installed
and running, run the following command(s):
<pre>$ sudo systemctl status nails</pre>
<pre>$ rpm -q McAfeeVSEForLinux</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Virus scanning software can be used to detect if a system has been compromised by
computer viruses, as well as to limit their spread to other systems.
</rationale>
<oval id="install_mcafee_antivirus" />
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80127-4" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SC-28,SI-3,SI-3(1)(ii)" disa="366,1239,1668"
ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" stigid="032000" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_nails_enabled" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Enable nails Service</title>
<description>The <tt>nails</tt> service is used to run McAfee VirusScan Enterprise
for Linux and McAfee Host-based Security System (HBSS) services.
<systemd-service-macro enable="true" service="nails" />
</description>
<ocil><systemd-check-macro enable="true" service="nails" /></ocil>
<rationale>
Virus scanning software can be used to detect if a system has been compromised by
computer viruses, as well as to limit their spread to other systems.
</rationale>
<oval id="service_nails_enabled" />
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80128-2" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SC-28,SI-3,SI-3(1)(ii)" disa="366,1239,1668"
ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="mcafee_antivirus_definitions_updated" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Virus Scanning Software Definitions Are Updated</title>
<description>
Ensure virus definition files are no older than 7 days or their last release.
</description>
<ocil clause="signatures are out of date">
To check on the age of McAfee virus definition files, run the following command:
<pre>$ sudo cd /opt/NAI/LinuxShield/engine/dat
$ sudo ls -la avvscan.dat avvnames.dat avvclean.dat</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Virus scanning software can be used to detect if a system has been compromised by
computer viruses, as well as to limit their spread to other systems.
</rationale>
<!--oval id="mcafee_antivirus_definitions_updated" /-->
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80129-0" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SC-28,SI-3,SI-3(1)(ii)" disa="366,1239,1668"
ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" stigid="032010" />
</Rule>

</Group>

</Group>

<Group id="fips">
<title>Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS)</title>
<description>
The Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) is a computer security standard which
is developed by the U.S. Government and industry working groups to validate the quality
of cryptographic modules. The FIPS standard provides four security levels to ensure
adequate coverage of different industries, implementation of cryptographic modules, and
organizational sizes and requirements.
<br /><br />
FIPS 140-2 is the current standard for validating that mechanisms used to access cryptographic modules
utilize authentication that meets industry and government requirements. For government systems, this allows
Security Levels 1, 2, 3, or 4 for use on Red Hat Enterprise Linux.
<br /><br />
See <b><weblink-macro link="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsFIPS.html"/></b> for more information.
</description>

<Rule id="package_dracut-fips_installed" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Install the dracut-fips Package</title>
<description>
To enable FIPS, the system requires that the <tt>dracut-fips</tt>
package be installed.
<yum-macro install="true" package="dracut-fips" />
</description>
<ocil clause="the package is not installed">
<package-check-macro package="dracut-fips" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
Use of weak or untested encryption algorithms undermines the purposes of utilizing encryption to
protect data. The operating system must implement cryptographic modules adhering to the higher
standards approved by the federal government since this provides assurance they have been tested
and validated.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80358-5" />
<oval id="package_dracut-fips_installed" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="AC-17(2)" disa="68,2450"
ossrg="SRG-OS-000033-GPOS-00014,SRG-OS-000396-GPOS-00176,SRG-OS-000478-GPOS-00223" cjis="5.10.1.2"
cui="3.13.11,3.13.8" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="grub2_enable_fips_mode" severity="medium" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Enable FIPS Mode in GRUB2</title>
<description>
To ensure FIPS mode is enabled, rebuild <tt>initramfs</tt> by running the following command:
<pre>dracut -f</pre>
After the <tt>dracut</tt> command has been run, add the argument <tt>fips=1</tt> to the default
GRUB 2 command line for the Linux operating system in
<tt>/etc/default/grub</tt>, in the manner below:
<pre>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX="crashkernel=auto rd.lvm.lv=VolGroup/LogVol06 rd.lvm.lv=VolGroup/lv_swap rhgb quiet rd.shell=0 fips=1"</pre>
Finally, rebuild the <tt>grub.cfg</tt> file by using the
<pre>grub2-mkconfig -o</pre> command as follows:
<ul>
<li>On BIOS-based machines, issue the following command as <tt>root</tt>:
<pre>~]# grub2-mkconfig -o /boot/grub2/grub.cfg</pre></li>
<li>On UEFI-based machines, issue the following command as <tt>root</tt>:
<pre>~]# grub2-mkconfig -o /boot/efi/EFI/redhat/grub.cfg</pre></li>
</ul>
</description>
<ocil clause="FIPS is not configured or enabled in grub">
To verify that FIPS is enabled properly in grub, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep fips /etc/default/grub</pre>
The output should contain fips=1
</ocil>
<rationale>
Use of weak or untested encryption algorithms undermines the purposes of utilizing encryption to
protect data. The operating system must implement cryptographic modules adhering to the higher
standards approved by the federal government since this provides assurance they have been tested
and validated.
</rationale>
<platform idref="cpe:/a:machine" />
<warning category="general">Running <pre>dracut -f</pre> will overwrite the existing initramfs file.</warning>
<warning category="general">The system needs to be rebooted for these changes to take effect.</warning>
<warning category="general">The ability to enable FIPS does not denote FIPS compliancy or certification.
Red Hat, Inc. and Red Hat Enterprise Linux are respectively FIPS certified and compliant. Community
projects such as CentOS, Scientific Linux, etc. do not necessarily meet FIPS certification and compliancy.
Therefore, non-certified vendors and/or projects do not meet this requirement even if technically feasible.
<br /><br />
See <b><weblink-macro link="http://csrc.nist.gov/groups/STM/cmvp/documents/140-1/1401vend.htm"/></b> for a list of FIPS certified
vendors.</warning>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80359-3" />
<oval id="grub2_enable_fips_mode" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="AC-17(2)" disa="68,2450" stigid="021350"
ossrg="SRG-OS-000033-GPOS-00014,SRG-OS-000396-GPOS-00176,SRG-OS-000478-GPOS-00223"
cjis="5.10.1.2" cui="3.13.8,3.13.11" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="certified-vendor">
<title>Operating System Vendor Support and Certification</title>
<description>
The assurance of a vendor to provide operating system support and maintenance
for their product is an important criterion to ensure product stability and
security over the life of the product. A certified product that follows the
necessary standards and government certification requirements guarantees that
known software vulnerabilities will be remediated, and proper guidance for
protecting and securing the operating system will be given.
</description>

<Rule id="installed_OS_is_certified" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>The Installed Operating System Is Vendor Supported and Certified</title>
<description>
The installed operating system must be maintained and certified by a vendor.
Red Hat Enterprise Linux is supported by Red Hat, Inc. As the Red Hat Enterprise
Linux vendor, Red Hat, Inc. is responsible for providing security patches as well
as meeting and maintaining goverment certifications and standards.
</description>
<ocil clause="the installed operating system is not supported or certified">
To verify that the installed operating system is supported or certified, run
the following command:
<pre>$ grep -i "red hat" /etc/redhat-release</pre>
The output should contain something similar to:
<pre>Red Hat Enterprise Linux Server 7.3 (Maipo)</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
An operating system is considered "supported" if the vendor continues to provide
security patches for the product as well as maintain government certification requirements.
With an unsupported release, it will not be possible to resolve security issue discovered in
the system software as well as meet government certifications.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="80349-4" />
<oval id="installed_OS_is_certified" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SI-2(c)" disa="366" stigid="020250" ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" />
</Rule>
</Group>

</Group>
