<Group id="updating">
<title>Updating Software</title>
<description>The <tt>yum</tt> command line tool is used to install and
update software packages. The system also provides a graphical
software update tool in the <b>System</b> menu, in the <b>Administration</b> submenu,
called <b>Software Update</b>.
<br /><br />
Red Hat Enterprise Linux systems contain an installed software catalog called
the RPM database, which records metadata of installed packages. Consistently using
<tt>yum</tt> or the graphical <b>Software Update</b> for all software installation
allows for insight into the current inventory of installed software on the system.
</description>

<Rule id="ensure_redhat_gpgkey_installed" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Ensure Red Hat GPG Key Installed</title>
<description>
To ensure the system can cryptographically verify base software
packages come from Red Hat (and to connect to the Red Hat Network to
receive them), the Red Hat GPG key must properly be installed.  
To install the Red Hat GPG key, run:
<pre>$ sudo rhn_register</pre>
If the system is not connected to the Internet or an RHN Satellite,
then install the Red Hat GPG key from trusted media such as
the Red Hat installation CD-ROM or DVD. Assuming the disc is mounted
in <tt>/media/cdrom</tt>, use the following command as the root user to import
it into the keyring:
<pre>$ sudo rpm --import /media/cdrom/RPM-GPG-KEY</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the Red Hat GPG Key is not installed">
To ensure that the GPG key is installed, run:
<pre>$ rpm -q --queryformat "%{SUMMARY}\n" gpg-pubkey</pre>
The command should return the string below:
<pre>gpg(Red Hat, Inc. (release key 2)  &lt;security@redhat.com&gt;</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Changes to software components can have significant effects on the
overall security of the operating system. This requirement ensures
the software has not been tampered with and that it has been provided 
by a trusted vendor. The Red Hat GPG key is necessary to 
cryptographically verify packages are from Red Hat.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="26957-1" />
<oval id="ensure_redhat_gpgkey_installed" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-5(3),SI-7,MA-1(b)" disa="1749" ossrg="366" 
pcidss="Req-6.2" cis="1.2.2" cjis="5.10.4.1" cui="3.4.8" />
</Rule>

<!-- REMINDER: Before telling people to update their systems
     via the security_patches_up_to_date rule, we must
     ensure they have configured an update source! -->
<Rule id="ensure_gpgcheck_globally_activated" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Ensure gpgcheck Enabled In Main Yum Configuration</title>
<description>The <tt>gpgcheck</tt> option controls whether
RPM packages' signatures are always checked prior to installation.
To configure yum to check package signatures before installing
them, ensure the following line appears in <tt>/etc/yum.conf</tt> in
the <tt>[main]</tt> section:
<pre>gpgcheck=1</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="GPG checking is not enabled">
To determine whether <tt>yum</tt> is configured to use <tt>gpgcheck</tt>,
inspect <tt>/etc/yum.conf</tt> and ensure the following appears in the
<tt>[main]</tt> section:
<pre>gpgcheck=1</pre>
A value of <tt>1</tt> indicates that <tt>gpgcheck</tt> is enabled. Absence of a
<tt>gpgcheck</tt> line or a setting of <tt>0</tt> indicates that it is
disabled.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Changes to any software components can have significant effects on the overall security 
of the operating system. This requirement ensures the software has not been tampered with
and that it has been provided by a trusted vendor.
<br />
Accordingly, patches, service packs, device drivers, or operating system components must
be signed with a certificate recognized and approved by the organization.
<br />
Verifying the authenticity of the software prior to installation
validates the integrity of the patch or upgrade received from
a vendor. This ensures the software has not been tampered with and
that it has been provided by a trusted vendor. Self-signed
certificates are disallowed by this requirement. Certificates
used to verify the software must be from an approved Certificate
Authority (CA).
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="26989-4" />
<oval id="ensure_gpgcheck_globally_activated" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-5(3),SI-7,MA-1(b)" disa="1749" ossrg="SRG-OS-000366-GPOS-00153" 
stigid="020050" pcidss="Req-6.2" cis="1.2.3" cjis="5.10.4.1" cui="3.4.8" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ensure_gpgcheck_never_disabled" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Ensure gpgcheck Enabled For All Yum Package Repositories</title>
<description>To ensure signature checking is not disabled for
any repos, remove any lines from files in <tt>/etc/yum.repos.d</tt> of the form:
<pre>gpgcheck=0</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="GPG checking is disabled">
To determine whether <tt>yum</tt> has been configured to disable
<tt>gpgcheck</tt> for any repos,  inspect all files in
<tt>/etc/yum.repos.d</tt> and ensure the following does not appear in any
sections:
<pre>gpgcheck=0</pre>
A value of <tt>0</tt> indicates that <tt>gpgcheck</tt> has been disabled for that repo. 
</ocil>
<rationale>
Verifying the authenticity of the software prior to installation
validates the integrity of the patch or upgrade received from
a vendor. This ensures the software has not been tampered with and
that it has been provided by a trusted vendor. Self-signed 
certificates are disallowed by this requirement. Certificates
used to verify the software must be from an approved Certificate
Authority (CA).
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="26876-3" />
<oval id="ensure_gpgcheck_never_disabled" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-5(3),SI-7,MA-1(b)" disa="1749" ossrg="366" pcidss="Req-6.2" 
cjis="5.10.4.1" cui="3.4.8" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="security_patches_up_to_date" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Ensure Software Patches Installed</title>
<description>If the system is joined to the Red Hat Network, a Red Hat Satellite Server,
or a yum server, run the following command to install updates:
<pre>$ sudo yum update</pre>
If the system is not configured to use one of these sources, updates (in the form of RPM packages)
can be manually downloaded from the Red Hat Network and installed using <tt>rpm</tt>.
<br /><br />
NOTE: U.S. Defense systems are required to be patched within 30 days or sooner as local policy
dictates.
</description>
<!-- Directly define remotely located OVAL to be executed when scanning this rule -->
<check system="http://oval.mitre.org/XMLSchema/oval-definitions-5">
  <check-content-ref href="https://www.redhat.com/security/data/oval/com.redhat.rhsa-RHEL7.xml.bz2" />
</check>
<ocil clause="updates are not installed">
If the system is joined to the Red Hat Network, a Red Hat Satellite Server, or
a yum server which provides updates, invoking the following command will
indicate if updates are available:
<pre>$ sudo yum check-update</pre>
<br /><br />
If the system is not configured to update from one of these sources,
run the following command to list when each package was last updated:
<pre>$ rpm -qa -last</pre>
<br /><br />
Compare this to Red Hat Security Advisories (RHSA) listed at
<weblink-macro link="https://access.redhat.com/security/updates/active/"/>
to determine if the system is missing applicable updates.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Installing software updates is a fundamental mitigation against
the exploitation of publicly-known vulnerabilities. If the most
recent security patches and updates are not installed, unauthorized
users may take advantage of weaknesses in the unpatched software. The
lack of prompt attention to patching could result in a system compromise.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="26895-3" />
<!-- Particular OVAL check is defined directly via <check> element above -->
<!-- DO NOT REFERENCE an OVAL id here !!! -->
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SI-2,SI-2(c),MA-1(b)" disa="366" pcidss="Req-6.2" cis="1.7"
ossrg="SRG-OS-000480-GPOS-00227" stigid="020260" cjis="5.10.4.1" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="clean_components_post_updating" severity="low" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Ensure YUM Removes Previous Package Versions</title>
<description>
<tt>Yum</tt> should be configured to remove previous software components after
previous versions have been installed. To configure <tt>yum</tt> to remove the
previous software components after updating, set the <tt>clean_requirements_on_remove</tt>
to <tt>1</tt> in <tt>/etc/yum.conf</tt>.
</description>
<ocil clause="clean_requirements_on_remove is not enabled or configured correctly">
To verify that <tt>clean_requirements_on_remove</tt> is configured properly, run the
following command:
<pre>$ grep clean_requirements_on_remove /etc/yum.conf</pre>
The output should return something similar to:
<pre>clean_requirements_on_remove=1</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Previous versions of software components that are not removed from the information
system after updates have been installed may be exploited by some adversaries.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="CCE-80346-0" />
<oval id="clean_components_post_updating" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="SI-2(6)" disa="2617" ossrg="SRG-OS-000437-GPOS-00194" 
stigid="020200" cui="3.4.8" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ensure_gpgcheck_local_packages" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Ensure gpgcheck Enabled for Local Packages</title>
<description>
<tt>Yum</tt> should be configured to verify the signature(s) of local packages
prior to installation. To configure <tt>yum</tt> to verify signatures of local
packages, set the <tt>localpkg_gpgcheck</tt> to <tt>1</tt> in <tt>/etc/yum.conf</tt>.
</description>
<ocil clause="gpgcheck is not enabled or configured correctly to verify local packages">
To verify that <tt>localpkg_gpgcheck</tt> is configured properly, run the following
command:
<pre>$ grep localpkg_gpgcheck /etc/yum.conf</pre>
The output should return something similar to:
<pre>localpkg_gpgcheck=1</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Changes to any software components can have significant effects to the overall security
of the operating system. This requirement ensures the software has not been tampered and
has been provided by a trusted vendor.
<br/><br/>
Accordingly, patches, service packs, device drivers, or operating system components must
be signed with a certificate recognized and approved by the organization.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="CCE-80347-8" />
<oval id="ensure_gpgcheck_local_packages" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-5(3)" disa="1749" ossrg="SRG-OS-000366-GPOS-00153" 
stigid="020060" cui="3.4.8" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ensure_gpgcheck_repo_metadata" severity="high" prodtype="rhel7">
<title>Ensure gpgcheck Enabled for Repository Metadata</title>
<description>
Verify the operating system prevents the installation of patches, service packs, device
drivers, or operating system components of local packages without verification of the 
repository metadata.
<br /><br />
Check that <tt>yum</tt> verifies the repository metadata prior to install with the
following command. This should be configured by setting <tt>repo_gpgcheck</tt> to <tt>1</tt>
in <tt>/etc/yum.conf</tt>.
</description>
<ocil clause="gpgcheck is not enabled or configured correctly to verify repository metadata">
To verify that <tt>repo_gpgcheck</tt> is configured properly, run the following
command:
<pre>$ grep repo_gpgcheck /etc/yum.conf</pre>
The output should return something similar to:
<pre>repo_gpgcheck=1</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Changes to any software components can have significant effects to the overall security
of the operating system. This requirement ensures the software has not been tampered and
has been provided by a trusted vendor.
<br/><br/>
Accordingly, patches, service packs, device drivers, or operating system components must
be signed with a certificate recognized and approved by the organization.
<br /><br />
Verifying the authenticity of the software prior to installation validates the integrity
of the patch or upgrade received from a vendor. This ensures the software has not been
tampered with and that it has been provided by a trusted vendor. Self-signed certificates
are disallowed by this requirement. The operating system should not have to verify the software
again.
<br /><br />
NOTE: For U.S. Military systems, this requirement does not mandate DoD certificates for
this purpose; however, the certificate used to verify the software must be from an 
approved Certificate Authority.
</rationale>
<ident prodtype="rhel7" cce="CCE-80348-6" />
<oval id="ensure_gpgcheck_repo_metadata" />
<ref prodtype="rhel7" nist="CM-5(3)" disa="1749" ossrg="SRG-OS-000366-GPOS-00153" stigid="020070" />
</Rule>

</Group>
