<Group id="base">
<title>Base Services</title>
<description>This section addresses the base services that are installed on a
Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6 default installation which are not covered in other
sections. Some of these services listen on the network and
should be treated with particular discretion. Other services are local
system utilities that may or may not be extraneous. In general, system services
should be disabled if not required.</description>

<Rule id="service_abrtd_disabled">
<title>Disable Automatic Bug Reporting Tool (abrtd)</title>
<description>The Automatic Bug Reporting Tool (<tt>abrtd</tt>) daemon collects
and reports crash data when an application crash is detected. Using a variety
of plugins, abrtd can email crash reports to system administrators, log crash
reports to files, or forward crash reports to a centralized issue tracking
system such as RHTSupport.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="abrtd" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="abrtd" /></ocil>
<rationale> Mishandling crash data could expose sensitive information about
vulnerabilities in software executing on the local system, as well as sensitive
information from within a process's address space or registers.</rationale>
<ident cce="27247-6" stig="RHEL-06-000261" />
<oval id="service_abrtd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="381" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_acpid_disabled">
<title>Disable Advanced Configuration and Power Interface (acpid)</title>
<description>The Advanced Configuration and Power Interface Daemon (<tt>acpid</tt>)
dispatches ACPI events (such as power/reset button depressed) to userspace
programs.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="acpid" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="acpid" /></ocil>
<rationale>ACPI support is highly desirable for systems in some network roles,
such as laptops or desktops. For other systems, such as servers, it may permit
accidental or trivially achievable denial of service situations and disabling
it is appropriate.</rationale>
<ident cce="27061-1" />
<oval id="service_acpid_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_certmonger_disabled">
<title>Disable Certmonger Service (certmonger)</title>
<description>Certmonger is a D-Bus based service that attempts to simplify interaction
with certifying authorities on networks which use public-key infrastructure. It is often
combined with Red Hat's IPA (Identity Policy Audit) security information management
solution to aid in the management of certificates.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="certmonger" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="certmonger" /></ocil>
<rationale>The services provided by certmonger may be essential for systems
fulfilling some roles a PKI infrastructure, but its functionality is not necessary
for many other use cases.</rationale>
<ident cce="27267-4" />
<oval id="service_certmonger_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_cgconfig_disabled">
<title>Disable Control Group Config (cgconfig)</title>
<description>Control groups allow an administrator to allocate system resources (such as CPU,
memory, network bandwidth, etc) among a defined group (or groups) of processes executing on
a system. The <tt>cgconfig</tt> daemon starts at boot and establishes the predefined control groups.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="cgconfig" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="cgconfig" /></ocil>
<rationale>Unless control groups are used to manage system resources, running the cgconfig
service is not necessary.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27250-0" />
<oval id="service_cgconfig_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_cgred_disabled">
<title>Disable Control Group Rules Engine (cgred)</title>
<description>The <tt>cgred</tt> service moves tasks into control groups according to
parameters set in the <tt>/etc/cgrules.conf</tt> configuration file.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="cgred" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="cgred" /></ocil>
<rationale>Unless control groups are used to manage system resources, running the cgred service
service is not necessary.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27252-6" />
<oval id="service_cgred_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_cpuspeed_disabled">
<title>Disable CPU Speed (cpuspeed)</title>
<description>The <tt>cpuspeed</tt> service can adjust the clock speed of supported CPUs based upon
the current processing load thereby conserving power and reducing heat.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="cpuspeed" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="cpuspeed" /></ocil>
<rationale>The <tt>cpuspeed</tt> service is only necessary if adjusting the CPU clock speed
provides benefit. Traditionally this has included laptops (to enhance battery life),
but may also apply to server or desktop environments where conserving power is
highly desirable or necessary.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26973-8" />
<oval id="service_cpuspeed_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_haldaemon_disabled">
<title>Disable Hardware Abstraction Layer Service (haldaemon)</title>
<description>The Hardware Abstraction Layer Daemon (<tt>haldaemon</tt>) collects
and maintains information about the system's hardware configuration. 
This service is required on a workstation
running a desktop environment, and may be necessary on any system which
deals with removable media or devices.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="haldaemon" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="haldaemon" /></ocil>
<rationale>The haldaemon provides essential functionality on systems
that use removable media or devices, but can be disabled for systems
that do not require these.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27086-8" />
<oval id="service_haldaemon_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_irqbalance_enabled">
<title>Enable IRQ Balance (irqbalance)</title>
<description>The <tt>irqbalance</tt> service optimizes the balance between
power savings and performance through distribution of hardware interrupts across
multiple processors.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="true" service="irqbalance" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="irqbalance" /></ocil>
<rationale>In an environment with multiple processors (now common), the irqbalance service
provides potential speedups for handling interrupt requests.</rationale>
<platform idref="cpe:/a:machine" />
<ident cce="26990-2" />
<oval id="service_irqbalance_enabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_kdump_disabled">
<title>Disable KDump Kernel Crash Analyzer (kdump)</title>
<description>The <tt>kdump</tt> service provides a kernel crash dump analyzer. It uses the <tt>kexec</tt>
system call to boot a secondary kernel ("capture" kernel) following a system
crash, which can load information from the crashed kernel for analysis.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="kdump" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="kdump" /></ocil>
<rationale>Unless the system is used for kernel development or testing, there
is little need to run the kdump service.</rationale>
<platform idref="cpe:/a:machine" />
<ident cce="26850-8" />
<oval id="service_kdump_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>


<Rule id="service_mdmonitor_disabled">
<title>Disable Software RAID Monitor (mdmonitor)</title>
<description>The <tt>mdmonitor</tt> service is used for monitoring a software RAID array; hardware
RAID setups do not use this service.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="mdmonitor" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="mdmonitor" /></ocil>
<rationale>If software RAID monitoring is not required,
there is no need to run this service.</rationale>
<ident cce="27193-2" />
<oval id="service_mdmonitor_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_messagebus_disabled">
<title>Disable D-Bus IPC Service (messagebus)</title>
<description>D-Bus provides an IPC mechanism used by 
a growing list of programs, such as those used for Gnome, Bluetooth, and Avahi.
Due to these dependencies, disabling D-Bus may not be practical for
many systems.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="messagebus" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="messagebus" /></ocil>
<rationale>If no services which require D-Bus are needed, then it
can be disabled. As a broker for IPC between processes of different privilege levels,
it could be a target for attack. However, disabling D-Bus is likely to be
impractical for any system which needs to provide
a graphical login session.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26913-4" />
<oval id="service_messagebus_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_netconsole_disabled">
<title>Disable Network Console (netconsole)</title>
<description>The <tt>netconsole</tt> service is responsible for loading the
netconsole kernel module, which logs kernel printk messages over UDP to a
syslog server. This allows debugging of problems where disk logging fails and
serial consoles are impractical.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="netconsole" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="netconsole" /></ocil>
<rationale>The <tt>netconsole</tt> service is not necessary unless there is a need to debug
kernel panics, which is not common.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27254-2" stig="RHEL-06-000289" />
<oval id="service_netconsole_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="381" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_ntpdate_disabled">
<title>Disable ntpdate Service (ntpdate)</title>
<description>The <tt>ntpdate</tt> service sets the local hardware clock by polling NTP servers
when the system boots. It synchronizes to the NTP servers listed in
<tt>/etc/ntp/step-tickers</tt> or <tt>/etc/ntp.conf</tt>
and then sets the local hardware clock to the newly synchronized
system time.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="ntpdate" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="ntpdate" /></ocil>
<rationale>The <tt>ntpdate</tt> service may only be suitable for systems which
are rebooted frequently enough that clock drift does not cause problems between
reboots. In any event, the functionality of the ntpdate service is now
available in the ntpd program and should be considered deprecated.</rationale>
<ident cce="27256-7" stig="RHEL-06-000265" />
<oval id="service_ntpdate_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="382" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_oddjobd_disabled">
<title>Disable Odd Job Daemon (oddjobd)</title>
<description>The <tt>oddjobd</tt> service exists to provide an interface and
access control mechanism through which
specified privileged tasks can run tasks for unprivileged client
applications. Communication with <tt>oddjobd</tt> through the system message bus.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="oddjobd" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="oddjobd" /></ocil>
<rationale>The <tt>oddjobd</tt> service may provide necessary functionality in
some environments, and can be disabled if it is not needed. Execution of
tasks by privileged programs, on behalf of unprivileged ones, has traditionally
been a source of privilege escalation security issues.</rationale>
<ident cce="27257-5" stig="RHEL-06-000266" />
<oval id="service_oddjobd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="381" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_portreserve_disabled">
<title>Disable Portreserve (portreserve)</title>
<description>The <tt>portreserve</tt> service is a TCP port reservation utility that can
be used to prevent portmap from binding to well known TCP ports that are
required for other services.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="portreserve" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="portreserve" /></ocil>
<rationale>The <tt>portreserve</tt> service provides helpful functionality by
preventing conflicting usage of ports in the reserved port range, but it can be
disabled if not needed.</rationale>
<ident cce="27258-3" />
<oval id="service_portreserve_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_psacct_enabled">
<title>Enable Process Accounting (psacct)</title>
<description>The process accounting service, <tt>psacct</tt>, works with programs
including <tt>acct</tt> and <tt>ac</tt> to allow system administrators to view
user activity, such as commands issued by users of the system.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="true" service="psacct" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="psacct" /></ocil>
<rationale>The <tt>psacct</tt> service can provide administrators a convenient
view into some user activities. However, it should be noted that the auditing
system and its audit records provide more authoritative and comprehensive
records.</rationale>
<ident cce="27259-1" />
<oval id="service_psacct_enabled" />
<ref nist="AU-12,CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_qpidd_disabled">
<title>Disable Apache Qpid (qpidd)</title>
<description>The <tt>qpidd</tt> service provides high speed, secure,
guaranteed delivery services.  It is an implementation of the Advanced Message
Queuing Protocol.  By default the qpidd service will bind to port 5672 and
listen for connection attempts.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="qpidd" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="qpidd" /></ocil>
<rationale>The qpidd service is automatically installed when the "base" 
package selection is selected during installation.  The qpidd service listens 
for network connections, which increases the attack surface of the system.  If 
the system is not intended to receive AMQP traffic, then the <tt>qpidd</tt> 
service is not needed and should be disabled or removed.</rationale>
<ident cce="26928-2" stig="RHEL-06-000267" />
<oval id="service_qpidd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="382" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_quota_nld_disabled">
<title>Disable Quota Netlink (quota_nld)</title>
<description>The <tt>quota_nld</tt> service provides notifications to
users of disk space quota violations. It listens to the kernel via a netlink
socket for disk quota violations and notifies the appropriate user of the
violation using D-Bus or by sending a message to the terminal that the user has
last accessed.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="quota_nld" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="quota_nld" /></ocil>
<rationale>If disk quotas are enforced on the local system, then the
<tt>quota_nld</tt> service likely provides useful functionality and should
remain enabled. However, if disk quotas are not used or user notification of
disk quota violation is not desired then there is no need to run this
service.</rationale>
<ident cce="27260-9" />
<oval id="service_quota_nld_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_rdisc_disabled">
<title>Disable Network Router Discovery Daemon (rdisc)</title>
<description>The <tt>rdisc</tt> service implements the client side of the ICMP
Internet Router Discovery Protocol (IRDP), which allows discovery of routers on
the local subnet. If a router is discovered then the local routing table is
updated with a corresponding default route. By default this daemon is disabled.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="rdisc" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="rdisc" /></ocil>
<rationale>General-purpose systems typically have their network and routing
information configured statically by a system administrator. Workstations or
some special-purpose systems often use DHCP (instead of IRDP) to retrieve
dynamic network configuration information.</rationale>
<ident cce="27261-7" stig="RHEL-06-000268" />
<oval id="service_rdisc_disabled" />
<ref nist="AC-4,CM-7" disa="382" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_rhnsd_disabled">
<title>Disable Red Hat Network Service (rhnsd)</title>
<description>The Red Hat Network service automatically queries Red Hat Network
servers to determine whether there are any actions that should be executed,
such as package updates. This only occurs if the system was registered to an
RHN server or satellite and managed as such.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="rhnsd" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="rhnsd" /></ocil>
<rationale>Although systems management and patching is extremely important to
system security, management by a system outside the enterprise enclave is not
desirable for some environments.  However, if the system is being managed by RHN or
 RHN Satellite Server the <tt>rhnsd</tt> daemon can remain on. </rationale>
<ident cce="26846-6" stig="RHEL-06-000009" />
<oval id="service_rhnsd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="382" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_rhsmcertd_disabled">
<title>Disable Red Hat Subscription Manager Daemon (rhsmcertd)</title>
<description>The Red Hat Subscription Manager (rhsmcertd) periodically checks for
changes in the entitlement certificates for a registered system and updates it
accordingly.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="rhsmcertd" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="rhsmcertd" /></ocil>
<rationale>The <tt>rhsmcertd</tt> service can provide administrators with some
additional control over which of their systems are entitled to particular
subscriptions. However, for systems that are managed locally or which are not
expected to require remote changes to their subscription status, it is
unnecessary and can be disabled.</rationale>
<ident cce="27262-5" />
<oval id="service_rhsmcertd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_saslauthd_disabled">
<title>Disable Cyrus SASL Authentication Daemon (saslauthd)</title>
<description>The <tt>saslauthd</tt> service handles plaintext authentication requests on
behalf of the SASL library. The service isolates all code requiring superuser
privileges for SASL authentication into a single process, and can also be used
to provide proxy authentication services to clients that do not understand SASL
based authentication.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="saslauthd" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="saslauthd" /></ocil>
<rationale>The <tt>saslauthd</tt> service provides essential functionality for
performing authentication in some directory environments, such as those which
use Kerberos and LDAP. For others, however, in which only local files may be
consulted, it is not necessary and should be disabled.</rationale>
<ident cce="27263-3" />
<oval id="service_saslauthd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_smartd_disabled">
<title>Disable SMART Disk Monitoring Service (smartd)</title>
<description>SMART (Self-Monitoring, Analysis, and Reporting Technology) is a
feature of hard drives that allows them to detect symptoms of disk failure and
relay an appropriate warning.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="smartd" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="smartd" /></ocil>
<rationale>SMART can help protect against denial of
service due to failing hardware. Nevertheless, if it is not needed or the
system's drives are not SMART-capable (such as solid state drives), it can be
disabled.</rationale>
<ident cce="26853-2" />
<oval id="service_smartd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>


<Rule id="service_sysstat_disabled">
<title>Disable System Statistics Reset Service (sysstat)</title>
<description>The <tt>sysstat</tt> service resets various I/O and CPU
performance statistics to zero in order to begin counting from a fresh state
at boot time.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="sysstat" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="sysstat" /></ocil>
<rationale>By default the <tt>sysstat</tt> service merely runs a program at
boot to reset the statistics, which can be retrieved using programs such as
<tt>sar</tt> and <tt>sadc</tt>. These may provide useful insight into system
operation, but unless used this service can be disabled.</rationale>
<ident cce="27265-8" />
<oval id="service_sysstat_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

</Group>
