<Group id="dhcp">
<title>DHCP</title>
<description>The Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) allows
systems to request and obtain an IP address and other configuration
parameters from a server.
<br /><br />
This guide recommends configuring networking on clients by manually editing
the appropriate files under <tt>/etc/sysconfig</tt>.  Use of DHCP can make client 
systems vulnerable to compromise by rogue DHCP servers, and should be avoided 
unless necessary.  If using DHCP is necessary, however, there are best practices 
that should be followed to minimize security risk.
</description>


<Group id="disabling_dhcp_server">
<title>Disable DHCP Server</title>
<description>
The DHCP server <tt>dhcpd</tt> is not installed or activated by
default. If the software was installed and activated, but the
system does not need to act as a DHCP server, it should be disabled
and removed.
</description>

<Rule id="service_dhcpd_disabled" severity="medium">
<title>Disable DHCP Service</title>
<description>The <tt>dhcpd</tt> service should be disabled on
any system that does not need to act as a DHCP server.
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="dhcpd" />
</description>
<ocil><service-check-macro enable="false" service="dhcpd" /></ocil>
<rationale>
Unmanaged or unintentionally activated DHCP servers may provide faulty information
to clients, interfering with the operation of a legitimate site
DHCP server if there is one.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27074-4" />
<oval id="service_dhcpd_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="366"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_dhcp_removed" severity="medium">
<title>Uninstall DHCP Server Package</title>
<description>If the system does not need to act as a DHCP server,
the dhcp package can be uninstalled.
<yum-macro install="false" package="dhcp" />
</description>
<ocil><package-check-macro package="dhcp" /></ocil>
<rationale>
Removing the DHCP server ensures that it cannot be easily or
accidentally reactivated and disrupt network operation.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27120-5" />
<oval id="package_dhcp_removed" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="366"/>
</Rule>

</Group> <!-- <Group id="disabling_dhcp_server"> -->

<Group id="dhcp_server_configuration">
<title>Disable DHCP Server</title>
<description>If the system must act as a DHCP server, the configuration
information it serves should be minimized. Also, support for other protocols
and DNS-updating schemes should be explicitly disabled unless needed. The
configuration file for dhcpd is called <tt>/etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</tt>. The file
begins with a number of global configuration options. The remainder of the file
is divided into sections, one for each block of addresses offered by dhcpd,
each of which contains configuration options specific to that address
block.</description>

<Rule id="dhcp_server_disable_ddns">
<title>Do Not Use Dynamic DNS</title>
<description>To prevent the DHCP server from receiving DNS information from
clients, edit <tt>/etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</tt>, and add or correct the following global
option: <pre>ddns-update-style none;</pre>
</description>
<rationale>The Dynamic DNS protocol is used to remotely update the data served
by a DNS server. DHCP servers can use Dynamic DNS to publish information about
their clients. This setup carries security risks, and its use is not
recommended.  If Dynamic DNS must be used despite the risks it poses, it is
critical that Dynamic DNS transactions be protected using TSIG or some other
cryptographic authentication mechanism. See dhcpd.conf(5) for more information
about protecting the DHCP server from passing along malicious DNS data from its
clients.  </rationale>
<warning category="general">The ddns-update-style option controls only whether
the DHCP server will attempt to act as a Dynamic DNS client. As long as the DNS
server itself is correctly configured to reject DDNS attempts, an incorrect
ddns-update-style setting on the client is harmless (but should be fixed as a
best practice).</warning>
<ident cce="27049-6" />
<oval id="dhcp_server_disable_ddns" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="dhcp_server_deny_decline">
<title>Deny Decline Messages</title>
<description>Edit <tt>/etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</tt> and add or correct the following
global option to prevent the DHCP server from responding the DHCPDECLINE
messages, if possible: <pre>deny declines;</pre> </description>
<rationale>The DHCPDECLINE message can be sent by a DHCP client to indicate
that it does not consider the lease offered by the server to be valid. By
issuing many DHCPDECLINE messages, a malicious client can exhaust the DHCP
server's pool of IP addresses, causing the DHCP server to forget old address
allocations.</rationale>
<ident cce="27106-4" />
<oval id="dhcp_server_deny_decline" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="dhcp_server_deny_bootp">
<title>Deny BOOTP Queries</title>
<description>Unless your network needs to support older BOOTP clients, disable
support for the bootp protocol by adding or correcting the global option:
<pre>deny bootp;</pre>
</description>
<rationale>The bootp option tells dhcpd to respond to BOOTP queries. If support
for this simpler protocol is not needed, it should be disabled to remove attack
vectors against the DHCP server.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27077-7" />
<oval id="dhcp_server_deny_bootp" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="dhcp_server_minimize_served_info">
<title>Minimize Served Information</title>
<description>Edit /etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf. Examine each address range section within
the file, and ensure that the following options are not defined unless there is
an operational need to provide this information via DHCP:
<pre>option domain-name
option domain-name-servers
option nis-domain
option nis-servers
option ntp-servers
option routers
option time-offset</pre>
</description>
<rationale>Because the configuration information provided by the DHCP server
could be maliciously provided to clients by a rogue DHCP server, the amount of
information provided via DHCP should be minimized. Remove these definitions
from the DHCP server configuration to ensure that legitimate clients do not
unnecessarily rely on DHCP for this information.
</rationale>
<warning category="general">By default, the Red Hat Enterprise Linux client installation uses DHCP
to request much of the above information from the DHCP server. In particular,
domain-name, domain-name-servers, and routers are configured via DHCP.  These
settings are typically necessary for proper network functionality, but are also
usually static across systems at a given site.</warning>
<!--<ident cce="26897-9" />
<ident cce="27042-1" />
<ident cce="27103-1" />
<ident cce="26943-1" />
<ident cce="27008-2" />
<ident cce="27064-5" />
<ident cce="27065-2" />-->
<oval id="dhcp_server_minimize_served_info" />
<ref nist="CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="dhcp_server_configure_logging">
<title>Configure Logging</title>
<description>Ensure that the following line exists in
<tt>/etc/rsyslog.conf</tt>:
<pre>daemon.*           /var/log/daemon.log</pre>
Configure logwatch or other log monitoring tools to summarize error conditions
reported by the dhcpd process.</description>
<rationale>By default, dhcpd logs notices to the daemon facility. Sending all
daemon messages to a dedicated log file is part of the syslog configuration
outlined in the Logging and Auditing section</rationale>
<ident cce="26898-7" />
<oval id="dhcp_server_configure_logging" />
<ref nist="AU-12" />
</Rule>

</Group> <!-- <Group id="dhcp_server_configuration"> -->

<Group id="disabling_dhcp_client">
<title>Disable DHCP Client</title>
<description>
DHCP is the default network configuration method provided by the system
installer, and common on many networks. Nevertheless, manual management
of IP addresses for systems implies a greater degree of management and
accountability for network activity.
</description>

<Rule id="sysconfig_networking_bootproto_ifcfg">
<title>Disable DHCP Client</title>
<description>
For each interface on the system (e.g. eth0), edit
<tt>/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-<i>interface</i></tt> and make the
following changes:
<ul>
<li> Correct the BOOTPROTO line to read:
<pre>BOOTPROTO=none</pre>
</li>
<li> Add or correct the following lines, substituting the appropriate
values based on your site's addressing scheme:
<pre>NETMASK=255.255.255.0
IPADDR=192.168.1.2
GATEWAY=192.168.1.1</pre>
</li>
</ul>
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not">
To verify that DHCP is not being used, examine the following file for each interface:
<pre># /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-<i>interface</i></pre>
Look for the following:
<pre>BOOTPROTO=none</pre>
and the following, substituting the appropriate values based on your site's addressing scheme:
<pre>NETMASK=255.255.255.0
IPADDR=192.168.1.2
GATEWAY=192.168.1.1</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
DHCP relies on trusting the local network. If the local network is not trusted,
then it should not be used.  However, the automatic configuration provided by
DHCP is commonly used and the alternative, manual configuration, presents an
unacceptable burden in many circumstances.</rationale>
<ident cce="27021-5" stig="RHEL-06-000292" />
<oval id="sysconfig_networking_bootproto_ifcfg" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="366"/>
</Rule>
</Group> <!-- <Group id="disabling_dhcp_client"> -->

<Group id="dhcp_client_configuration">
<title>Configure DHCP Client if Necessary</title>
<description>If DHCP must be used, then certain configuration changes can
minimize the amount of information it receives and applies from the network,
and thus the amount of incorrect information a rogue DHCP server could
successfully distribute.  For more information on configuring dhclient, see the
<tt>dhclient(8)</tt> and <tt>dhclient.conf(5)</tt> man pages.  </description>

<Rule id="dhcp_client_restrict_options">
<title>Minimize the DHCP-Configured Options</title>
<description>Create the file <tt>/etc/dhcp/dhclient.conf</tt>, and add an
appropriate setting for each of the ten configuration settings which can be
obtained via DHCP. For each setting, do one of the following:
<br/>
If the setting should <i>not</i> be configured remotely by the DHCP server,
select an appropriate static value, and add the line:
<pre>supersede <tt>setting value</tt>;</pre>
If the setting should be configured remotely by the DHCP server, add the lines:
<pre>request <tt>setting</tt>;
require <tt>setting</tt>;</pre>
For example, suppose the DHCP server should provide only the IP address itself
and the subnet mask. Then the entire file should look like:
<pre>supersede domain-name "example.com";
supersede domain-name-servers 192.168.1.2;
supersede nis-domain "";
supersede nis-servers "";
supersede ntp-servers "ntp.example.com ";
supersede routers 192.168.1.1;
supersede time-offset -18000;
request subnet-mask;
require subnet-mask;</pre>
</description>
<rationale>By default, the DHCP client program, dhclient, requests and applies
ten configuration options (in addition to the IP address) from the DHCP server.
subnet-mask, broadcast-address, time-offset, routers, domain-name,
domain-name-servers, host-name, nis-domain, nis-servers, and ntp-servers.  Many
of the options requested and applied by dhclient may be the same for every
system on a network. It is recommended that almost all configuration options be
assigned statically, and only options which must vary on a host-by-host basis
be assigned via DHCP. This limits the damage which can be done by a rogue DHCP
server.  If appropriate for your site, it is also possible to supersede the
host-name directive in <tt>/etc/dhcp/dhclient.conf</tt>, establishing a static
hostname for the system. However, dhclient does not use the host name option
provided by the DHCP server (instead using the value provided by a reverse DNS
lookup).</rationale>
<warning category="general">In this example, the options nis-servers and
nis-domain are set to empty strings, on the assumption that the deprecated NIS
protocol is not in use. It is necessary to supersede settings for unused
services so that they cannot be set by a hostile DHCP server. If an option is
set to an empty string, dhclient will typically not attempt to configure the
service.</warning>
<!--<ident cce="27120-5" /> -->
<oval id="dhcp_client_restrict_options" />
<!--<ref nist="CM-7" /> -->
</Rule>

</Group> <!-- <Group id="dhcp_client_configuration"> -->
</Group> <!-- <Group id="dhcp"> -->
