<Group id="ldap">
<title>LDAP</title>
<description>LDAP is a popular directory service, that is, a
standardized way of looking up information from a central database.
It is relatively simple to configure a RHEL6 machine to obtain
authentication information from an LDAP server. If your network
uses LDAP for authentication, be sure to configure both clients and
servers securely.</description>

<Group id="openldap_client">
<title>Configure OpenLDAP Clients</title>
<description>This guide recommends configuring OpenLDAP clients by
manually editing the appropriate configuration files. RHEL6
provides an automated configuration tool called authconfig and a
graphical wrapper for authconfig called
<tt>system-config-authentication</tt>. However, these tools do not give
sufficient flexibility over configuration. The authconfig tools do
not allow you to specify locations of SSL certificate files, which
is useful when trying to use SSL cleanly across several protocols.
They are also overly aggressive in placing services such as
netgroups and automounter maps under LDAP control, where it is
safer to use LDAP only for services to which it is relevant in your
environment.</description>
<warning category="general">Before configuring any machine to be an
LDAP client, ensure that a working LDAP server is present on the
network.</warning>

<Rule id="ldap_client_start_tls">
<title>Configure LDAP to Use TLS For All Transactions</title>
<description>Configure LDAP to enforce TLS use. First, edit the file 
<tt>/etc/pam_ldap.conf</tt>, and add or correct the following lines:
<pre>ssl start_tls</pre>
Then review the LDAP server and ensure TLS has been configured.
</description>
<ocil clause="no lines are returned">
To ensure LDAP is configured to use TLS for all transactions, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep start_tls /etc/pam_ldap.conf</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>The ssl directive specifies whether to use ssl or not. If
not specified it will default to no. It should be set to start_tls rather
than doing LDAP over SSL.</rationale>
<ref disa="776,778,1453" />
<ident cce="14894-0" />
<oval id="ldap_client_start_tls" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ldap_client_tls_cacertpath">
<title>Configure Certificate Directives for LDAP Use of TLS</title>
<description>Ensure a copy of the site's CA certificate has been placed in
the file <tt>/etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</tt>. Configure LDAP to enforce TLS 
use and to trust certificates signed by the site's CA. First, edit the file 
<tt>/etc/pam_ldap.conf</tt>, and add or correct either of the following lines:
<pre>tls_cacertdir /etc/pki/tls/CA</pre>
or
<pre>tls_cacertfile /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</pre>
Then review the LDAP server and ensure TLS has been configured.
</description>
<ocil clause="there is no output, or the lines are commented out">
To ensure TLS is configured with trust certificates, run the following command:
<pre># grep cert /etc/pam_ldap.conf</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>The tls_cacertdir or tls_cacertfile directives are required when
tls_cheekpeer is configured (which is the default for openldap versions 2.1 and
up). These directives define the path to the trust certificates signed by the
site CA.</rationale>
<ref disa="776,778,1453" />
<ident cce="14894-0" />
<oval id="ldap_client_tls_cacertpath" />
</Rule>

</Group><!--End <Group id="openldap_client"> -->

<Group id="openldap_server">
<title>Configure OpenLDAP Server</title>
<description>This section contains guidance on how to configure an
OpenLDAP server to securely provide information for use in a
centralized authentication service. This is not a comprehensive
guide to maintaining an OpenLDAP server, but may be helpful in
securing an OpenLDAP infrastructure nonetheless.
</description>

<Rule id="package_openldap-servers_removed">
<title>Uninstall openldap-servers Package</title>
<description>The <tt>openldap-servers</tt> package should be removed if not in use.
Is this machine the OpenLDAP server? If not, remove the package:
<pre># yum erase openldap-servers</pre>
The openldap-servers RPM is not installed by default on RHEL6
machines. It is needed only by the OpenLDAP server, not by the
clients which use LDAP for authentication. If the system is not
intended for use as an LDAP Server it should be removed.
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not">
To verify the <tt>openldap-servers</tt> package is not installed, 
run the following command:
<pre>$ rpm -q openldap-servers</pre>
The output should show:
<pre>package openldap-servers is not installed</pre>
</ocil>
<ident cce="3501-4" />
<oval id="package_openldap-servers_removed" />
<ref nist="CM-6, CM-7" disa="366"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="ldap_server_config_olcsuffix">
<title>Configure Domain-Specific Parameters</title>
<description>The <tt>ldap</tt> server should be configured to use a domain specific suffix.
Is this system an OpenLDAP server? If so,
edit the ldap configuration file at
<tt>/etc/openldap/slapd.d/cn=config/olcDatabase={*}bdb.ldif</tt>
to include suffix information relevant to your domain.
<pre>olcSuffix: "dc=example,dc=com "
olcRootDN: "cn=Manager,dc=example,dc=com "</pre>
where dc=example,dc=com is the same root you will use on the LDAP clients.
<br />
These are basic LDAP configuration directives. The suffix parameter gives the root name of all information served by this LDAP server, and should be some name related to your domain. The rootdn parameter names LDAP's privileged user, who is allowed to read or write all data managed by this LDAP server.
</description>
<ident cce="3501-4" />
<oval id="ldap_server_config_olcsuffix" />
<ref nist="AC-2, CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ldap_server_config_bdb_file_security">
<title>LDAP Configuration File Security</title>
<description>Is this system an OpenLDAP server? If so,
ensure that the configuration files are protected from unauthorized
access or modification.
<br /><br />
Edit the ldap configuration file at <tt>/etc/openldap/slapd.d/cn=config/olcDatabase={*}bdb.ldif</tt>.
Ensure that the configuration file has reasonable permissions:
<pre># chown root:ldap /etc/openldap/slapd.d/cn=config/olcDatabase={*}bdb.ldif
# chmod 640 /etc/openldap/slapd.d/cn=config/olcDatabase={*}bdb.ldif</pre>
Protect configuration files containing the hashed password the same way you would protect other files, such as
<tt>/etc/shadow</tt>, which contain hashed authentication data.
</description>
<!--<ident cce="TODO:CCE" />-->
<oval id="ldap_server_config_bdb_file_security" />
<ref nist="AC-6, CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ldap_server_config_olcrootpw">
<title>Configure LDAP Root Password</title>
<description>Is this system an OpenLDAP server? If so,
ensure that the RootDN uses a secure password.
<br /><br />
Generate a hashed password using the slappasswd utility:
<pre># slappasswd
New password:
Re-enter new password:</pre>
This will output a hashed password string.
<br /><br />
Edit the file <tt>/etc/openldap/slapd.d/cn=config/olcDatabase={*}bdb.ldif</tt>, and add or correct
the line:
<pre>olcRootPW: {SSHA}hashed-password-string</pre>
Be sure to select a secure password for the LDAP root user, since this user has permission to read and write all
LDAP data, so a compromise of the LDAP root password will probably enable a full compromise of your site.
In addition, be sure to use a reasonably strong hash function. The default hash function should be used. The default hash function is a salted SHA-1 algorith which is FIPS 160-1 compliant. Insecure schemes such as crypt should not be used.
</description>
<!--<ident cce="TODO:CCE" />-->
<oval id="ldap_server_config_olcrootpw" />
<ref nist="AC-2, IA-2" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ldap_server_config_certificate_files">
<title>Protect LDAP Certificate Files</title>
<description>Create the PKI directory for LDAP certificates if it does not already exist:
<pre># mkdir /etc/pki/tls/ldap
# chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/ldap
# chmod 755 /etc/pki/tls/ldap</pre>
Using removable media or some other secure transmission format, install the files generated in the previous
step onto the LDAP server:
<ul>
<li><tt>/etc/pki/tls/ldap/serverkey.pem</tt>: the private key <tt>ldapserverkey.pem</tt></li>
<li><tt>/etc/pki/tls/ldap/servercert.pem</tt>: the certificate file <tt>ldapservercert.pem</tt></li>
</ul>
Verify the ownership and permissions of these files:
<pre># chown root:ldap /etc/pki/tls/ldap/serverkey.pem
# chown root:ldap /etc/pki/tls/ldap/servercert.pem
# chmod 640 /etc/pki/tls/ldap/serverkey.pem
# chmod 640 /etc/pki/tls/ldap/servercert.pem</pre>
Verify that the CA's public certificate file has been installed as <tt>/etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</tt>, and has the
correct permissions:
<pre># mkdir /etc/pki/tls/CA
# chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem
# chmod 644 /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</pre>
As a result of these steps, the LDAP server will have access to its own private certificate and the key with which
that certificate is encrypted, and to the public certificate file belonging to the CA. Note that it would be possible
for the key to be protected further, so that processes running as ldap could not read it. If this were done, the
LDAP server process would need to be restarted manually whenever the server rebooted.
</description>
<ident cce="4360-4" />
<ident cce="4378-6" />
<ident cce="4492-5" />
<ident cce="4263-0" />
<ident cce="3502-2" />
<ident cce="4449-5" />
<ident cce="4361-2" />
<ident cce="4427-1" />
<ident cce="4321-6" />
<ident cce="4339-8" />
<ident cce="4105-3" />
<ident cce="3718-4" />
<oval id="ldap_server_config_certificate_files" />
<ref nist="AC-6, CM-7, SC-11, SC-12, SC-13, SC-17" />
</Rule>

<Group id="ldap_server_config_directory_domain">
<title>Create Top-level LDAP Structure for Domain</title>
<description>Create a structure for the domain itself with at least the following attributes:
<pre>dn: dc=example,dc=com
objectClass: dcObject
objectClass: organization
dc: example
o: Organization Description</pre>
This is a placeholder for the root of the domain's LDAP tree. Without this entry, LDAP will not be able to find
any other entries for the domain.
</description>
<!--<ident cce="TODO:CCE" />-->
<!--oval id="MANUAL AUDIT" /-->
<ref nist="AC-2" />
</Group>

<Group id="ldap_server_config_directory_users_groups">
<title>Create LDAP Structures for Users and Groups</title>
<description>Create LDAP structures for people (users) and for groups with at least the following attributes:
<pre>dn: ou=people,dc=example,dc=com
ou: people
structuralObjectClass: organizationalUnit
objectClass: organizationalUnit
dn: ou=groups,dc=example,dc=com
ou: groups
structuralObjectClass: organizationalUnit
objectClass: organizationalUnit</pre>
Posix users and groups are the two top-level items which will be needed in order to use LDAP for authentication.
These organizational units are used to identify the two categories within LDAP.
</description>
<!--<ident cce="TODO:CCE" />-->
<!--oval id="MANUAL AUDIT" /-->
<ref nist="AC-2, AC-6, SC-2" />
</Group>

<Group id="ldap_server_config_directory_accounts">
<title>Create Unix Accounts</title>
<description>For each Unix user, create an LDAP entry with at least the following attributes (others may be appropriate
for your site as well), using variable values appropriate to that user.
<pre>dn: uid=username ,ou=people,dc=example,dc=com
structuralObjectClass: inetOrgPerson
objectClass: inetOrgPerson
objectClass: posixAccount
objectClass: shadowAccount
cn: fullname
sn: surname
gecos: fullname
gidNumber: primary-group-id
homeDirectory: /home/username
loginShell: /path/to/shell
uid: username
uidNumber: uid
userPassword: {MD5}md5-hashed-password
shadowMax: N</pre>
In general, the LDAP schemas for users use uid to refer to the text username, and uidNumber for the numeric
UID. This usage may be slightly confusing when compared to the standard Unix usage.
You should not create entries for the root account or for system accounts which are unique to individual systems,
but only for user accounts which are to be shared across machines, and which have authentication information
(such as a password) associated with them.
</description>
<!--<ident cce="TODO:CCE" />-->
<!--oval id="MANUAL AUDIT" /-->
<ref nist="AC-2, CM-7, SC-2" />
</Group>

<Group id="ldap_server_config_directory_groups">
<title>Create Unix Groups</title>
<description>For each Unix group, create an LDAP entry with at least the following attributes:
<pre>dn: cn=groupname ,ou=groups,dc=example,dc=com
cn: groupname
structuralObjectClass: posixGroup
objectClass: posixGroup
gidNumber: gid
memberUid: username1
memberUid: username2
...
memberUid: usernameN</pre>
Note that each user has a primary group, identified by the gidNumber field in the user's account entry. That
group must be created, but it is not necessary to list the user as a memberUid of the group. This behavior should
be familiar to administrators, since it is identical to the handling of the /etc/passwd and /etc/group files.
Do not create entries for the root group or for system groups, but only for groups which contain human users
or which are shared across systems.
</description>
<!--<ident cce="TODO:CCE" />-->
<!--oval id="MANUAL AUDIT" /-->
<ref nist="AC-2, CM-7, SC-2" />
</Group>

<Group id="ldap_server_config_directory_admin_group">
<title>Create Groups to Administer LDAP</title>
<description>If a group of LDAP administrators is desired, that group must be created somewhat differently.
The specification should have these attributes:
<pre>dn: cn=admins ,ou=groups,dc=example,dc=com
cn: admins
structuralObjectClass: groupOfUniqueNames
objectClass: groupOfUniqueNames
uniqueMember: cn=Manager,dc=example,dc=com
uniqueMember: uid=admin1-username ,ou=people,dc=example,dc=com
uniqueMember: uid=admin2-username ,ou=people,dc=example,dc=com
...
uniqueMember: uid=adminN-username ,ou=people,dc=example,dc=com</pre>
LDAP cannot use Posix groups for its own internal authentication - it needs to compare the username specified
in an authenticated bind to some internal groupOfUniqueNames. If you do not specify an LDAP administrators'
group, then all LDAP management will need to be done using the LDAP root user (Manager). For reasons of
auditing and error detection, it is recommended that LDAP administrators have unique identities.
</description>
<!--<ident cce="TODO:CCE" />-->
<!--oval id="MANUAL AUDIT" /-->
<ref nist="AC-2, CM-7, SC-2" />
</Group>

<Rule id="ldap_server_config_olcaccess">
<title>Configure slapd to Protect Authentication Information</title>
<description>Use ldapmodify to add these entries to the database. Add or correct the following access specifications:
1. Protect the user's password by allowing the user himself or the LDAP administrators to change it,
allowing the anonymous user to authenticate against it, and allowing no other access:
<pre>olcAccess: to attrs=userPassword
    by self write
    by group/groupOfUniqueNames/uniqueMember="cn=admins ,ou=groups,dc=example,dc=com " write
    by anonymous auth
    by * none
olcAccess: to attrs=shadowLastChange
    by self write
    by group/groupOfUniqueNames/uniqueMember="cn=admins ,ou=groups,dc=example,dc=com " write
    by * read</pre>
2. Allow anyone to read other information, and allow the administrators to change it:
<pre>olcAccess: to *
    by group/groupOfUniqueNames/uniqueMember="cn=admins ,ou=groups,dc=example,dc=com " write
    by * read</pre>
Access rules are applied in the order encountered, so more specific rules should appear first. In particular,
the rule restricting access to userPassword must appear before the rule allowing access to all data. The
shadowLastChange attribute is a timestamp, and is only critical if your site implements password expiration. If
your site does not have an LDAP administrators group, the LDAP root user (called Manager in this guide) will
be able to change data without an explicit access statement.
</description>
<!--<ident cce="TODO:CCE" />-->
<oval id="ldap_server_config_olcaccess" />	
<ref nist="AC-2, AC-4, AC-6, CM-7, SC-2" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ldap_server_config_directory_file_security">
<title>Correct Permissions on LDAP Server Files</title>
<description>Correct the permissions on the ldap server's files:
<pre># chown ldap:root /var/lib/ldap/*</pre>
Some manual methods of inserting information into the LDAP database may leave these files with incorrect
permissions. This will prevent slapd from starting correctly.
</description>
<ident cce="4484-2" />
<ident cce="4502-1" />
<oval id="ldap_server_config_directory_file_security" />
<ref nist="AC-6, CM-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="iptables_ldap_enabled">
<title>Configure iptables to Allow Access to the LDAP Server</title>
<description>Determine an appropriate network block representing the machines on
your network which will synchronize to this server.
<iptables-desc-macro net="true" proto="tcp" port="389" />
<iptables-desc-macro net="true" proto="tcp" port="636" />
The default Iptables configuration does not allow inbound access to any 
services. These modifications allow access to the LDAP primary (389) and 
encrypted-only (636) ports, while keeping all other ports on the server in 
their default protected state.
Note: Even if the LDAP server restricts connections so that only encrypted 
queries are allowed, it will probably be necessary to allow traffic to the 
default port 389. This is true because many LDAP clients implement encryption 
by connecting to the primary port and issuing the STARTTLS command.
</description>
<!--<ident cce="TODO:CCE" />-->
<oval id="iptables_ldap_enabled" />
<ref nist="AC-4, CM-7, SC-2, SC-5, SC-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="ldap_server_config_logging">
<title>Configure Logging for LDAP</title>
<description>
<ol>
<li>Edit the file <tt>/etc/rsyslog.conf</tt>. Add or correct the following line:
<pre>local4.*</pre>
</li>
<li>Create the log file with safe permissions:
<pre># touch /var/log/ldap.log
# chown root:root /var/log/ldap.log
# chmod 0600 /var/log/ldap.log</pre>
</li>
<li>Edit the file /etc/logrotate.d/syslog and add the pathname
<pre>/var/log/ldap.log</pre>
to the space-separated list in the first line.</li>
<li>Edit the LDAP configuration file /etc/openldap/slapd.conf and set a reasonable set of default log
parameters, such as:
<pre>loglevel stats2</pre>
</li>
</ol>

OpenLDAP sends its log data to the syslog facility local4 at priority debug. By default, RHEL5 does not store
this facility at all. The syslog configuration suggested here will store any output logged by slapd in the file
<tt>/var/log/ldap.log</tt>, and will include that file in the standard log rotation for syslog files.
By default, LDAP's logging is quite verbose. The loglevel parameter is a space-separated list of items to be
logged. Specifying <tt>stats2</tt> will reduce the log output somewhat, but this level will still produce some logging
every time an LDAP query is made. (This may be appropriate, depending on your site's auditing requirements.)
In order to capture only <tt>slapd</tt> startup messages, specify <tt>loglevel none</tt>.
See <tt>slapd.conf(5)</tt> for detailed information about the loglevel parameter.
</description>
<!--<ident cce="TODO:CCE" />-->
<oval id="ldap_server_config_logging" />
<ref nist="AC-6, AU-2, AU-3, AU-9" />
</Rule>

</Group><!--End <Group id="openldap_server"> -->
</Group><!--End <Group id="ldap"> -->
