<Group id="mail">
<title>Mail Server Software</title>
<description>
Mail servers are used to send and receive email over the network.
Mail is a very common service, and Mail Transfer Agents (MTAs) are obvious
targets of network attack.
Ensure that machines are not running MTAs unnecessarily,
and configure needed MTAs as defensively as possible.
<br /><br />
Very few systems at any site should be configured to directly receive email over the
network. Users should instead use mail clients programs to retrieve email
from a central server that support protocols such as IMAP or POP3.
However, it is normal for most systems to be independently capable of sending email,
for instance so that cron jobs can report output to an administrator.
Most MTAs, including Postfix, support a submission-only mode in which mail can be sent from
the local system to a central site MTA (or directly delivered to a local account),
but the system still cannot receive mail directly over a network.
<br /><br />
The <tt>alternatives</tt> program in RHEL permits selection of other mail server software
(such as Sendmail), but Postfix is the default and is preferred.
Postfix was coded with security in mind and can also be more effectively contained by
SELinux as its modular design has resulted in separate processes performing specific actions.
More information is available on its website, http://www.postfix.org.</description>

<Rule id="service_postfix_enabled">
<title>Enable Postfix (postfix)</title>
<description>The Postfix mail transfer agent is used for local mail delivery within
the system. The default configuration only listens for connections to the default SMTP
port (port 25) on the loopback interface (127.0.0.1). 
It is recommended to leave this
service enabled for local mail delivery.
<service-enable-macro service="postfix" />
</description>
<rationale>Local mail delivery is essential to some system maintenance and
notification tasks.
</rationale>
<ident cce="14068-1" />
<oval id="service_postfix_enabled" />
<ref nist="CM-6" />
</Rule>

<Group id="postfix_client">
<title>Configure SMTP For Mail Clients</title>
<description>This section discusses settings for Postfix in a submission-only e-mail configuration.</description>

<!-- postfix is installed by default on RHEL 6,
but sendmail was the default on RHEL 5. -->

<!-- <Rule id="postfix_package_installation">
<title>The postfix package should be installed</title>
<description>If this machine does not need to operate as a mail server, follow the remaining
instructions in this section to ensure this software run only in a submission-only mode.
MTA software must still be installed in order to ensure local mail delivery for services
such as cron.

If the machine must operate as a mail server, follow the remaining instructions in this section for
 strategies for MTA configuration. Then apply both the MTA-independent operating system
configuration guidance, and the specific guidance for your MTA in this section.
</description>
<ident cce="14068-1" />
<oval id="package_postfix_installed" />
</Rule>
-->

<Rule id="postfix_network_listening">
<title>Disable Postfix Network Listening</title>
<description>
Edit the file <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt> to ensure that only the following
<tt>inet_interfaces</tt> line appears:
<pre>inet_interfaces = localhost</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not">
Run the following command to ensure postfix accepts mail messages from only the local system:
<pre>$ grep inet_interfaces /etc/postfix/main.cf</pre>
If properly configured, the output should show only <tt>localhost</tt>.
</ocil>
<rationale>
This ensures that <tt>postfix</tt> accepts mail messages
(such as cron job reports) from the local system only,
and not from the network, which protects it from network attack.
</rationale>
<ident cce="15018-5" />
<oval id="postfix_network_listening_disabled" />
<ref nist="CM-7" disa="382"/>
</Rule>

</Group><!--End <Group id="postfix_client"> -->

<Group id="postfix_harden_os">
<title>Configure Operating System to Protect Mail Server
</title>
<description>The guidance in this section is appropriate for any host which is operating as a site MTA, whether the mail server runs using Sendmail, Postfix, or some other software.
</description>

<Group id="postfix_seperate_internal_external">
<title>Use Separate Hosts for External and Internal Mail if Possible</title>
<description>The mail server is a frequent target of network attack from the outside. However, since all site users receive mail,
the mail server must be open to some connection from each inside users. It is strongly recommended that these
functions be separated, by having an externally visible mail server which processes all incoming and outgoing
mail, then forwards internal mail to a separate machine from which users can access it.
</description>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<ref nist="CM-7, SC-5, SC-7" />
</Group>

<Group id="postfix_restrict_user_access">
<title>Protect the MTA Host from User Access</title>
<description>The mail server contains privileged data belonging to all users and performs a
vital network function. Preventing users from logging into this server is a precaution against
privilege escalation or denial of service attacks which might compromise the mail service. Take
steps to ensure that only system administrators are allowed shell access to the MTA host.
</description>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<ref nist="AC-6, SC-2" />
</Group>

<Group id="postfix_restrict_mail_spool_access">
<title>Restrict Remote Access to the Mail Spool</title>
<description>The mail server contains privileged data belonging to all users and performs a vital
network function. Preventing users from logging into this server is a precaution against privilege
escalation or denial of service attacks which might compromise the mail service. Take steps to
ensure that only system administrators are allowed shell access to the MTA host.
</description>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<ref nist="AC-2, AC-4, CM-7, SC-2" />
</Group>

<Rule id="iptables_smtp_enabled">
<title>Configure iptables to Allow Access to the Mail Server</title>
<description>
<iptables-desc-macro proto="tcp" port="25" />
</description>
<rationale>The default Iptables configuration does not allow inbound access to the SMTP service. This modification allows
that access, while keeping other ports on the server in their default protected state.
</rationale>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<oval id="iptables_smtp_enabled" />
<ref nist="AC-4, CM-7, SC-7" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="postfix_logging">
<title>Verify System Logging and Log Permissions for Mail</title>
<description>Edit the file <tt>/etc/rsyslog.conf</tt>. Add or correct the following line if necessary (this is the default):
<pre>mail.*					-/var/log/maillog</pre>
Run the following commands to ensure correct permissions on the mail log:
<pre># chown root:root /var/log/maillog
# chmod 600 /var/log/maillog</pre>
Ensure log will be rotated as appropriate by adding or correcting the following line if needed into the list on the first line of <tt>/etc/logrotate.d/syslog</tt> (this is the default):
<pre>/var/log/maillog</pre>
</description>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<oval id="postfix_logging" />
<ref nist="AC-6, AU-2, AU-9" />
</Rule>

<Group id="postfix_configure_ssl_certs">
<title>Configure SSL Certificates for Use with SMTP AUTH</title>
<description>If SMTP AUTH is to be used, the use of SSL to protect credentials in transit is strongly recommended.
There are also configurations for which it may be desirable to encrypt all mail in transit from one MTA to another,
though such configurations are beyond the scope of this guide. In either event, the steps for creating and installing
an SSL certificate are independent of the MTA in use, and are described here.
</description>

<Group id="postfix_create_cert">
<title>Create an SSL Certificate</title>
<description>
Change into the CA certificate directory:
<pre># cd /etc/pki/tls/certs</pre>
Generate a key pair for the mail server:
<pre># openssl genrsa -out mailserverkey.pem 2048</pre>
Next, generate a certificate signing request (CSR) for the CA to sign, making sure to supply your mail
server's fully qualified domain name as the Common Name:
<pre># openssl req -new -key mailserverkey.pem -out mailserver.csr</pre>
Next, the mail server CSR must be signed to create the mail server certificate. You can either send the CSR
to an established CA or sign it with your CA.
To sign mailserver.csr using your CA:
<pre># openssl ca -in mailserver.csr -out mailservercert.pem</pre>
</description>
<rationale>This step creates a private key, <tt>mailserverkey.pem</tt>, and a public certificate, <tt>mailservercert.pem</tt>.
The mail server will use these to prove its identity by demonstrating that it has a certificate which has been signed by a
CA. Mail clients at your site should be willing to send their mail only to a server they can authenticate.
</rationale>
<warning category="general">Note: This step must be performed on your CA system, not on the MTA host itself. If you will have a commercial
CA sign certificates, then this step should be performed on a separate, physically secure system devoted to that
purpose.</warning>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<ref nist="CM-7, SC-12" />
</Group>

<Rule id="postfix_install_ssl_cert">
<title>Install the SSL Certificate</title>
<description>Create the PKI directory for mail certificates, if it does not already exist:
<pre># mkdir /etc/pki/tls/mail
# chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/mail
# chmod 755 /etc/pki/tls/mail</pre>
Using removable media or some other secure transmission format, install the files generated in the previous
step onto the mail server:
<pre>/etc/pki/tls/mail/serverkey.pem: the private key mailserverkey.pem
/etc/pki/tls/mail/servercert.pem: the certificate file mailservercert.pem</pre>
Verify the ownership and permissions of these files:
<pre># chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/mail/serverkey.pem
# chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/mail/servercert.pem
# chmod 600 /etc/pki/tls/mail/serverkey.pem
# chmod 644 /etc/pki/tls/mail/servercert.pem</pre>
Verify that the CA's public certificate file has been installed as <tt>/etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</tt>, and has the
correct permissions:
<pre># chown root:root /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem
# chmod 644 /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem</pre>
</description>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<oval id="postfix_certificate_files" />
<ref nist="AC-6, SC-12, SC-13" />
</Rule>

</Group><!--End <Group id="postfix_configure_ssl_certs"> -->
</Group><!--End <Group id="postfix_harden_os"> -->

<Group id="postfix_server_configuration">
<title>Configure Postfix if Necessary</title>
<description>Postfix stores its configuration files in the directory /etc/postfix by default. The primary configuration file is
/etc/postfix/main.cf. Other files will be introduced as needed.
</description>

<Rule id="postfix_server_denial_of_service">
<title>Limit Denial of Service Attacks</title>
<description>Edit <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt>. Add or correct the following lines:
<pre>default_process_limit = 100
smtpd_client_connection_count_limit = 10
smtpd_client_connection_rate_limit = 30
queue_minfree = 20971520
header_size_limit = 51200
message_size_limit = 10485760
smtpd_recipient_limit = 100</pre>
</description>
<rationale>These configuration options serve to make it more difficult for attackers to consume resources on the MTA host.
The <tt>default_process_limit</tt> parameter controls how many <tt>smtpd</tt> processes can exist at a time, while
<tt>smtpd_client_connection_count_limit</tt> controls the number of those which can be occupied by any one
remote sender, and <tt>smtpd_client_connection_rate_limit</tt> controls the number of connections any one client
can make per minute. By default, local hosts (those in <tt>mynetworks</tt>) are exempted from per-client rate limiting.
The <tt>queue_minfree</tt> parameter establishes a free space threshold, in order to stop e-mail receipt before the
queue filesystem is entirely full. The <tt>header_size_limit</tt>, <tt>message_size_limit</tt>, and <tt>smtpd_recipient_limit</tt>
parameters place bounds on the legal sizes of messages received via SMTP.
</rationale>
<warning category="general">Note: The values given here are examples, and may need to be modified for any particular site. By default, the
Postfix anvil process gathers mail receipt statistics. To get information about about what connection rates are
typical at your site, look in <tt>/var/log/maillog</tt> for lines with the daemon name postfix/anvil.
</warning>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<oval id="postfix_server_denial_of_service" />
<ref nist="SC-5" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="postfix_server_banner">
<title>Configure SMTP Greeting Banner</title>
<description>Edit <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt>, and add or correct the following line, substituting some other wording for the
banner information if you prefer:
<pre>smtpd_banner = $myhostname ESMTP</pre>
</description>
<rationale>The default greeting banner discloses that the listening mail process is Postfix.
When remote mail senders connect to the MTA on port 25, they are greeted by an initial banner as part of
the SMTP dialogue. This banner is necessary, but it frequently gives away too much information, including
the MTA software which is in use, and sometimes also its version number. Remote mail senders do not need
this information in order to send mail, so the banner should be changed to reveal only the hostname (which is
already known and may be useful) and the word ESMTP, to indicate that the modern SMTP protocol variant is
supported.
</rationale>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<oval id="postfix_server_banner" />
<ref nist="AC-22, AU-13" />
</Rule>

<Group id="postfix_server_mail_relay">
<title>Control Mail Relaying</title>
<description>Postfix's mail relay controls are implemented with the help of the smtpd recipient restrictions option, which
controls the restrictions placed on the SMTP dialogue once the sender and recipient envelope addresses are known.
The guidance in the following sections should be applied to all machines. If there are machines which
must be allowed to relay mail, but which cannot be trusted to relay unconditionally, configure SMTP AUTH
with SSL support.
</description>

<Rule id="postfix_server_mail_relay_set_trusted_networks">
<title>Configure Trusted Networks and Hosts</title>
<description>Edit <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt>, and configure the contents of the mynetworks variable in one of the following
ways:
<ul>
<li>If any machine in the subnet containing the MTA may be trusted to relay messages, add or correct the line:
<pre>mynetworks_style = subnet</pre></li>
<li>If only the MTA host itself is trusted to relay messages, add or correct:
<pre>mynetworks_style = host</pre></li>
<li>If the set of machines which can relay is more complicated, manually specify an entry for each netblock
or IP address which is trusted to relay by setting the mynetworks variable directly:
<pre>mynetworks = 10.0.0.0/16 , 192.168.1.0/24 , 127.0.0.1</pre></li>
</ul>
</description>
<rationale>The <tt>mynetworks</tt> variable must contain only the set of machines for which this MTA should unconditionally
relay mail. This is a trust relationship - if spammers gain access to these machines, your site will effectively
become an open relay. It is recommended that only machines which are managed by you or by another trusted
organization be placed in mynetworks, and users of all other machines be required to use SMTP AUTH to send
mail.
</rationale>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<oval id="postfix_server_mail_relay_set_trusted_networks" />
<ref nist="IA-8, SI-8" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="postfix_server_mail_relay_for_trusted_networks">
<title>Allow Unlimited Relaying for Trusted Networks Only</title>
<description>Edit <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt>, and add or correct the <tt>smtpd_recipient_restrictions</tt> definition so that it
contains at least:
<pre>smtpd_recipient_restrictions =
    ...
    permit_mynetworks,
    reject_unauth_destination,
    ...</pre>
</description>
<rationale>The full contents of <tt>smtpd_recipient_restrictions</tt> will vary by site, since this is a common place
to put spam restrictions and other site-specific options. The <tt>permit_mynetworks</tt> option allows all mail to be
relayed from the machines in <tt>mynetworks</tt>. Then, the <tt>reject_unauth_destination</tt> option denies all mail
whose destination address is not local, preventing any other machines from relaying. These two options should always appear in
this order, and should usually follow one another immediately unless SMTP AUTH is used.
</rationale>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<oval id="postfix_server_mail_relay_for_trusted_networks" />
<ref nist="SI-8" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="postfix_server_mail_relay_smtp_auth_for_untrusted_networks">
<title>Require SMTP AUTH Before Relaying from Untrusted Clients</title>
<description>SMTP authentication allows remote clients to relay mail safely by requiring them to authenticate before submit-
ting mail. Postfix's SMTP AUTH uses an authentication library called SASL, which is not part of Postfix itself.
This section describes how to configure authentication using the Cyrus-SASL implementation. See below for a
discussion of other options.
<br /><br />
To enable the use of SASL authentication, edit <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt> and add or correct the following
settings:
<pre>smtpd_sasl_auth_enable = yes
smtpd_recipient_restrictions =
    ...
    permit_mynetworks,
    permit_sasl_authenticated,
    reject_unauth_destination,
    ...</pre>
Then edit <tt>/usr/lib/sasl2/smtpd.conf</tt> and add or correct the following line with the correct authentication
mechanism for SASL to use:
<pre>pwcheck_method: saslauthd</pre>
<service-enable-macro service="saslauthd" />
</description>
<rationale>Postfix can use either the Cyrus library or Dovecot as a source for SASL authentication. If this host is running
Dovecot for some other reason, it is recommended that Dovecot's SASL support be used instead of running the
Cyrus code as well. See http://www.postfix.org/SASL_README.html for instructions on implementing that
configuration, which is not described in this guide.
<br /><br />
In Postfix's configuration, the directive <tt>smtpd_sasl_auth_enable</tt> tells <tt>smtpd</tt> to allow the use of the SMTP AUTH
command during the SMTP dialogue, and to support that command by getting authentication information from
SASL. The <tt>smtpd_recipient_restrictions</tt> directive is changed so that, if the client is not connecting from a
trusted address, it is allowed to attempt authentication (<tt>permit_sasl_authenticated</tt>) in order to relay mail.
The file <tt>/usr/lib/sasl2/smtpd.conf</tt> is the Cyrus-SASL configuration file. The <tt>pwcheck_method</tt> directive tells
SASL how to find passwords. The simplest method, described above, is to run a separate authentication daemon,
<tt>saslauthd</tt>, which is able to communicate with the system authentication system. On RHEL6, <tt>saslauthd</tt> uses
PAM by default, which should work in most cases. If you have a centralized authentication system which does not
work via PAM, look at the <tt>saslauthd(8)</tt> manpage to find out how to configure <tt>saslauthd</tt> for your environment.
</rationale>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<oval id="postfix_server_mail_relay_smtp_auth_for_untrusted_networks" />
<ref nist="IA-8, SI-8" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="postfix_server_mail_relay_require_tls_for_smtp_auth">
<title>Require TLS for SMTP AUTH</title>
<description>Edit <tt>/etc/postfix/main.cf</tt>, and add or correct the following lines:
<pre>smtpd_tls_CApath = /etc/pki/tls/CA
smtpd_tls_CAfile = /etc/pki/tls/CA/cacert.pem
smtpd_tls_cert_file = /etc/pki/tls/mail/servercert.pem
smtpd_tls_key_file = /etc/pki/tls/mail/serverkey.pem
smtpd_tls_security_level = may
smtpd_tls_auth_only = yes</pre>
</description>
<rationale>These options tell Postfix to protect all SMTP AUTH transactions using TLS. The first four options describe
the locations of the necessary TLS key files.
The <tt>smtpd_tls_security_level</tt> directive tells <tt>smtpd</tt> to allow the STARTTLS command during the SMTP protocol
exchange, but not to require it for mail senders. (Unless your site receives mail only from other trusted sites
whose sysadmins can be asked to maintain a copy of your site certificate, you do not want to require TLS for all
SMTP exchanges.)
The <tt>smtpd_tls_auth_only</tt> directive tells <tt>smtpd</tt> to require the STARTTLS command before allowing the client to
attempt to authenticate for relaying using SMTP AUTH. It may not be possible to use this directive if you must
allow relaying from non-TLS-capable client software. If this is the case, simply omit that line.
</rationale>
<!-- <ident cce="TODO:CCE" /> -->
<oval id="postfix_server_mail_relay_require_tls_for_smtp_auth" />
<ref nist="IA-8, SC-13" />
</Rule>

</Group><!--End <Group id="postfix_server_mail_relay"> -->
</Group><!--End <Group id="postfix_server_configuration"> -->
</Group><!--End <Group id="mail"> -->
