<Group id="smb">
<title>Samba(SMB) Microsoft Windows File Sharing Server</title>
<description>When properly configured, the Samba service allows
Linux systems to provide file and print sharing to Microsoft
Windows systems. There are two software packages that provide
Samba support. The first, <tt>samba-client</tt>, provides a series of
command line tools that enable a client system to access Samba
shares. The second, simply labeled <tt>samba</tt>, provides the Samba
service. It is this second package that allows a Linux system to
act as an Active Directory server, a domain controller, or as a
domain member. Only the <tt>samba-client</tt> package is installed by
default.</description>

<Group id="disabling_samba">
<title>Disable Samba if Possible</title>
<description>
Even after the Samba server package has been installed, it
will remain disabled. Do not enable this service unless it is
absolutely necessary to provide Microsoft Windows file and print
sharing functionality.
</description>

<Rule id="service_smb_disabled">
<title>Disable Samba</title>
<description>
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="smb" />
</description>
<ocil>
<service-check-macro enable="false" service="smb" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
Running a Samba server provides a network-based avenue of attack, and
should be disabled if not needed.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27143-7" />
<oval id="service_smb_disabled" />
<ref disa="1436" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="package_samba_removed">
<title>Uninstall samba Package</title>
<description>
<yum-macro install="false" package="samba" />
</description>
<ocil>
<package-check-macro package="samba" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
If there is no need to mount directories and file systems to
Windows systems, then this service can be deleted to reduce 
the potential attack surface.
</rationale>
<ident cce="CCE-27102-3" />
<oval id="package_samba_removed" />
</Rule>
</Group> <!--<Group id="disabling_samba">-->

<Group id="configuring_samba">
<title>Configure Samba if Necessary</title>
<description>All settings for the Samba daemon can be found in
<tt>/etc/samba/smb.conf</tt>. Settings are divided between a
<tt>[global]</tt> configuration section and a series of user
created share definition sections meant to describe file or print
shares on the system. By default, Samba will operate in user mode
and allow client systems to access local home directories and
printers. It is recommended that these settings be changed or that
additional limitations be set in place.</description>

<Rule id="package_samba-common_installed" severity="medium">
<title>Install the Samba Common Package</title>
<description>
The <tt>samba-common</tt> package should be installed.
<yum-macro install="true" package="samba-common"/>
</description>
<ocil clause="the package is not installed" >
<package-check-macro install="true" package="samba-common" />
</ocil>
<rationale>
If the samba-common package is not installed, samba cannot be configured.
</rationale>
<ident cce="RHEL6-CCE-TBD" />
<oval id="package_samba-common_installed" />
</Rule>

<Group id="smb_restrict_file_sharing">
<title>Restrict SMB File Sharing to Configured Networks</title>
<description>Only users with local user accounts will be able to log in to
Samba shares by default. Shares can be limited to particular users or network
addresses. Use the <tt>hosts allow</tt> and <tt>hosts deny</tt> directives
accordingly, and consider setting the valid users directive to a limited subset
of users or to a group of users. Separate each address, user, or user group
with a space as follows for a particular <i>share</i> or global:
<pre>[<i>share</i>]
  hosts allow = 192.168.1. 127.0.0.1
  valid users = userone usertwo @usergroup</pre>
It is also possible to limit read and write access to particular users with the
read list and write list options, though the permissions set by the system
itself will override these settings. Set the read only attribute for each share
to ensure that global settings will not accidentally override the individual
share settings. Then, as with the valid users directive, separate each user or
group of users with a space:
<pre>[<i>share</i>]
  read only = yes
  write list = userone usertwo @usergroup</pre>
</description>
<rationale>The Samba service is only required for sharing files and printers
with Microsoft Windows workstations, and even then, other options may exist. 
</rationale>
</Group>

<Rule id="smb_server_disable_root">
<title>Disable Root Access to SMB Shares</title>
<description>Administrators should not use administrator accounts to access
Samba file and printer shares. Disable the root user and the wheel
administrator group:
<pre>[<i>share</i>]
  invalid users = root @wheel</pre>
If administrator accounts cannot be disabled, ensure that local system
passwords and Samba service passwords do not match.</description>
<rationale>
Typically, administrator access is required when Samba must create user and
system accounts and shares. Domain member servers and standalone servers may
not need administrator access at all. If that is the case, add the invalid
users parameter to <tt>[global]</tt> instead.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27533-9" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="require_smb_client_signing">
<title>Require Client SMB Packet Signing, if using <tt>smbclient</tt></title>
<description>
To require samba clients running <tt>smbclient</tt> to use
packet signing, add the following to the <tt>[global]</tt> section
of the Samba configuration file, <tt>/etc/samba/smb.conf</tt>:
<pre>client signing = mandatory</pre>
Requiring samba clients such as <tt>smbclient</tt> to use packet
signing ensures they can
only communicate with servers that support packet signing.
</description>
<ocil clause="it is not">
To verify that Samba clients running smbclient must use packet signing, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep signing /etc/samba/smb.conf</pre>
The output should show:
<pre>client signing = mandatory</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Packet signing can prevent
man-in-the-middle attacks which modify SMB packets in
transit.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26328-5" />
<oval id="require_smb_client_signing" />
<ref stigid="RHEL-06-000272" srg="SRG-OS-999999" />
</Rule>


<Rule id="mount_option_smb_client_signing">
<title>Require Client SMB Packet Signing, if using mount.cifs</title>
<description>Require packet signing of clients who mount Samba
shares using the <tt>mount.cifs</tt> program (e.g., those who specify shares
in <tt>/etc/fstab</tt>). To do so, ensure signing options (either
<tt>sec=krb5i</tt> or <tt>sec=ntlmv2i</tt>) are used.
<br /><br />
See the <tt>mount.cifs(8)</tt> man page for more information. A Samba
client should only communicate with servers who can support SMB
packet signing.
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not">
To verify that Samba clients using mount.cifs must use packet signing, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep sec /etc/fstab</pre>
The output should show either <tt>krb5i</tt> or <tt>ntlmv2i</tt> in use.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Packet signing can prevent man-in-the-middle
attacks which modify SMB packets in transit.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26792-2" />
<oval id="mount_option_smb_client_signing" />
<ref stigid="RHEL-06-000273" srg="SRG-OS-999999" />
</Rule>

<Group id="smb_disable_printing">
<title>Restrict Printer Sharing</title>
<description>By default, Samba utilizes the CUPS printing service to enable
printer sharing with Microsoft Windows workstations. If there are no printers
on the local system, or if printer sharing with Microsoft Windows is not
required, disable the printer sharing capability by commenting out the
following lines, found in <tt>/etc/samba/smb.conf</tt>:
<pre>[global]
  load printers = yes
  cups options = raw
[printers]
  comment = All Printers
  path = /usr/spool/samba
  browseable = no
  guest ok = no
  writable = no
  printable = yes</pre>
There may be other options present, but these are the only options enabled and
uncommented by default. Removing the <tt>[printers]</tt> share should be enough
for most users.  If the Samba printer sharing capability is needed, consider
disabling the Samba network browsing capability or restricting access to a
particular set of users or network addresses. Set the <tt>valid users</tt>
parameter to a small subset of users or restrict it to a particular group of
users with the shorthand <tt>@</tt>. Separate each user or group of users with
a space. For example, under the <tt>[printers]</tt> share:
<pre>[printers]
  valid users = user @printerusers</pre>
</description>
<rationale>The Samba service is only required for sharing files and printers
with Microsoft Windows workstations, and even then, other options may exist. Do
not use the Samba service to share files between Unix or Linux systems.
</rationale>
</Group>

</Group>
</Group>
