<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Developer_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Developer_Guide-Patching">
	<title>Patch Creation</title>
	<para>.... intro on GitHub pull request system ..... </para>
	<para> </para>
	<section id="sect-Developer_Guide-Patching-maillist">
		<title>Fork SSG </title>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Visit SSG's GitHub webpage at <ulink
						url="https://github.com/OpenSCAP/scap-security-guide"
						>https://github.com/OpenSCAP/scap-security-guide</ulink>. In the top-right
					corner, you will see a button that says "Fork." Click it.</para>
				<para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ch002-Patching-fork.png"/></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>If you're a member of multiple GitHub groups/accounts, you will be asked for
					the fork destination. For most users it is sufficient to fork into their local
					account. To do so, click on your username/icon. For example:</para>
				<para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ch002-Patching-forklocation.png"/></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Congratulations, you've created a localized repository! Any changes you make
					will be localized, consider it your own sandbox. At this point you can 'git
					clone' the source over SSH, HTTPS, or Subversion. </para>
				<para>GitHub dynamically generates the appropriate git URLs, and dynamically
					generates zip-compressed archives should you desire them. In the right-most
					column, near the bottom, you will see the various git clone options:</para>
				<para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ch002-Patching-githubURL.png"/></para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Developer_Guide-Patching-commit">
		<title>Committing to your Local Repository</title>
		<para>... text to describe .... </para>
		<section>
			<title>Edits via GUI</title>
			<para>The GitHub website supports in-line editing of files. This is extremely convenient
				when making small changes, such as fixing typos. When you've found a file in need of
				edits, note the "Edit" button within the file's toolbar:</para>
			<para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ch002-Patching-inline_edits.png"/></para>
			<para>This will bring you to an in-line editor. Make your changes and scroll to the
				bottom of the webpage. You will notice a "Commit Changes" form. The first field is a
				one-line description of the change, while within the second (main body) you are
				expected to provide a detailed description of any changes. Your entries in this
				field should be as concise as possible while providing enough description for a
				community member to properly evaluate your changes, and the logic for making them.
				For example:</para>
			<para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ch002-Patching-GUI_naming_scheme_sample.png"
				/></para>
			<para>Click on "Commit changes," which will push the change to your local
				repository.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Edits via CLI</title>
			<para>As mentioned earlier, GitHub creates a localized git repository, your own personal
				sandbox. Clone the repository locally, then 'git commit' and 'git push' changes as
				you normally would.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Developer_Guide-Patching-ssgproject">
		<title>Issuing Pull Requests</title>
		<para>When you're ready for your patches to be merged upstream, you must issue a "Pull Request." </para>
		<para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Return to your local repositories webpage on GitHub. </para>
					<para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE: </emphasis>If you've created local branches,
						ensure you've selected the appropriate branch that you'd like to submit
						patches against. <emphasis role="italic">For most people, this step can be
							ignored.</emphasis></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Click on "Pull Request," located in the top-right of the frame which lists
						your directory contents:</para>
					<para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ch002-Patching-Pull_Requests.png"/></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>You will be brought to a listing of your commits. Click the green button
						labelled "Create Pull Request":</para>
					<para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ch002-Patching-Create_Pull.png"/></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>You will be requested to input a patch title and description. Be concise,
						but thorough enough for a community member to understand logic behind your
						changes. Paste into the description field testing evidence (e.g. running
						testoval.py on any submitted OVAL, or before/after for remediation
						scripts). </para>
					<para>After completing the form, select "Send pull request":</para>
					<para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/ch002-Patching-Send_Pull_Request.png"
						/></para>
					<para/>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>A community member will review your patch. They will either merge the
						patch upstream, indicate additional changes/documentation needed, or decline
						the patch. You'll automatically be notified via EMail of any status
						updates.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
