<Group id="mounting">
<title>Restrict Dynamic Mounting and Unmounting of
Filesystems</title>
<description>
Linux includes a number of facilities for the automated addition and removal of filesystems on a running system.
These facilities may be necessary in many environments, but this capability also carries some risk -- whether direct risk from allowing users to introduce arbitrary filesystems, or risk that software flaws in the automated mount facility itself could allow an attacker to compromise the system.
<br/><br/>
This command can be used to list the types of filesystems that are available to the currently executing kernel:
<pre>$ find /lib/modules/`uname -r`/kernel/fs -type f -name '*.ko'</pre>
If these filesystems are not required then they can be explicitly disabled in a configuratio file in  <tt>/etc/modprobe.d</tt>.
</description>

<Rule id="service_autofs_disabled" severity="medium">
<title>Disable the Automounter</title>
<description>
The <tt>autofs</tt> daemon mounts and unmounts filesystems, such as user home directories shared via NFS, on demand.
In addition, autofs can be used to handle removable media, and the default configuration provides the cdrom device as <tt>/misc/cd</tt>.
However, this method of providing access to removable media is not common, so autofs can almost always be disabled if NFS is not in use.
Even if NFS is required, it may be possible to configure filesystem mounts statically by editing <tt>/etc/fstab</tt> rather than relying on the automounter.
<br/><br/>
<systemd-service-macro enable="false" service="autofs" />
</description>
<ocil>
<systemd-check-macro enable="false" service="autofs" />
</ocil>
<rationale>Disabling the automounter permits the administrator to
statically control filesystem mounting through <tt>/etc/fstab</tt>.
<br/><br/>
Additionally, automatically mounting filesystems permits easy introduction of
unknown devices, thereby facilitating malicious activity.
</rationale>
<oval id="service_autofs_disabled" />
</Rule>

</Group>
