<!-- partitioning -->
<Group id="installation-storage-partitioning">
<title>Partitioning</title>
<description>
  Separating various locations of the file systems in different partitions allows a more restrictive
  segregation, distinctly from one location to another. Moreover, some native restrictions can be made by
partitioning, such as no hard link between different filesystems, and reduce the corruption impact to the
affected filesystem instead of the entire system. The last gain is to allow a differenciated usage of storage
media, depending on the operational needs (speed, resilience, etc.).
</description>
<reference href="http://www.pathname.com/fhs/">Filesystem Hierarchy Standard</reference>

<Rule id="partition_for_tmp">
<title>Ensure /tmp Located On Separate Partition</title>
<description>
The <tt>/tmp</tt> directory is a world-writable directory used
for temporary file storage. Ensure it has its own partition or
logical volume at installation time, or migrate it using LVM (when non-ephemeral is needed) or use tmpfs if possible.
</description>
<!--
<fixtext ffixref="partition_for_tmp_fix">
  When tmpfs is possible, just add a specific tmpfs line on the <h:code>fstab</h:code> file (or via systemd), and specify the maximum
  associated size by using <h:code>size=</h:code> argument.
</fixtext>
-->
<rationale>
The <tt>/tmp</tt> partition is used as temporary storage by many programs.
Placing <tt>/tmp</tt> in its own partition enables the setting of more
restrictive mount options, which can help protect programs which use it.
</rationale>
<ocil><partition-check-macro part="/tmp "/></ocil>
<ident cce="27173-4" />
<oval id="partition_for_tmp" />
<ref nist="SC-32" />
<tested by="MM" on="20120928"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="partition_for_var">
<title>Ensure /var Located On Separate Partition</title>
<description>The <tt>/var</tt> directory is used by daemons and other system
services to store frequently-changing data. Ensure that <tt>/var</tt> has its own partition
or logical volume at installation time, or migrate it using LVM.
</description>
<ocil><partition-check-macro part="/var "/></ocil>
<rationale>
Ensuring that <tt>/var</tt> is mounted on its own partition enables the
setting of more restrictive mount options. This helps protect
system services such as daemons or other programs which use it.
It is not uncommon for the <tt>/var</tt> directory to contain
world-writable directories installed by other software packages.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26404-4" />
<oval id="partition_for_var" />
<ref nist="SC-32"  />
<tested by="MM" on="20120928"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="partition_for_var_log">
<title>Ensure /var/log Located On Separate Partition</title>
<description>
System logs are stored in the <tt>/var/log</tt> directory.
Ensure that it has its own partition or logical
volume at installation time, or migrate it using LVM.
</description>
<ocil><partition-check-macro part="/var/log "/></ocil>
<rationale>
Placing <tt>/var/log</tt> in its own partition
enables better separation between log files
and other files in <tt>/var/</tt>.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26967-0" />
<oval id="partition_for_var_log" />
<ref nist="AU-9,SC-32" disa="" />
<tested by="MM" on="20120928"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="partition_for_var_log_audit">
<title>Ensure /var/log/audit Located On Separate Partition</title>
<description>
Audit logs are stored in the <tt>/var/log/audit</tt> directory.  Ensure that it
has its own partition or logical volume at installation time, or migrate it
later using LVM. Make absolutely certain that it is large enough to store all
audit logs that will be created by the auditing daemon.
</description>
<ocil><partition-check-macro part="/var/log/audit "/></ocil>
<rationale>
Placing <tt>/var/log/audit</tt> in its own partition
enables better separation between audit files
and other files, and helps ensure that
auditing cannot be halted due to the partition running out
of space.
</rationale>
<ident cce="26971-2" />
<oval id="partition_for_var_log_audit" />
<ref nist="AU-4,AU-9,SC-32" disa=""/>
<tested by="MM" on="20120928"/>
</Rule>

<Rule id="partition_for_home">
<title>Ensure /home Located On Separate Partition</title>
<description>
If user home directories will be stored locally, create a separate partition
for <tt>/home</tt> at installation time (or migrate it later using LVM). If
<tt>/home</tt> will be mounted from another system such as an NFS server, then
creating a separate partition is not necessary at installation time, and the
mountpoint can instead be configured later.
</description>
<ocil><partition-check-macro part="/home "/></ocil>
<rationale>
Ensuring that <tt>/home</tt> is mounted on its own partition enables the
setting of more restrictive mount options, and also helps ensure that
users cannot trivially fill partitions used for log or audit data storage.
</rationale>
<oval id="partition_for_home" />
<ref nist="SC-32" disa="1208" />
<tested by="MM" on="20120928"/>
</Rule>

</Group>
