<Group id="c2s_support" hidden="true">
<title>Documentation to Support C2S/CIS  Mapping</title>
<description>These groups exist to document how the Red Hat Enterprise Linux
product meets (or does not meet) requirements listed in C2S/CIS, for
those cases where Groups or Rules elsewhere in scap-security-guide do
not clearly relate.
</description>

<Rule id="c2s_procedural_requirement">
<title>Procedural Requirement</title>
<rationale>This requirement is procedural, and can not be met through
automated means.</rationale>
<ocil>TBD</ocil>
<description>This requirement is procedural, and can not be met
through automated means.
</description>
<ref cis="" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="c2s_not_OS_applicable">
<title>Not Applicable to Operating System</title>
<rationale>This requirement is not applicable to an operating system.</rationale>
<description>While this requirement is applicable at an information system level, implementation
is not performed within the Operating System.</description>
<ref cis="" /> 
</Rule>

<Rule id="c2s_met_inherently">
<title>Product Meets this Requirement</title>
<rationale>
Red Hat Enterprise Linux meets this requirement through design and implementation.
</rationale>
<ocil>RHEL7 supports this requirement and cannot be configured to be out of
compliance. This is a permanent not a finding.
</ocil>
<description>
This requirement is permanent not a finding. No fix is required.
</description>
<ref cis="" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="apply_to_everything">
<title>Requirement Applies to All Rules</title>
<rationale>The following requirements apply to all rules</rationale>
<description>These are generic requirements, and apply to all rules</description>
<ref cis="" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="cis_xinetd">
<title>Rule Compliance through Removal of xinetd</title>
<rationale>These rules are inherently compliant when xinetd is removed
from the system</rationale>
<description>The upstream CIS guidance is incorrect, stating that xinetd services can be managed through systemctl. The proper way to disable xinetd services, such as chargen-dgram, is to create a <tt>/etc/xinetd.d/SERVICE</tt> file which disables the service. Regardless, these rules are inherently compliant with C2S/CIS policies through the removal of xinetd itself.</description>
<ref cis="2.1.12, 2.1.13, 2.1.14, 2.1.15, 2.1.16, 2.1.17, 2.1.18" />
</Rule>

</Group>
