<Group id="network-wireless">
<title>Wireless Networking</title>
<description>Wireless networking, such as 802.11
(WiFi) and Bluetooth, can present a security risk to sensitive or
classified systems and networks. Wireless networking hardware is
much more likely to be included in laptop or portable systems than
in desktops or servers. 
<br /><br />
Removal of hardware provides the greatest assurance that the wireless
capability remains disabled. Acquisition policies often include provisions to
prevent the purchase of equipment that will be used in sensitive spaces and
includes wireless capabilities. If it is impractical to remove the wireless
hardware, and policy permits the device to enter sensitive spaces as long
as wireless is disabled, efforts should instead focus on disabling wireless capability
via software.</description>

<Group id="wireless_software">
<title>Disable Wireless Through Software Configuration</title>
<description>If it is impossible to remove the wireless hardware
from the device in question, disable as much of it as possible
through software. The following methods can disable software
support for wireless networking, but note that these methods do not
prevent malicious software or careless users from re-activating the
devices.</description>

<Rule id="wireless_disable_in_bios">
<title>Disable WiFi or Bluetooth in BIOS</title>
<description>Some systems that include built-in wireless support offer the
ability to disable the device through the BIOS. This is system-specific;
consult your hardware manual or explore the BIOS setup during
boot.</description>
<rationale>Disabling wireless support in the BIOS prevents easy
activation of the wireless interface, generally requiring administrators
to reboot the system first.
</rationale>
<platform idref="cpe:/a:machine"/>
<ident cce="26878-9" />
<!--TODO:OCIL <oval id="wireless_disable_in_bios" />-->
<ref nist="AC-18(a),AC-18(d),AC-18(3),CM-7" disa="85" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="wireless_disable_interfaces">
<title>Deactivate Wireless Network Interfaces</title>
<description>Deactivating wireless network interfaces should prevent
normal usage of the wireless capability.
<br /><br />
First, identify the interfaces available with the command:
<pre>$ ifconfig -a</pre>
Additionally, the following command may be used to
determine whether wireless support is included for a
particular interface, though this may not always be a clear
indicator:
<pre>$ iwconfig</pre>
After identifying any wireless interfaces (which may have
names like <tt>wlan0</tt>, <tt>ath0</tt>, <tt>wifi0</tt>, <tt>em1</tt> or
<tt>eth0</tt>), deactivate the interface with the command:
<pre>$ sudo ifdown <i>interface</i></pre>
These changes will only last until the next reboot. To
disable the interface for future boots, remove the appropriate
interface file from <tt>/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts</tt>:
<pre>$ sudo rm /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-<i>interface</i></pre>
</description>
<rationale>Wireless networking allows attackers within physical proximity to
launch network-based attacks against systems, including those against local LAN
protocols which were not designed with security in mind.
</rationale>
<ident cce="27057-9" />
<oval id="wireless_disable_interfaces" />
<ref nist="AC-18(a),AC-18(d),AC-18(3),CM-7" disa="85" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="service_bluetooth_disabled" severity="medium">
<title>Disable Bluetooth Service</title>
<description>
<chkconfig-service-macro enable="false" service="bluetooth" />
<pre>$ sudo service bluetooth stop</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the service is configured to run">
To check that the <code>bluetooth</code> service is disabled in system boot configuration, run the following command: 
<pre># chkconfig <code>bluetooth</code> --list</pre>
Output should indicate the <code>bluetooth</code> service has either not been installed or has been disabled at all runlevels, as shown in the example below:
<pre># chkconfig <code>bluetooth</code> --list
<code>bluetooth</code>       0:off   1:off   2:off   3:off   4:off   5:off   6:off</pre> 
</ocil>
<rationale>Disabling the <tt>bluetooth</tt> service prevents the system from attempting
connections to Bluetooth devices, which entails some security risk.
Nevertheless, variation in this risk decision may be expected due to the
utility of Bluetooth connectivity and its limited range.</rationale>
<ident cce="27081-9" />
<oval id="service_bluetooth_disabled" />
<ref nist="AC-18(a),AC-18(d),AC-18(3),CM-7" disa="85,1551" stigid="RHEL-06-000331"
srg="SRG-OS-000034" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="kernel_module_bluetooth_disabled" severity="medium">
<title>Disable Bluetooth Kernel Modules</title>
<description>The kernel's module loading system can be configured to prevent
loading of the Bluetooth module. Add the following to
the appropriate <tt>/etc/modprobe.d</tt> configuration file
to prevent the loading of the Bluetooth module:
<pre>install bluetooth /bin/true</pre>
</description>
<ocil>
<module-disable-check-macro module="bluetooth" />
</ocil>
<rationale>If Bluetooth functionality must be disabled, preventing the kernel
from loading the kernel module provides an additional safeguard against its
activation.</rationale>
<platform idref="cpe:/a:machine"/>
<ident cce="26763-3" />
<oval id="kernel_module_bluetooth_disabled" />
<ref nist="AC-18(a),AC-18(d),AC-18(3),CM-7" disa="85,1551" stigid="RHEL-06-000315"
srg="SRG-OS-000034" />
</Rule>

</Group><!--<Group id="wireless_software">-->
</Group><!--<Group id="network-wireless">-->
