<Group id="accounts-physical">
<title>Protect Physical Console Access</title>
<description>It is impossible to fully protect a system from an
attacker with physical access, so securing the space in which the
system is located should be considered a necessary step. However,
there are some steps which, if taken, make it more difficult for an
attacker to quickly or undetectably modify a system from its
console.</description>

<Group id="bootloader">
<title>Set Boot Loader Password</title>
<description>During the boot process, the boot loader is
responsible for starting the execution of the kernel and passing
options to it. The boot loader allows for the selection of
different kernels - possibly on different partitions or media.
The default Red Hat Enterprise Linux boot loader for x86 systems is called GRUB.
Options it can pass to the kernel include <i>single-user mode</i>, which
provides root access without any authentication, and the ability to
disable SELinux. To prevent local users from modifying the boot
parameters and endangering security, protect the boot loader configuration
with a password and ensure its configuration file's permissions
are set properly.
</description>

<Rule id="bootloader_exists" severity="high">
<title>Verify /boot/grub/grub.conf Exists</title>
<description>The file <tt>/boot/grub/grub.conf</tt> should exist.
</description>
<rationale>
GRUB is a versatile boot loader used by several platforms that 
can provide authentication for access to the system or boot loader.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN008660" />
<oval id="bootloader_exists" />
<ref nist="ECAR-1,ECAR-2,ECAR-3" disa="366" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="file_owner_grub_conf" severity="medium">
<title>Verify /etc/grub.conf User Ownership</title>
<description>The file <tt>/etc/grub.conf</tt> should 
be owned by the <tt>root</tt> user to prevent destruction 
or modification of the file.
<fileowner-desc-macro file="/etc/grub.conf" owner="root"/>
</description>
<ocil><fileowner-check-macro file="/etc/grub.conf" owner="root"/></ocil>
<rationale>
Only root should be able to modify important boot parameters.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN008760" />
<oval id="file_owner_grub_conf" />
<ref nist="ECLP-1" disa="225" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="file_groupowner_grub_conf" severity="medium">
<title>Verify /etc/grub.conf Group Ownership</title>
<description>The file <tt>/etc/grub.conf</tt> should 
be group-owned by the <tt>root</tt> group to prevent 
destruction or modification of the file.
<filegroupowner-desc-macro file="/etc/grub.conf" group="root"/>
</description>
<ocil><filegroupowner-check-macro file="/etc/grub.conf" group="root"/></ocil>
<rationale>
The <tt>root</tt> group is a highly-privileged group. Furthermore, the group-owner of this
file should not have any access privileges anyway.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN008780" />
<oval id="file_groupowner_grub_conf" />
<ref nist="ECLP-1" disa="225" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="file_permissions_grub_conf" severity="medium">
<title>Verify /boot/grub/grub.conf Permissions</title>
<description>File permissions for <tt>/boot/grub/grub.conf</tt> should be set to 600, which
is the default.
<fileperms-desc-macro file="/boot/grub/grub.conf" perms="600"/>
</description>
<ocil clause ="it does not">
To check the permissions of /etc/grub.conf, run the command:
<pre># ls -lL /etc/grub.conf</pre>
If properly configured, the output should indicate the following 
permissions: <tt>-rw-------</tt>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Proper permissions ensure that only the root user can modify important boot
parameters.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN008720" />
<oval id="file_permissions_grub_conf" />
<ref nist="ECLP-1" disa="225" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="file_permissions_extended_grub_conf" severity="medium">
<title>Verify /boot/grub/grub.conf Extended ACLs</title>
<description>The system's boot loader configuration file(s) must 
not have extended ACLs.
</description>
<ocil clause ="it does not">
To check the permissions of /etc/grub.conf, run the command:
<pre># ls -lL /etc/grub.conf</pre>
If properly configured, the output should indicate the following 
permissions: <tt>-rw-------</tt>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Proper permissions ensure that only the root user can modify important boot
parameters.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN008740" />
<oval id="file_permissions_extended_grub_conf" />
<ref nist="ECLP-1" disa="225" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="bootloader_password" severity="high">
<title>Set Boot Loader Password</title>
<description>The grub boot loader should have password protection
enabled to protect boot-time settings.
To do so, select a password and then generate a hash from it by running the following command:
<pre># /sbin/grub-md5-crypt</pre>
When prompted to enter a password, insert the following line into <tt>/etc/grub.conf</tt>
immediately after the header comments. (Use the output from <tt>grub-md5-crypt</tt> as the
value of <b>password-hash</b>):
<pre>password --md5 <b>password-hash</b></pre>
NOTE: To meet FISMA Moderate, the bootloader password MUST differ from the root password.
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not">
To verify the boot loader password has been set and encrypted, run the following command:
<pre># grep password /etc/grub.conf</pre>
The output should show the following:
<pre>password --md5 <b>password-hash</b></pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Password protection on the boot loader configuration ensures
users with physical access cannot trivially alter
important bootloader settings. These include which kernel to use,
and whether to enter single-user mode.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN008700" />
<oval id="bootloader_password" />
<ref nist="IAIA-1,IAIA-2" disa="213" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="bootloader_password_hash" severity="medium">
<title>Set Boot Loader Password Hash</title>
<description>The grub boot loader password should be protected by being hashed with an approved 
hash algorithm, such as md5.
To do so, select a password and then generate a hash from it by running the following command:
<pre># /sbin/grub-md5-crypt</pre>
When prompted to enter a password, insert the following line into <tt>/etc/grub.conf</tt>
immediately after the header comments. (Use the output from <tt>grub-md5-crypt</tt> as the
value of <b>password-hash</b>):
<pre>password --md5 <b>password-hash</b></pre>
NOTE: To meet FISMA Moderate, the bootloader password MUST differ from the root password.
</description>
<ocil clause="it does not">
To verify the boot loader password has been set and encrypted, run the following command:
<pre># grep password /etc/grub.conf</pre>
The output should show the following:
<pre>password --md5 <b>password-hash</b></pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
Password protection on the boot loader configuration ensures
users with physical access cannot trivially alter
important bootloader settings. These include which kernel to use,
and whether to enter single-user mode.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN008710" />
<oval id="bootloader_password_hash" />
<ref nist="IAIA-1,IAIA-2" disa="213" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Rule id="require_singleuser_auth" severity="medium">
<title>Require Authentication for Single User Mode</title>
<description>Single-user mode is intended as a system recovery
method, providing a single user root access to the system by
providing a boot option at startup. By default, no authentication
is performed if single-user mode is selected.
<br /><br />
To require entry of the root password even if the system is
started in single-user mode, add or correct the following line in the
file <tt>/etc/inittab</tt>:
<pre>~:S:wait:/sbin/sulogin</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the output is different">
To check if authentication is required for single-user mode, run the following command:
<pre>$ grep <tt>:S:</tt> /etc/inittab</pre>
The output should be the following:
<pre>~:S:wait:/sbin/sulogin</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
This prevents attackers with physical access from trivially bypassing security
on the machine and gaining root access. Such accesses are further prevented
by configuring the bootloader password.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN000020" />
<oval id="require_singleuser_auth" />
<ref nist="IAIA-1,IAIA-2" disa="213" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="disable_ctrlaltdel_reboot" severity="high">
<title>Disable Ctrl-Alt-Del Reboot Activation</title>
<description>
By default, the system includes the following line in
<tt>/etc/init/control-alt-delete.conf</tt>
to reboot the system when the Ctrl-Alt-Del key sequence is pressed:
<pre>exec /sbin/shutdown -r now "Control-Alt-Delete pressed"</pre>
<br/>
To configure the system to log a message instead of
rebooting the system, alter that line to read as follows:
<pre>exec /usr/bin/logger -p security.info "Control-Alt-Delete pressed"</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="the system is configured to run the shutdown command">
To ensure the system is configured to log a message instead of rebooting the system when 
Ctrl-Alt-Del is pressed, ensure the following line is in <tt>/etc/init/control-alt-delete.conf</tt>:
<pre>exec /usr/bin/logger -p security.info "Control-Alt-Delete pressed"</pre>
</ocil>
<rationale>
A locally logged-in user who presses Ctrl-Alt-Del, when at the console,
can reboot the system. If accidentally pressed, as could happen in
the case of mixed OS environment, this can create the risk of short-term
loss of availability of systems due to unintentional reboot.
In the GNOME graphical environment, risk of unintentional reboot from the
Ctrl-Alt-Del sequence is reduced because the user will be
prompted before any action is taken.
</rationale>
<oval id="disable_ctrlaltdel_reboot" />
<ref nist="ECSC-1" disa="366" />
<ident stig="GEN000000-LNX00580" />
</Rule>

<Group id="screen_locking">
<title>Configure Screen Locking</title>
<description>When a user must temporarily leave an account
logged-in, screen locking should be employed to prevent passersby
from abusing the account. User education and training is
particularly important for screen locking to be effective, and policies
can be implemented to reinforce this.
<br /><br />
Automatic screen locking is only meant as a safeguard for
those cases where a user forgot to lock the screen.</description>

<Group id="gui_screen_locking">
<title>Configure GUI Screen Locking</title>
<description>In the default GNOME desktop, the screen can be locked
by choosing <b>Lock Screen</b> from the <b>System</b> menu.
<br /><br />
The <tt>gconftool-2</tt> program can be used to enforce mandatory
screen locking settings for the default GNOME environment.
The
following sections detail commands to enforce idle activation of the screen saver,
screen locking, a blank-screen screensaver, and an idle
activation time.

<br /><br />
Because users should be trained to lock the screen when they
step away from the computer, the automatic locking feature is only
meant as a backup. The Lock Screen icon from the System menu can
also be dragged to the taskbar in order to facilitate even more
convenient screen-locking.
<br /><br />
The root account cannot be screen-locked, but this should
<!-- TODO: is this still true? -->have no practical effect as the root account should <i>never</i> be used
to log into an X Windows environment, and should only be used to
for direct login via console in emergency circumstances.
<br /><br />
For more information about configuring GNOME screensaver, see
<weblink-macro link="http://live.gnome.org/GnomeScreensaver"/>. For more information about
enforcing preferences in the GNOME environment using the GConf
configuration system, see <weblink-macro link="http://projects.gnome.org/gconf"/> and
the man page <tt>gconftool-2(1)</tt>.</description>

<Value id="inactivity_timeout_value" type="number" operator="equals">
<title>Inactivity timeout</title>
<description>Choose allowed duration of inactive SSH connections, shells, and X sessions</description>
<value>15</value>
<value selector="5_minutes">5</value>
<value selector="10_minutes">10</value>
<value selector="15_minutes">15</value>
</Value>

<Rule id="gconf_gnome_screensaver_idle_delay" severity="medium">
<title>Set GNOME Login Inactivity Timeout</title>
<description>
Run the following command to set the idle time-out value for
inactivity in the GNOME desktop to 15 minutes:
<pre># gconftool-2 \
  --direct \
  --config-source xml:readwrite:/etc/gconf/gconf.xml.mandatory \
  --type int \
  --set /apps/gnome-screensaver/idle_delay 15</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="it is not">
To check the current idle time-out value, run the following command:
<pre>$ gconftool-2 -g /apps/gnome-screensaver/idle_delay</pre>
If properly configured, the output should be <tt>15</tt>. 
</ocil>
<rationale>
Setting the idle delay controls when the
screensaver will start, and can be combined with
screen locking to prevent access from passersby.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN000500-2" />
<oval id="gconf_gnome_screensaver_idle_delay" value="inactivity_timeout_value" />
<ref nist="PESL-1" disa="57" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="gconf_gnome_screensaver_idle_activation_enabled" severity="medium">
<title>GNOME Desktop Screensaver Mandatory Use</title>
<description>
Run the following command to activate the screensaver
in the GNOME desktop after a period of inactivity:
<pre># gconftool-2 --direct \
  --config-source xml:readwrite:/etc/gconf/gconf.xml.mandatory \
  --type bool \
  --set /apps/gnome-screensaver/idle_activation_enabled true</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="it is not">To check the screensaver mandatory use status, run the following command:
<pre>$ gconftool-2 -g /apps/gnome-screensaver/idle_activation_enabled</pre>
If properly configured, the output should be <tt>true</tt>.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Enabling idle activation of the screen saver ensures the screensaver will
be activated after the idle delay.  Applications requiring continuous,
real-time screen display (such as network management products) require the
login session does not have administrator rights and the display station is located in a
controlled-access area.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN000500" />
<oval id="gconf_gnome_screensaver_idle_activation_enabled" />
<ref nist="PESL-1" disa="57" />
</Rule>

<Rule id="gconf_gnome_screensaver_lock_enabled" severity="medium">
<title>Enable Screen Lock Activation After Idle Period</title>
<description>
Run the following command to activate locking of the screensaver
in the GNOME desktop when it is activated:
<pre># gconftool-2 --direct \
  --config-source xml:readwrite:/etc/gconf/gconf.xml.mandatory \
  --type bool \
  --set /apps/gnome-screensaver/lock_enabled true</pre>
</description>
<ocil clause="it is not">
To check the status of the idle screen lock activation, run the following command:
<pre>$ gconftool-2 -g /apps/gnome-screensaver/lock_enabled</pre>
If properly configured, the output should be <tt>true</tt>.
</ocil>
<rationale>
Enabling the activation of the screen lock after an idle period
ensures password entry will be required in order to
access the system, preventing access by passersby.
</rationale>
<ident stig="GEN000500-3" />
<oval id="gconf_gnome_screensaver_lock_enabled" />
<ref nist="PESL-1" disa="57" />
</Rule>

</Group>

<Group id="console_screen_locking">
<title>Configure Console Screen Locking</title>
<description>
A console screen locking mechanism is provided in the
<tt>screen</tt> package, which is not installed by default.
</description>

<Group id="smart_card_login">
<title>Hardware Tokens for Authentication</title>
<description>
The use of hardware tokens such as smart cards for system login
provides stronger, two-factor authentication than using a username/password.
In Red Hat Enterprise Linux servers and workstations, hardware token login
is not enabled by default and must be enabled in the system settings.
</description>

<Rule id="smartcard_auth" severity="medium">
<title>Enable Smart Card Login</title>
<description>
To enable smart card authentication, consult the documentation at:
<ul>
<li><weblink-macro link="https://docs.redhat.com/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/6/html/Managing_Smart_Cards/enabling-smart-card-login.html"/></li>
</ul>
</description>
<ocil clause="non-exempt accounts are not using CAC authentication">
Interview the SA to determine if all accounts not exempted by policy are
using CAC authentication. 
For DoD systems, the following systems and accounts are exempt from using
smart card (CAC) authentication:
<ul>
<li>SIPRNET systems</li> <!-- also any other non-Internet systems? -->
<li>Standalone systems</li>
<li>Application accounts</li>
<li>Temporary employee accounts, such as students or interns, who cannot easily receive a CAC or PIV</li>
<li>Operational tactical locations that are not collocated with RAPIDS workstations to issue CAC or ALT</li>
<li>Test systems, such as those with an Interim Approval to Test (IATT) and use a separate VPN, firewall, or security measure preventing access to network and system components from outside the protection boundary documented in the IATT.</li>
</ul>
</ocil>
<rationale>Smart card login provides two-factor authentication stronger than
that provided by a username/password combination. Smart cards leverage a PKI
(public key infrastructure) in order to provide and verify credentials.
</rationale>
<ref nist="IAIA-1,IAIA-2" disa="768" />
<ident stig="GEN009120" />
</Rule>

</Group>

</Group>
</Group>
</Group>
